<?xml version="1.0" ?><PAPER><mode2 hasDoc="yes" name="S0019103513005058.tmf1" version="elsevier"/>
<TITLE>The formation of sulfate, nitrate and perchlorate salts in the martian atmosphere
</TITLE>
<ABSTRACT>

Highlights
•
<s sid="1"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We model a modified martian atmosphere to calculate deposition fluxes of salts.</text></s>
•
<s sid="2"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Estimated sulfate soil concentrations are consistent with observed sulfate on Mars.</text></s>
•
<s sid="3"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Pernitric acid forms more rapidly in the martian atmosphere than nitric acid.</text></s>
•
<s sid="4"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>An atmospheric origin for perchlorate is precluded (or supplemented by other processes).</text></s>
Abstract
<s sid="5"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In extremely arid regions on Earth, such as the Atacama Desert, nitrate, sulfate and perchlorate salts form in the atmosphere and accumulate on the surface from dry deposition according to diagnostic evidence in their oxygen isotopes.</text></s>
<s sid="6"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Salts of similar oxyanions should have formed in the atmosphere of Mars because of comparable photochemical reactions.</text></s>
<s sid="7"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We use a 1-D photochemical model to calculate the deposition rates of sulfate, nitrogen oxyanions, and perchlorate from Mars' atmosphere, given a plausible range of volcanic fluxes of sulfur- and chlorine-containing gases in the past.</text></s>
<s sid="8"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>To calculate integrated fluxes over time, we assume that throughout the last 3byr (the Amazonian eon), the typical background atmosphere would have been similar to today's cold and dry environment.</text></s>
<s sid="9"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>If the soil has been mixed by impact perturbations to a characteristic depth of ∼2m during this time, given a time-average volcanic flux 0.1% of the modern terrestrial volcanic flux, the model suggests that the soil would have accumulated 1.0-1.7wt.% SO42- and 0.2-0.4wt.% N in the form of pernitrate (peroxynitrate) or nitrate.</text></s>
<s sid="10"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The calculated sulfate concentration is consistent with in situ observations of soils from rovers and landers and orbital gamma ray spectroscopy.</text></s>
<s sid="11"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, nitrates or pernitrates are yet to be detected.</text></s>
<s sid="12"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The modeled formation of perchlorate via purely gas-phase oxidation of volcanically-derived chlorine is insufficient by orders of magnitude to explain 0.4-0.6wt.% ClO4- measured by NASA's Phoenix Lander.</text></s>
<s sid="13"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The far smaller amount of ozone in the martian atmosphere compared to the terrestrial atmosphere and the colder, drier conditions are the cause of lower rates of gas phase oxidation of chlorine volatiles to perchloric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="14"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Our calculations imply that non-gas-phase processes not included in the photochemical model, such as heterogeneous reactions, are likely important for the formation of perchlorate and are yet to be identified.</text></s>
</ABSTRACT>
<BODY>

Introduction
<s sid="15"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>The elemental composition of the martian soil was first determined by X-ray fluorescence spectroscopy on the Viking Landers (VLs), which measured absolute concentrations (Clark et al., 1977).</text></s>
<s sid="16"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Concentrations of elements in what was called the &quot;average deep soil&quot; at the VLs only summed to ∼89%.</text></s>
<s sid="17"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>The missing ∼11% was attributed to bound water (H2O, -OH), carbonates, nitrates, phosphates and oxides, given that some light elements (H, C, N, O plus Li, B, and F) were undetectable while other elements were obscured (Na, P, Cr and Mn) (Clark et al., 1982).</text></s>
<s sid="18"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>How the elements were bound into salts was uncertain, although Mg and S were correlated in duricrust soils, which was interpreted as a cement of magnesium sulfate (Clark, 1993).</text></s>
<s sid="19"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Some of the &quot;missing components&quot; in VL soil analyses have since been detected.</text></s>
<s sid="20"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Orbital thermal infrared spectroscopy showed that 2-5wt.% carbonates are present in the global dust (Bandfield et al., 2003), while thermal evolved gas analysis in soils at the site of the Phoenix Lander revealed 3-6wt.% carbonate (Boynton et al., 2009; Sutter et al., 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="21"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Additionally, thermal evolved gas analysis in soils at the Rocknest location in Gale Crater was consistent with the presence of 1-2% fine-grained siderite and/or magnesite (Leshin et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="22"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Orbital gamma-spectroscopy have also revealed 1.5-7.5wt.% water-equivalent hydrogen near the martian surface (Boynton et al., 2007), and the Sample Analysis at Mars (SAM) instrument suite on the Mars Science Laboratory (MSL) detected evolved H2O consistent with ∼1.5-3wt.% H2O in sand grains at the Rocknest location (Leshin et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="23"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The Wet Chemistry Laboratory (WCL) on the Phoenix Lander provided in situ measurements of the composition of soluble salts in the martian soil.</text></s>
<s sid="24"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Soluble sulfate was present at 1.3±0.5wt.% (Kounaves et al., 2010b), along with cations of sodium, potassium, calcium and magnesium.</text></s>
<s sid="25"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The most surprising result was the presence of perchlorate (ClO4-) at an inferred concentration in the soil of ∼0.5wt.% (Hecht et al., 2009; Kounaves et al., 2010a).</text></s>
<s sid="26"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The dominance of Mg(ClO4)2 is consistent with simulations of evaporation and freezing at the Phoenix landing site (Marion et al., 2010); however, further analysis of data from the WCL suggests that Ca(ClO4)2 may be the dominant form of perchlorate (Kounaves et al., 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="27"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The perchlorate-sensitive electrode in the WCL experiment was also sensitive to nitrate, but it was 1000 times more sensitive to perchlorate.</text></s>
<s sid="28"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Thus, the methodology precluded the detection of nitrate because the signal would have required a mass of nitrate that exceeded the mass of the sample (Hecht et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="29"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Recently, the MSL mission has also confirmed the presence of perchlorate using pyrolysis as part of the SAM experiment (Steininger et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="30"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Specifically, pyrolysis showed release of chloromethane and O2 from heated soil samples at the Rocknest location, which is consistent with the decomposition of perchlorate (Sutter et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="31"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>If all of the evolved O2 was released from perchlorate, then the samples contained a comparable amount of perchlorate to the samples at the Phoenix landing site (Leshin et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="32"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Furthermore, reanalysis of the Viking thermal volatilization experiments suggest ⩽1.6% perchlorate at both Viking 1 and Viking 2 landing sites (Navarro-Gonzalez et al., 2010); however, this has been subject to some debate (Biemann and Bada, 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="33"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Native perchlorate has also recently been measured in the martian meteorite EETA79001, albeit at a level &lt;1ppm by mass (Kounaves et al., 2014).</text></s>
<s sid="34"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Given the various locations of possible detection, perchlorate appears to be ubiquitous on the martian surface.</text></s>
<s sid="35"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Alpha-proton X-ray fluorescence on landers and rovers after the VLs has led to the inference of a global soil unit (Blake et al., 2013; Bruckner et al., 2003; Morris et al., 2010; Rieder et al., 2004; Yen et al., 2013, 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="36"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Soils can have components derived from local rocks but these are imprinted upon a global-scale soil that has characteristic ratios of the concentration of certain elements (Mg, Al, K, Ca and Fe) relative to silicon and also a positive correlation of Cl and S. Given the lander and rover detections of perchlorate, the Cl in this global soil may well be in the form of perchlorate.</text></s>
<s sid="37"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Salts are relevant to the habitability of Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="38"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>First, perchlorate reduction is a metabolism used by some terrestrial bacteria in anaerobic conditions (Coates and Achenbach, 2004).</text></s>
<s sid="39"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>If such organisms exist (or did exist) on Mars, then they could gain energy by reducing perchlorate and oxidizing an electron donor such as organic carbon or ferrous iron.</text></s>
<s sid="40"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>This would require organic molecules to be present on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="41"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Indigenous organic molecules have yet to be confirmed on Mars; however the presence of perchlorate itself may have inhibited the detection of organics on Mars in pyrolysis experiments (Navarro-Gonzalez et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="42"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Second, perchlorate salts are highly deliquescent and significantly lower the freezing point of liquid water (Gough et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="43"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The eutectic point of Mg(ClO4)2 is -57°C (Stillman and Grimm, 2011), while that of Ca(ClO4)2 is -75°C (Pestova et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="44"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Given typical soil salt concentrations, small amounts of water (∼0.02g H2O per g soil) would permit a water activity sufficient for terrestrial life to be viable (Kounaves et al., 2010b).</text></s>
<s sid="45"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Third, if all organisms require fixed nitrogen in proteins and nucleic acids, as they do on Earth, then the discovery of nitrogen oxyanions on Mars would be significant as well.</text></s>
<s sid="46"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Perchlorate may be advantageous to microorganisms, but its impact on human exploration is more complicated.</text></s>
<s sid="47"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot6" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Perchlorate may be harmful because it is potentially toxic to humans if ingested (Urbansky, 2002).</text></s>
<s sid="48"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot7" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>On the other hand, perchlorate could be useful for future exploration of Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="49"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>It is kinetically stable at typical planetary surface temperatures, but at high temperatures perchlorate is a powerful oxidant suitable for rocket propulsion (Trumpolt et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="50"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>So perchlorate could be utilized as an in situ fuel resource for sample return missions and in the eventual human exploration of Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="51"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>On Earth, one source of sulfate, nitrate, and perchlorate salts is atmospheric deposition.</text></s>
<s sid="52"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The salts can build up in extremely arid environments, such as the Atacama Desert in Chile (Catling et al., 2010; Ericksen, 1983) and the Antarctic Dry Valleys (Kounaves et al., 2010c).</text></s>
<s sid="53"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Given the oxic arid environment of Mars, it is possible that the same salts, or similar ones, have formed in the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="54"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>This work estimates the photochemical formation and deposition rates of martian oxyanions, and evaluates the plausibility of atmospheric chemistry as an important source of salts in the global martian soil.</text></s>
<s sid="55"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>This study builds upon the work of Catling et al. (2010), which used a one-dimensional photochemical model to investigate the formation of salts in the terrestrial atmosphere over the Atacama Desert.</text></s>
<s sid="56"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Using purely gas-phase pathways, Catling et al. (2010) reproduced measured profiles of chlorine species in the terrestrial atmosphere and estimated deposition rates of both perchlorate and nitrate that were consistent with Atacama soil measurements.</text></s>
<s sid="57"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Several profound differences, however, alter the photochemistry of Mars relative to Earth, including atmospheric composition, density, and temperature.</text></s>
<s sid="58"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Our results reveal how these differences impact the formation of atmospheric salts on Mars as compared to Earth.</text></s>
<s sid="59"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Background: atmospheric perchlorates, sulfates, and nitrates on Earth versus Mars</text></s>
<s sid="60"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Perchlorates, sulfates, and nitrates are formed in the atmosphere on Earth and by analogy may have formed in the atmosphere of Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="61"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>In this section, we consider how terrestrial pathways of salt formation inform possible mechanisms on Mars.</text></s>
Perchlorate formation
<s sid="62"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Perchlorate salts produced synthetically on Earth can be distinguished from those produced naturally in the atmosphere by virtue of their oxygen and chlorine isotope ratios.</text></s>
<s sid="63"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Synthetic formation creates perchlorate with ordinary mass-dependent oxygen isotope fractionation (i.e. oxygen isotopes are distributed according to the linear relationship, δ17O≈0.52×δ18O).</text></s>
<s sid="64"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Conversely, naturally occurring perchlorate typically contains mass-independently fractionated oxygen isotopes, a deviation defined as Δ17O, where Δ17O=δ17O-0.52×δ18O.</text></s>
<s sid="65"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The known source for Δ17O occurs during ozone formation, leading to stratospheric ozone with 30-40‰ (Thiemens, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="66"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Perchlorate that contains Δ17O thus preserves a telltale signature of a naturally occurring formation pathway involving stratospheric photochemistry.</text></s>
<s sid="67"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Natural perchlorate has been discovered in locations across the globe, including the Atacama Desert (Bao and Gu, 2004), the Antarctic Dry Valleys (Kounaves et al., 2010c), and the American southwest (Jackson et al., 2010; Rajagopalan et al., 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="68"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The Mojave Desert in California and Atacama Desert in Chile have the highest Δ17O values.</text></s>
<s sid="69"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In perchlorate samples from the Mojave Desert, Δ17O=8.6-18.4‰ (Jackson et al., 2010), and in samples from the Atacama Desert, Δ17O=4.2-9.6‰ (Bao and Gu, 2004).</text></s>
<s sid="70"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The occurrence of radioactive 36Cl (produced by cosmic rays acting on atmospheric 36Ar) relative to 37Cl (Sturchio et al., 2009) further confirms a stratospheric source for the chlorine in natural terrestrial perchlorate.</text></s>
<s sid="71"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot8" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>A gas phase pathway for producing perchlorate is through the reaction of halogens with ozone.</text></s>
<s sid="72"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Simonaitis and Heicklen (1975) proposed that perchloric acid, HClO4, forms by:(1)Cl+O3+M→ClO3+M(2)ClO3+OH+M→HClO4+M</text></s>
<s sid="73"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>For this study, we employ Eqs.</text></s>
<s sid="74"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>(1) and (2) as the major pathway to form HClO4.</text></s>
<s sid="75"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>However, the effectiveness of this mechanism has been questioned by Prasad and Lee (1994) based on the slow three-body kinetics.</text></s>
<s sid="76"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In the same study, the authors presented an alternative method of HClO4 formation involving ClO·O3 and ClO·O2 (Prasad and Lee, 1994).</text></s>
<s sid="77"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>ClO·O2 has been detected (Kopitzky et al., 2002), but the existence of ClO·O3 is hypothetical.</text></s>
<s sid="78"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" type="Hyp"/><text>Still, it is possible that other atmospheric reactions may form perchloric acid in addition to, or in place of, Eqs.</text></s>
(1) and (2).
<s sid="79"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Regardless of the formation pathway, HClO4 has been shown to be stable by ab initio methods (Francisco, 1995), and it has been detected in the terrestrial stratosphere (Jaegle et al., 1996).</text></s>
<s sid="80"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In the absence of rain, perchloric acid accumulates on the surface through dry deposition, where it reacts with minerals to form perchlorate salts (Catling et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="81"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Another photochemical pathway to ClO3 that was not investigated by Catling et al. (2010) involves the effect of bromine oxides:(3)BrO+ClO→Br+OClO</text></s>
<s sid="82"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" type="Hyp"/><text>OClO then can form ClO3 by(4)OClO+O3→ClO3+O2</text></s>
<s sid="83"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" type="Hyp"/><text>It is reasonable to assume that when Mars was volcanically active, the atmosphere contained the reactants for the above reactions.</text></s>
<s sid="84"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>There are multiple lines of evidence that volcanoes on Mars emitted both HCl and HBr.</text></s>
<s sid="85"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>First, the inferred composition of the martian mantle is enriched in Cl and Br by more than a factor of two compared with Earth (Wänke and Dreibus, 1994).</text></s>
<s sid="86"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Second, the mineral composition of martian basaltic meteorites is consistent with an enrichment in Cl relative to terrestrial basalts (Filiberto and Treiman, 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="87"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Third, there are elevated bromine levels in soils (Rieder et al., 2004), and recent analysis of Br/Cl ratios in soil profiles at Gusev Crater and Meridiani Planum indicate that bromine gas may have been released from soil to atmosphere by UV photolysis or chemical oxidation (Karunatillake et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="88"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Other ways to form perchlorate</text></s>
In addition to Eqs.
<s sid="89"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>(1) and (4), several other atmospheric reactions form precursors to HClO4; however, their relevance to Mars has not yet been demonstrated.</text></s>
<s sid="90"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>For example, laboratory experiments showed that oxidation of HCl gas by O3 gas produces both chlorate, ClO3-, and perchlorate, ClO4- (Wang, 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="91"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The recovered ClO4- mass was two to three orders of magnitude greater than the recovered ClO3- mass (Wang, 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="92"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, HCl gas was exposed to O3 gas concentrations of 150-180mg/L (Wang, 2011), which are values that far exceed the concentration of O3 in both the terrestrial stratosphere and the martian atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="93"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The Phoenix WCL was not designed to detect chlorate (the ion-sensitive electrode in the WCL has similar sensitivity to chlorate and nitrate, so a signal due mostly to chlorate is precluded).</text></s>
<s sid="94"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>However, it is possible that ClO3- contributed to the perchlorate signal (Hanley et al., 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="95"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Lightning-induced oxidation of NaCl aerosols also produces ClO4-, but the recovered ratio of ClO4-/Cl- is only ∼10-4 by mass (Rao et al., 2012b).</text></s>
<s sid="96"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Phoenix WCL measurements suggest that the ratio of ClO4-/Cl- is ∼15 by mass in the soil (Kounaves et al., 2010b), so the lightning production of perchlorate is not compatible with data.</text></s>
<s sid="97"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Several authors have recently argued that ClO4- can be produced through aqueous and heterogeneous reactions; however, once again, it is unclear how effective such mechanisms would be on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="98"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Decomposition of chlorine-based bleach through UV exposure produces ClO4-, but at low yields ∼10-3% (Rao et al., 2012a).</text></s>
<s sid="99"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Schuttlefield et al. (2011) show that perchlorate is produced by irradiation of titanium-containing crystals in aqueous solutions of chloride.</text></s>
<s sid="100"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The perchlorate can initially be produced 2000 times faster than perchlorate produced via atmospheric oxidation of chlorine volatiles in Catling et al. (2010), but the reaction rate asymptotes and produces only ppm levels of perchlorate in 0.5M solutions of chloride.</text></s>
<s sid="101"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met5" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Additionally, the radiation source used in their experiment, a 100-W xenon lamp, simulates the solar spectrum in space, which greatly exceeds the spectrum at Mars' surface because scattering and absorption by atmospheric gases and dust attenuates the ultraviolet solar flux (Patel et al., 2002).</text></s>
<s sid="102"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In another recent study, CO2-doped chloride-bearing ices were bombarded with electrons, and chlorine oxides, such as ClO2- and ClO3-, formed (Kim et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="103"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>These species can subsequently be oxidized to perchlorate; however, the yield of chlorine-oxides has not been quantified.</text></s>
<s sid="104"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Atmospheric sulfates on Earth and Mars</text></s>
<s sid="105"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>On Earth and Venus, sulfate aerosols form when volcanic SO2 is oxidized and hydrated to form H2SO4 (McGouldrick et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="106"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>On Earth, dry deposition of H2SO4 and subsequent reactions with minerals can form sulfates.</text></s>
<s sid="107"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In fact, sulfates that are found within and near nitrate ore fields of the Atacama have Δ17O=0.4-4‰ (Michalski et al., 2004), which implies a stratospheric source for some of the oxygen molecules bound in the sulfate.</text></s>
<s sid="108"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Settle (1979) suggested that sulfates on Mars would form in the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="109"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Mass independent fractionation of sulfur isotopes in secondary minerals in martian meteorites confirms this hypothesis, as it indicates an atmospheric source for sulfur (Farquhar et al., 2000).</text></s>
<s sid="110"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Additionally, sulfates have been detected across the planet, which could be evidence for atmospheric deposition.</text></s>
<s sid="111"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Apart from salts directly measured in the soil, large mounds of hydrated sulfate have been detected from orbit (Bibring et al., 2006; Murchie et al., 2009a, 2009b).</text></s>
<s sid="112"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Atmospheric sources of the sulfate have been suggested for such sulfate-rich sedimentary deposits in Meridiani Planum (Niles and Michalski, 2009), Valles Marineris troughs, and Juventae Chasma (Catling et al., 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="113"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Nitrates on Earth and Mars</text></s>
<s sid="114"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In the terrestrial atmosphere, nitric acid (HNO3) can form by the reaction of NO2 with OH (Brasseur and Solomon, 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="115"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Deposition of HNO3 forms nitrates.</text></s>
<s sid="116"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Oxygen isotopes in nitrates from the Atacama Desert also indicate a stratospheric source, with Δ17O=14-21‰ (Michalski et al., 2004).</text></s>
<s sid="117"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>While nitrates have not yet been definitively detected on the martian surface, they should naturally form through oxidation of atmospheric N and accumulate on the surface (Mancinelli, 1996).</text></s>
<s sid="118"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In photochemical models of the martian atmosphere, odd nitrogen (N and NO) forms in the thermosphere through photodissociation of N2, recombination of N2+ and NO+, the reaction of N2+ with O, and the reaction of O+(2P) with N2 (Krasnopolsky, 1993; Yung et al., 1977).</text></s>
<s sid="119"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>N and NO then flow into the lower atmosphere (Krasnopolsky, 1993; Yung et al., 1977).</text></s>
<s sid="120"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>These species can then be oxidized to NO2, which then can form nitric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="121"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Previous work showed possible detections of indigenous nitrate in martian meteorite EETA79001 and Nakhla (Grady et al., 1995).</text></s>
<s sid="122"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>A more recent study of EETA79001 suggests a nitrate upper limit of ∼0.5wt.% in a sawdust sample that includes white-gray granular material known as &quot;druse&quot; (Kounaves et al., 2014).</text></s>
<s sid="123"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Nitrate also may have been detected in Gale Crater by the Mars Science Laboratory (Navarro-Gonzalez et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="124"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot9" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>However, the specific amount of nitrate in the soil remains largely unconstrained.Manning et al. (2008) have developed a steady-state model of nitrate decomposition and nitrogen escape in the martian atmosphere in an attempt to estimate the amount of nitrate in martian soil.</text></s>
<s sid="125"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>They calculated a ∼3m-thick global equivalent layer of pure NaNO3on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="126"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The actual inventory; however, is not known.</text></s>
Photochemical model
<s sid="127"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>To investigate chlorine, sulfur, and nitrogen chemistry in the martian atmosphere, we use a one-dimensional photochemical model derived from the model developed by Kasting (1979).</text></s>
<s sid="128"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The model has recently been modified to study chlorine, sulfur, and nitrogen chemistry in the modern terrestrial atmosphere (Catling et al., 2010) and hydrogen, carbon, and oxygen chemistry in the modern martian atmosphere (Zahnle et al., 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="129"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We combine the two models.</text></s>
<s sid="130"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>As part of model development, we matched the calculated mixing ratios of H2O, CO, H2O2, and O2 to those in the modern martian atmosphere (following Zahnle et al., 2008) and then added chlorine and sulfur chemistry from Catling et al. (2010), as discussed in Section 3.1.</text></s>
<s sid="131"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The model uses a 1km vertical grid spacing and solves a time-dependent coupled transport-chemistry equation, as given in Catling et al. (2010).</text></s>
<s sid="132"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The model is stepped forward to steady-state using the reverse Euler method.</text></s>
<s sid="133"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Vertical transport occurs by eddy diffusion for all species, as well as molecular diffusion for H and H2.</text></s>
<s sid="134"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Following the model of Zahnle et al. (2008), atmospheric transport, temperature, and relative humidity are initialized as follows.</text></s>
<s sid="135"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The eddy diffusion coefficient K=106cm2s-1 for altitude z&lt;20km, and K=106N(20km)/N(z)cm2s-1, where N is the atmospheric number density (moleculescm-3), for 20km&lt;z&lt;110km.</text></s>
<s sid="136"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The surface temperature, T0, is set to 211K.</text></s>
<s sid="137"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The atmospheric temperature follows a nominal profile of T=T0-1.4z for z&lt;50km, and T is isothermal for z&gt;50km.</text></s>
<s sid="138"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The relative humidity is set to 17% throughout the entire atmosphere, and the atmospheric composition is set to 95% CO2.</text></s>
<s sid="139"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The modern solar flux at Mars is applied at the top of the model grid.</text></s>
<s sid="140"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>A test to evaluate the effect of the evolution of the solar flux on salt deposition fluxes over the Amazonian eon (3Gyr-present) showed negligible effect (see Section 5.2).</text></s>
<s sid="141"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met6" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Consequently, the nominal model assumes atmospheric Cl, S, and N chemistry is relatively insensitive to the evolving solar flux and uses the modern solar flux.</text></s>
<s sid="142"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met7" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Updates to the photochemical model from Catling et al. (2010) include the incorporation of the delta 2-stream radiative transfer formulation of Toon et al. (1989) and a modification to the Rayleigh scattering cross-section.</text></s>
<s sid="143"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met8" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>The Rayleigh scattering cross-section is computed using the relative gas concentrations at each model height rather than assigning a global cross-section based on the ground level gas concentrations.</text></s>
<s sid="144"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met9" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>These improvements in realism were made primarily for model atmosphere studies involving variable pressure (Misra et al., 2014).</text></s>
<s sid="145"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, they make little difference to results in a thin atmosphere with well-mixed concentrations, such as modern Mars.</text></s>
Model chemistry
<s sid="146"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The nominal chemistry includes gaseous species listed in Table 1 as well as two aerosols: H2SO4 (sulfate) aerosols and S8 (elemental sulfur) aerosols.</text></s>
<s sid="147"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We neglected nitrate aerosols because the model runs in conditions where the partial pressure of HNO3 is insufficient to exceed its saturation vapor pressure based information in Luo et al. (1995).</text></s>
<s sid="148"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The atmospheric chemistry allows for a version of the modern atmosphere, modified by volcanic fluxes, meant to simulate the atmosphere in the mid-Amazonian eon.</text></s>
<s sid="149"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Volcanic fluxes are discussed in Section 3.2.</text></s>
<s sid="150"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The 348 photochemical reactions include those used in Zahnle et al. (2008) and Catling et al. (2010), with the exception of reactions involving CH3Cl, which is produced biologically, and its photochemical products, CH2Cl, CH2ClO2, CH2ClO, and CHClO.</text></s>
<s sid="151"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met10" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>All reaction rates were updated where new rates were available from Sander et al. (2011).</text></s>
<s sid="152"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met11" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>For completeness, we also added one new chlorine reaction not included in Catling et al. (2010): Cl2O2+O3→ClO + ClOO+O2.</text></s>
<s sid="153"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>But the upper limit of the rate constant, k=1×10-19cm3s-1, is slow (Atkinson et al., 2007), so the effect on overall chemistry is negligible.</text></s>
<s sid="154"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A background of 95% carbon dioxide allows for enhanced three-body reaction rates compared to terrestrial air (Lindner, 1988), so rate constants for three-body reactions measured in air are multiplied by a rate of 2.5 following Nair et al. (1994).</text></s>
<s sid="155"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Atmospheric formation of salt-precursors occurs through the injection of volcanic gases (discussed in Section 3.2) and subsequent reactions in the gas-phase.</text></s>
<s sid="156"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Formation of sulfuric acid in the gas-phase occurs by the following reactions (Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006):(5)SO2+OH+M→HOSO2+M(6)HOSO2+O2→HO2+SO3(7)SO3+H2O→H2SO4</text></s>
<s sid="157"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Gas to particle conversion occurs when the saturation vapor pressure of H2SO4 is exceeded.</text></s>
<s sid="158"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The H2O/H2SO4 ratio of the particles is self-consistently predicted.</text></s>
<s sid="159"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Further details of aerosol formation are given in Pavlov et al. (2001).</text></s>
<s sid="160"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>S8 aerosols are formed when S2 polymerizes to form longer sulfur chains.</text></s>
<s sid="161"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Polymerization stops at the stable S8 ring-molecule, which is assumed to condense.</text></s>
<s sid="162"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>S2 is formed by the reaction of HS and S, or, as discussed in Section 3.2, it is injected directly into the atmosphere through volcanism.</text></s>
<s sid="163"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, the nominal model has an oxidizing atmosphere, so S8 is not the relevant fate for S2 molecules.</text></s>
<s sid="164"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Rather, S2 is oxidized to SO, which can be further oxidized to SO2 and H2SO4.</text></s>
<s sid="165"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is consistent with previous work showing that in CO2 atmospheres with low sulfur input and high SO2/H2S, like the atmosphere modeled here, primary sulfur is converted to sulfuric acid more efficiently than it is converted to elemental sulfur (Hu et al., 2013).</text></s>
<s sid="166"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Gas-phase nitric acid is produced by a reaction analogous to Eq. (5):(8)NO2+OH+M→HNO3+M</text></s>
<s sid="167"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Likewise, gas phase pernitric acid is formed by reaction of HO2 and NO2:(9)HO2+NO2+M→HNO4+M</text></s>
<s sid="168"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Perchloric acid forms through reaction (2).</text></s>
<s sid="169"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We also developed a version of the model with bromine chemistry to test whether the effects of interactions between the bromine and chlorine cycles, including Eq.</text></s>
(3), are significant.
<s sid="170"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The bromine-version of the model is discussed in Section 6.</text></s>
<s sid="171"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Volcanism and transport of species at the upper and lower boundaries</text></s>
<s sid="172"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In the model, chlorine and sulfur gases are emitted from volcanoes.</text></s>
<s sid="173"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These gases are the sources of Cl- and S-bearing gases.</text></s>
<s sid="174"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Evidence for volcanism in the Amazonian eon is abundant.</text></s>
<s sid="175"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Evidence includes lava flows dated by crater counts to be no older than 100myr old (Hartmann et al., 1999; Hartmann and Neukum, 2001) and basaltic meteorites that have crystallization ages of less than 1.3Gyr (Nyquist et al., 2001).</text></s>
<s sid="176"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>The composition and emission rates for martian volcanic gases are poorly constrained, so we use nominal estimates from the literature and test the model for sensitivity to their variations.</text></s>
<s sid="177"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We assume a total emission rate that is ∼0.1% of the terrestrial volcanic emission rate used in Catling et al. (2010), which results in ∼106moleculescm-2s-1.</text></s>
<s sid="178"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This factor is consistent with the estimate that the eruption rate of volcanic rocks was ∼103 times lower than contemporary terrestrial emission rates at 1-2Ga (Jakosky and Shock, 1998), assuming that volcanic gas emission rates scale directly with volcanic rock eruption rates.</text></s>
<s sid="179"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We estimate the H-O-C-S composition of volcanic gases using the geochemical model results of Gaillard and Scaillet (2009).</text></s>
<s sid="180"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For HCl, which is not considered by Gaillard and Scaillet (2009), we take the terrestrial arc volcano HCl/SO2 ratio of 0.3 (Pyle and Mather, 2009) and multiply by a factor of 2.</text></s>
<s sid="181"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This factor of 2 is consistent with the chlorine enrichment observed on Mars (Wänke and Dreibus, 1994) and a Cl/La enrichment of ∼2.5 in martian meteorites compared to terrestrial basalts (Filiberto and Treiman, 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="182"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The emission rates of volcanic gases in the nominal model are shown in Table 2.</text></s>
<s sid="183"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>S2 appears as the dominant sulfur gas because SO2 and S2 are favored over H2S at lower pressures (Gaillard and Scaillet, 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="184"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Gaillard and Scaillet (2009) model martian magma as relatively water-poor (0.2wt.%) with a mantle oxygen fugacity of QFM-2 (2 log units below the quartz-fayalite-magnetite redox buffer).</text></s>
<s sid="185"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>These combined conditions favor S2 over SO2 (Gaillard and Scaillet, 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="186"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Emissions are distributed evenly between the middle of the second atmospheric layer, 1.5km, and 20km in the model (the troposphere and lower stratosphere).</text></s>
<s sid="187"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Most gases are removed from the atmosphere to the surface according to a prescribed deposition velocity.</text></s>
<s sid="188"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The deposition velocity is a scaling factor that affects the transport of species from the bulk atmosphere to the surface in the absence of rain.</text></s>
<s sid="189"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The deposition velocity is coupled to the gas concentrations computed by chemical kinetics.</text></s>
<s sid="190"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Following Zahnle et al. (2008), we apply a deposition velocity of 0.02cms-1 to all species, with two exceptions.</text></s>
<s sid="191"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>First, the deposition velocities for O2, H2, and CO are set to zero (following Zahnle et al., 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="192"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Second, all species with a zero deposition velocity in Catling et al. (2010) are prescribed a zero deposition velocity because we consider them to be nonreactive.</text></s>
<s sid="193"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These species include NO3, N2O5, N2O, CH3O, CH3ONO, CH3ONO2, CH2ONO2, CH3O2, CH3OH, CH2OOH, Cl2, CH2OH, CH2O2, OClO, ClOO, ClONO, ClNO, ClNO2, CH3OCl, Cl2O2, Cl2O, ClO3, and Cl2O4.</text></s>
<s sid="194"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The deposition velocity multiplied by the species number density at the lower boundary, in addition to the flux term from eddy diffusion, determines the flux of species to the surface.</text></s>
<s sid="195"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The photochemical model simulates chemistry up to 110km, so upper boundary conditions, for certain species, must be applied to account for chemistry that takes place above the vertical bounds of the model.</text></s>
<s sid="196"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As mentioned previously, both N and NO precipitate into the neutral atmosphere from the ionosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="197"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The ionosphere is not explicitly modeled here, so the nominal input of odd-nitrogen at 110km is set to 2×106moleculesNcm-2s-1 and 2×107moleculesNOcm-2s-1 (Krasnopolsky, 1993).</text></s>
<s sid="198"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We vary these rates later to test model sensitivity.</text></s>
<s sid="199"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Additionally, following Zahnle et al. (2008), atomic oxygen is lost at the top of the model at a rate of 107moleculescm-2s-1.</text></s>
<s sid="200"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This rate is consistent with literature estimates (Fox and Hac, 1997; Lammer et al., 2003).</text></s>
<s sid="201"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Additionally, CO flows into the top of the model at a rate of 2×107moleculescm-2s-1 in order to maintain redox balance, and hydrogen escapes at the diffusion-limited rate (Zahnle et al., 2008).</text></s>
Methods
<s sid="202"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>We employ two groups of sensitivity tests to determine the effect of changing model parameters on the deposition rate of salt precursors.</text></s>
<s sid="203"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The purpose of the first group of tests (Section 4.1) is to quantify the sensitivity of perchloric acid, (per)nitric acid, and sulfate aerosol deposition to a subset of upper and lower boundary conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="204"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These include the solar flux; the input of Cl, N, and S atoms; and the deposition velocities of Cl and S atoms.</text></s>
<s sid="205"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We will use the results to calculate the possible range of integrated salt deposition fluxes over the Amazonian eon.</text></s>
<s sid="206"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res73" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The purpose of the second group of sensitivity tests (Section 4.2) is to figure out why the deposition rate of perchloric acid is different on Mars and Earth.</text></s>
<s sid="207"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res74" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Several atmospheric parameters differ significantly between Mars and Earth.</text></s>
<s sid="208"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res75" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We choose three parameters: surface temperature, pressure, and O2 mixing ratio, and vary them to see how each one affects the deposition rate of perchloric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="209"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res76" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity tests: upper and lower boundary conditions</text></s>
<s sid="210"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We vary unconstrained boundary conditions, including volcanic emission rates, deposition velocities, and precipitation of odd nitrogen from above the model's upper boundary.</text></s>
<s sid="211"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>But first we test the model's sensitivity to the solar flux at the top of the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="212"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res77" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity test #1: evolution of solar flux</text></s>
<s sid="213"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res78" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We apply a parameterization of the evolution of the solar flux (from Claire et al., 2012) to the nominal model to quantify changes in deposition fluxes over time.</text></s>
<s sid="214"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res79" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity test #1: volcanic emissions</text></s>
<s sid="215"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met12" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We vary the total volcanic emission rate from ∼106moleculescm-2s-1 to ∼108moleculescm-2s-1, or in other words, 0.1-10% of the terrestrial volcanic flux used in Catling et al. (2010).</text></s>
<s sid="216"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Throughout this range, we also vary the HCl/SO2 from the nominal case of 0.6, up to 60.</text></s>
<s sid="217"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Sensitivity test #2: deposition velocities</text></s>
<s sid="218"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The deposition velocity used in the nominal model is not a measured value.</text></s>
<s sid="219"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res80" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Rather, it is best understood as a fitting parameter tuned to reproduce CO, O2, and H2 abundances on modern Mars, valid as a global average on a 105year time scale.</text></s>
<s sid="220"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res81" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Deposition velocities could have been different at other times and for other conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="221"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res82" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We complete two model simulations in which two key deposition velocities are changed.</text></s>
<s sid="222"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res83" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>First, we set the deposition velocity of SO2, which competes with sulfate aerosol deposition, to zero.</text></s>
<s sid="223"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res84" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Second, we set the deposition velocity of HCl, which competes with HClO4 deposition, to zero.</text></s>
<s sid="224"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res85" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity test #3: input of odd nitrogen</text></s>
<s sid="225"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res86" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Nitrogen input from the upper atmosphere almost entirely controls the rate of nitrate deposition to the surface.</text></s>
<s sid="226"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>At the upper boundary of the model, we vary the odd nitrogen (N and NO) input from the ionosphere because the fluxes we assume in the nominal model are uncertain (Krasnopolsky, 1993).</text></s>
<s sid="227"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We simulate the atmosphere under the following fluxes (in moleculescm-2s-1): NO=2.0×107 and N=2.0×106; NO=2×104 and N=2×103; NO=2×103 and N=2×102; and NO=2×102 and N=20.</text></s>
<s sid="228"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Sensitivity tests: temperature, pressure, and oxygen mixing ratio</text></s>
<s sid="229"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>We vary the atmospheric pressure, temperature, and O2 mixing ratio to understand how these three parameters affect the deposition rate of perchloric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="230"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>Specifically, we want to answer the question: How does the different atmospheric state on Mars and Earth affect the perchloric acid deposition flux on each planet?</text></s>
<s sid="231"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met13" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We start from the nominal model for Mars and then shift each parameter, separately, to more Earth-like values.</text></s>
<s sid="232"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res87" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>From here, we can see how the perchloric acid deposition flux either approaches or diverges from the calculated perchloric acid deposition flux on Earth of ∼105moleculescm-2s-1 (Catling et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="233"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res88" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These tests are not meant to represent physically plausible scenarios.</text></s>
<s sid="234"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res89" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For example, temperature and pressure are varied independently, and the O2 mixing ratio is increased.</text></s>
<s sid="235"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res90" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This latter change implicitly assumes there is a source of O2 at the surface.</text></s>
<s sid="236"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res91" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Therefore, our interpretations are qualitative.</text></s>
Sensitivity test #4: temperature
<s sid="237"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res92" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Atmospheric temperatures affect photochemical rate constants and atmospheric water vapor content.</text></s>
<s sid="238"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>These, in turn, affect the chain of reaction rates that lead to the oxidation of Cl to form HClO4.</text></s>
<s sid="239"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>To pinpoint how atmospheric temperatures alter reaction rates, we shift the nominal Mars temperature profile to higher surface temperatures.</text></s>
<s sid="240"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res93" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The shape of the profile is preserved, but the surface temperature is increased from 211K to 284K (a temperature increase of ∼35%), with the latter temperature being more representative of surface temperatures on Earth.</text></s>
<s sid="241"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res94" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity test #5: surface pressure</text></s>
<s sid="242"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res95" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Photochemical reaction rates are density-dependent; therefore, we vary the surface pressure from the nominal value of 6.3mb to 35mb.</text></s>
<s sid="243"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res96" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This pressure is as high as the surface pressure can be taken without the model entering a CO-runaway as described in Zahnle et al. (2008).</text></s>
<s sid="244"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res97" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity test #6: oxygen concentration</text></s>
<s sid="245"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res98" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The formation rate of perchloric acid in Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="246"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res99" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(2) is dependent upon the atmospheric abundances of Cl and O3, in addition to the rate constant.</text></s>
<s sid="247"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa7" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>In Section 4.1.2, we described a test to determine the sensitivity of perchloric acid formation to Cl volcanic input, so for the last sensitivity test, we vary the O2 mixing ratio to determine sensitivity to the abundance of O2 and its photochemical product, O3.</text></s>
<s sid="248"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met14" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>In the nominal model, the O2 mixing ratio is calculated as model output; however for this test, the O2 mixing ratio is fixed as model input.</text></s>
<s sid="249"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>While holding the surface pressure constant, the O2 mixing ratio is increased by a factor of ten starting from its value in the nominal model, 1.6×10-3.</text></s>
Results
<s sid="250"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Photochemical products of CO2 and H2O dominate the nominal model atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="251"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res100" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The volcanic input is low, and therefore the atmosphere remains highly oxidizing.</text></s>
<s sid="252"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res101" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The net redox imbalance of the atmosphere, pOx=2pO2-pCO-pH2, is 15μbar (as defined in Zahnle et al., 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="253"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Dominant chlorine, sulfur, and nitrogen gases are HCl, SO2, and NO, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="254"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The mixing ratio profiles are plotted in Fig. 1.</text></s>
<s sid="255"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Additionally, the production profiles of salt precursors are plotted in Fig. 2.</text></s>
<s sid="256"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res102" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>HNO3, HNO4, and sulfate aerosol (SO4 AER) production primarily occurs close to the surface, while HClO4 production primarily occurs aloft where the O3 abundance is highest.</text></s>
<s sid="257"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Below we describe results from the sensitivity tests to assess the role of variables in salt formation and deposition on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="258"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Deposition fluxes in the nominal Mars model</text></s>
<s sid="259"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res103" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The deposition fluxes of perchloric acid, sulfate aerosols, nitric acid, and pernitric acid in the nominal Mars model are listed in Table 3.</text></s>
<s sid="260"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res104" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We assume that salts form from the acids upon deposition to the surface.</text></s>
<s sid="261"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res105" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We next make several assumptions to calculate the concentration of salts that have accumulated in the soil during the Amazonian eon.</text></s>
<s sid="262"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res106" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We first assume that perchloric acid, sulfate aerosols, nitric acid and pernitric acid have accumulated at a uniform rate.</text></s>
<s sid="263"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res107" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This assumption is valid because the lack of aqueous minerals and very low weathering rates tell us the Amazonian eon on Mars has been characterized by a climate and atmosphere not greatly different from today (Bibring et al., 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="264"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We next assume a range of soil mixing depths so that salts are distributed throughout the soil column.</text></s>
<s sid="265"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>According to Zent (1998), small post-Noachian impactors have churned the soil on Mars to a 1/e mixing depth of 0.51-0.85m.</text></s>
<s sid="266"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Taking three e-folding depths, the range would be 1.5-2.6m depth, with a mean ∼2m.</text></s>
<s sid="267"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The last assumption we make is that the soil density is 1gcm-3 (Moore and Jakosky, 1989).</text></s>
<s sid="268"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Using these assumptions, we calculate the concentrations of anions in the soil for the nominal model and report them in Table 4.</text></s>
<s sid="269"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These anions must be combined into salts.</text></s>
<s sid="270"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res108" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For perchlorate, the salts may be Mg(ClO4)2 or Ca(ClO4)2 as discussed earlier.</text></s>
<s sid="271"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res109" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The dominant nitrogen-bearing salt is unknown.</text></s>
<s sid="272"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res110" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The sulfate deposition flux produced in the nominal model is compatible with estimates of the amount of sulfates on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="273"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res111" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The nominal range (1.0-1.7wt.% SO4) is consistent with 1.3wt.% soluble sulfate measured at the Phoenix landing site (Kounaves et al., 2010b).</text></s>
<s sid="274"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res112" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The estimates also compare well with an average ∼6.8wt.% sulfur as SO3 (2.7wt.% S) in global soil inferred from elemental abundances measured at various locations on Mars by Spirit, Opportunity, Pathfinder, and Viking Landers.</text></s>
<s sid="275"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res113" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We can also compare the average sulfur content in the top few tens of centimeters of the soil of ∼4.4wt.% inferred from Gamma Ray Spectrometer measurements (King and McLennan, 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="276"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res114" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The agreement between model results and data suggest that 0.1% of the terrestrial volcanic gas flux is a good estimate for the volcanic emission rate on Mars 1-2Ga if soil salts derive from volcanic input.</text></s>
<s sid="277"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res115" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Deposition of pernitric acid, HO2NO2 or HNO4, exceeds deposition of nitric acid, HNO3, contrary to the case on Earth.</text></s>
<s sid="278"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res116" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Production of HNO4 is enhanced at lower temperatures because the rate constant of Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="279"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res117" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(9) is inversely related to temperature.</text></s>
<s sid="280"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res118" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The same is true for the rate constant of Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="281"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res119" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(8), but the HNO3 abundance is depressed at lower temperatures due to the lower abundance of OH.</text></s>
<s sid="282"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res120" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>OH is produced by the photolysis of water vapor and the reaction of H2O with O(1D), but the water vapor abundance is lower at lower temperatures.</text></s>
<s sid="283"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res121" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Implications of enhanced deposition of HNO4 on Mars, compared with Earth, will be discussed in a separate paper about N deposition on Mars (Catling et al., in preparation).</text></s>
<s sid="284"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res122" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>There is no confirmed nitrate on Mars, so we compare the results to an estimate of N on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="285"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res123" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The integrated deposition flux of HNO4 in the model corresponds to an evenly-distributed global layer of NO4 with a mass of 4.3×1018g, which is far smaller than the NO3 mass of 7.2±3.6 (×1020) calculated by Manning et al. (2008).</text></s>
<s sid="286"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res124" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>If the concentration of N predicted here are correct, then they could be below the detection limit for near-infrared orbital instruments, which may explain why nitrates have not yet been observed.</text></s>
<s sid="287"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res125" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The model-inferred abundances of perchlorate are far smaller than observations, however.</text></s>
<s sid="288"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res126" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>If we assume the soil is mixed to an average depth of 2m and the parent salt is Ca(ClO4)2 or Mg(ClO4)2, then we calculate concentrations of 4.3×10-8wt.% and 4.0×10-10wt.%, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="289"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res127" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These concentrations are both many orders of magnitude lower than the observed abundance at the Phoenix landing site: 0.4-0.6wt.% (Hecht et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="290"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res128" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Also, the concentrations are far below what would be inferred from observations of perchlorate:nitrate ratios ∼1:60 measured in EETA79001 (Kounaves et al., 2014) and the Atacama perchlorate:nitrate of ∼1:1000.</text></s>
<s sid="291"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res129" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Distinct from the results for Earth where gas phase reactions were sufficient to reproduce data (Catling et al., 2010), we conclude that additional heterogeneous reactions must be present to account for the efficient formation of perchlorate on Mars, a hypothesis we discuss further in Section 7.</text></s>
<s sid="292"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res130" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>But first we explore the sensitivity of deposition fluxes to model parameters.</text></s>
<s sid="293"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res131" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity of salt deposition to solar flux evolution</text></s>
<s sid="294"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res132" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The effect of an evolving solar flux from Claire et al. (2012) on the salt deposition fluxes was negligible (Fig. 3).</text></s>
<s sid="295"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res133" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Consequently, we set the solar flux to be the modern solar flux for the rest of the simulations.</text></s>
<s sid="296"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res134" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity of salt deposition fluxes to volcanic input</text></s>
<s sid="297"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res135" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We next calculated the perchlorate, sulfate, and nitrate deposition fluxes on Mars as a function of volcanic input.</text></s>
<s sid="298"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res136" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The total volcanic emission rate was increased from the nominal case (∼106moleculescm-2s-1) to one hundred times this value to reflect possible higher rates of volcanism on Mars in the past.</text></s>
<s sid="299"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res137" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>At the same time, we tested the effect of increasing the HCl/SO2 ratio, given that the value is uncertain.</text></s>
<s sid="300"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res138" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We completed two simulations, one with HCl/SO2=0.6, and another with HCl/SO2=60.</text></s>
<s sid="301"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res139" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The deposition fluxes of sulfate aerosols and perchloric acid are both sensitive to volcanic input (Fig. 4).</text></s>
<s sid="302"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res140" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, at the highest level of volcanic input, the deposition fluxes of both species are incompatible with observations.</text></s>
<s sid="303"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res141" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>First, we consider the largest deposition flux of sulfate aerosols.</text></s>
<s sid="304"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res142" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This value occurs at a volcanic input of 100 times the nominal value.</text></s>
<s sid="305"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res143" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We use the same range of mixing depths as we did in the previous section (1.5-2.6m) to calculate a concentration of 100-173wt.% sulfate in the soil.</text></s>
<s sid="306"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res144" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This range is incompatible with observations of sulfur on Mars described in Section 5.1, and values greater than 100wt.% indicate that sulfate deposition is unrealistically high when the mixing depth is restricted to 1.5m.</text></s>
<s sid="307"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res145" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Second, we consider the largest deposition flux of perchloric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="308"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res146" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This value occurs at a volcanic input of 100 times the nominal value and the HCl/SO2 emission flux ratio of 60.</text></s>
<s sid="309"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res147" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Once again, we use a range of mixing depths of 1.5-2.6m to calculate the concentration of ClO4- in the soil.</text></s>
<s sid="310"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res148" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The range is 6.1×10-6-1.0×10-5wt.% ClO4-, which again is incompatible with the measurement of ∼0.5wt.% ClO4- made by the Phoenix Lander (Hecht et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="311"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res149" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity of pernitrate and nitrate deposition flux to odd nitrogen input</text></s>
<s sid="312"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res150" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As stated previously, there is considerable uncertainty in the input rate of odd nitrogen (N and NO) species from the martian ionosphere to the neutral atmosphere (Krasnopolsky, 1993).</text></s>
<s sid="313"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res151" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In his own model of the neutral atmosphere, Krasnopolsky considers cases both with and without input of odd nitrogen from the upper atmosphere (Krasnopolsky, 1993).</text></s>
<s sid="314"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res152" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We vary the input of N and NO into the model, using the nominal case as an upper limit.</text></s>
<s sid="315"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res153" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As these values are decreased, the pernitrate deposition flux drops, which is shown in Fig. 5.</text></s>
<s sid="316"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res154" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The lowest input of odd nitrogen corresponds to 3.5-6.1 (×10-4)wt.% N accumulated over 3byr and mixed into 1.5-2.6m of soil.</text></s>
<s sid="317"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res155" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity of salt deposition flux to deposition velocities</text></s>
<s sid="318"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res156" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Perchloric acid and sulfate aerosols are minor sinks of chlorine and sulfur in the nominal model (Table 5).</text></s>
<s sid="319"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res157" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>To calculate upper limits on the deposition of sulfate aerosols and HClO4, we separately turned off the deposition velocity of its main competitors.</text></s>
<s sid="320"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>First we set the deposition velocity of SO2 to zero, and then we set the deposition velocity of HCl to zero.</text></s>
<s sid="321"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The modified sinks of chlorine and sulfur are listed in Table 6.</text></s>
<s sid="322"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res158" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>When the SO2 deposition velocity is zero, ∼98% of the input sulfur exits the atmosphere as sulfate aerosols.</text></s>
<s sid="323"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res159" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We repeat the calculation from Section 5.1 and find that this corresponds to 2.9-5.0wt.% SO4 accumulated over 3byr mixed into 1.5-2.6m of soil.</text></s>
<s sid="324"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res160" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>When the HCl deposition velocity is zero, the major surface sink of chlorine is HOCl.</text></s>
<s sid="325"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res161" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>HClO4 deposition increases by about four orders of magnitude from the nominal model.</text></s>
<s sid="326"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res162" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This flux corresponds to 6.9×10-5-1.2×10-4wt.% ClO4- accumulated over 3byr mixed into 1.5-2.6m of soil.</text></s>
Temperature
<s sid="327"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res163" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>To semi-quantitatively assess the sensitivity of the deposition fluxes of salts to temperature, we forced the model temperature profile to higher values by increasing the temperature profile by 35% in 5% increments.</text></s>
<s sid="328"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res164" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Warmer temperatures significantly increase the formation of perchloric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="329"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res165" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Over the range tested, the deposition rate of perchloric acid increases by around six orders of magnitude.</text></s>
<s sid="330"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>As the atmospheric temperature increases, the chemistry begins to favor the deposition of HClO4 over HCl.</text></s>
<s sid="331"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res166" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>At higher temperatures, there is more H2O in the atmosphere, which is set by the atmospheric temperature.</text></s>
<s sid="332"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res167" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>More water vapor decreases CO and increases OH, while O2 concentrations are relatively insensitive to H2O abundance (Zahnle et al., 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="333"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res168" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>OH reacts with ClO3, through Eq.</text></s>
(2), to produce HClO4.
<s sid="334"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>HCl production increases at warmer temperatures because of increased amounts of HO2 (O+OH→H+O2 makes O2, H+O2+M→HO2+M makes HO2, and HO2+Cl→HCl+O2 makes HCl).</text></s>
<s sid="335"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, the destruction of HCl through HCl+OH→Cl+H2O also increases; hence the chemistry favors HClO4 deposition over HCl deposition.</text></s>
<s sid="336"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res169" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is shown in Fig. 6.</text></s>
Pressure
<s sid="337"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res170" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Increasing the surface pressure from 6.3mb to 35mb decreases the deposition rate of atmospheric perchlorate from 4.6×10-3 to 7×10-5moleculescm-2s-1.</text></s>
<s sid="338"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res171" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We did not continue to increase the surface pressure up to Earth-like pressures because a build-up of CO causes the atmosphere to become progressively more reduced, which only further decreases the formation of oxidized salt-precursors.</text></s>
<s sid="339"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res172" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In thicker CO2 atmospheres, the significance of H2O vapor photolysis is reduced, and the OH mixing ratio decreases.</text></s>
<s sid="340"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This, in turn, reduces the oxidation of CO via CO+OH→H+CO2 and the production of O2 via O+OH→H+O2.</text></s>
<s sid="341"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>As a consequence, the redox state of a more dense atmosphere becomes more reducing because the reducing gas CO is favored over the oxidizing gas O2.</text></s>
<s sid="342"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res173" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This behavior was also recognized, and is detailed further, in Zahnle et al. (2008).</text></s>
<s sid="343"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res174" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A more reduced atmosphere is less amenable to perchloric acid production (Fig. 7).</text></s>
Chemistry: oxygen concentration
<s sid="344"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res175" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Changing the chemical composition of the atmosphere affects the perchlorate production and deposition rate.</text></s>
<s sid="345"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res176" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A lower concentration of atmospheric ozone on Mars compared with Earth inhibits the production of perchloric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="346"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res177" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As shown in Fig. 8, increasing the O2 mixing ratio from the level in the nominal model, while holding the total atmospheric pressure constant, causes a significant increase in the O3 column density.</text></s>
<s sid="347"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This, in turn, causes the perchlorate deposition flux to increase by around four orders of magnitude.</text></s>
<s sid="348"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>While a larger O2 mixing ratio may not represent a specific past time on Mars, the results demonstrate that lower O2 and O3 concentrations limit the production of HClO4 in the nominal model.</text></s>
<s sid="349"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res178" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For comparison, on Earth, a typical O3 column density is ∼8×1018moleculesO3cm-2.</text></s>
Bromine chemistry
<s sid="350"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In one simulation, we included volcanogenic bromine, in the form of HBr.</text></s>
<s sid="351"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res179" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Bromine interacts with chlorine cycles through Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="352"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res180" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(3) and various other reactions.</text></s>
<s sid="353"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot10" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>The addition of gas phase bromine chemistry makes the model more complete and introduces known chemistry that may affect formation of perchloric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="354"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Adding bromine chemistry involved a number of steps.</text></s>
<s sid="355"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac60" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>First we added bromine chemistry (see Appendix A) to the model of Catling et al. (2010) for the terrestrial atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="356"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac61" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The model was validated against data, further details of which are given in Appendix A.</text></s>
<s sid="357"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac62" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>After validation, we then added inorganic bromine chemistry to the nominal Mars model.</text></s>
<s sid="358"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac63" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The terrestrial arc volcano HCl/HBr emission flux ratio of ∼103 (Pyle and Mather, 2009) was applied, and two more cases with HCl/HBr=100 and HCl/HBr=10 were run, to determine if more HBr affected HClO4 production.</text></s>
<s sid="359"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac64" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>We note, again, that recent work indicates bromine gas may have been released to the atmosphere by volatilization of soil-derived bromine (Karunatillake et al., 2013), but the flux is not quantified, so we do not consider this source here.</text></s>
<s sid="360"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res181" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>When we include inorganic bromine chemistry, the effect on the deposition flux of perchloric acid is negligible.</text></s>
This is because Eqs.
<s sid="361"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res182" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(3) and (4) occur at slower rates than other reactions, involving species from the nominal model, that form OClO and ClO3 (Table 7).</text></s>
Discussion
<s sid="362"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The model results show that atmospheric dry deposition can plausibly explain typical abundances of a several wt.% sulfate observed in soils on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="363"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The model also predicts nitrogen amounts, as nitrates or pernitrates, at levels on the order of 0.1wt.%, assuming these species do not react or decompose.</text></s>
<s sid="364"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Perchlorate is formed very slowly through the gas phase atmospheric chemistry that is modeled here.</text></s>
<s sid="365"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>For the nominal case, we calculate a ClO4- concentration of 2.8-4.8 (×10-8)wt.%, which is a factor of 107 less than the measurement made by the WCL instrument on the Phoenix Lander (Hecht et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="366"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res183" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>With regard to perchlorate, the sensitivity tests revealed that changing the model boundary conditions did not increase perchloric acid deposition rates substantially.</text></s>
<s sid="367"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res184" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The inclusion of bromine gas phase photochemistry has negligible effect on perchlorate fluxes.</text></s>
<s sid="368"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res185" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sensitivity tests revealed two primary causes of the lower perchlorate fluxes from gas phase reactions on Mars relative to Earth: lower amounts of ozone and colder, drier air.</text></s>
<s sid="369"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The much smaller amounts of ozone in the martian atmosphere compared to the terrestrial atmosphere (Fig. 8) are important because ozone is critical for the gas phase formation reactions of precursors to perchloric acid, Eqs.</text></s>
(1) and (4).
<s sid="370"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In addition, the colder and drier air results in a smaller concentration of OH radicals needed in the three-body reaction to make perchloric acid, Eq. (2).</text></s>
<s sid="371"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The purpose of the sensitivity tests was not to model a physically plausible environment on Mars; however, the tests revealed that no one factor could perturb the nominal model to produce amounts of perchlorate that approach the amount measured by the Phoenix Lander.</text></s>
<s sid="372"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>A combination of such factors, including reduced odd nitrogen fluxes, higher oxygen mixing ratios, and increased temperatures may have worked in concert to produce larger perchlorate:nitrate ratios.</text></s>
<s sid="373"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Specifically, if odd nitrogen downward fluxes and oxygen escape rates are smaller than currently thought, nitrate fluxes would drop while perchlorate fluxes would increase.</text></s>
<s sid="374"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In conjunction, as the surface temperature warms toward 280K (as it does in the current equatorial summer) local perchlorate production fluxes could increase further.</text></s>
<s sid="375"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>While it is possible to tweak the photochemical model into this mode, it is difficult to imagine a self-consistent scenario where all of these processes are working in concert to create high perchlorate:nitrate and perchlorate:chloride ratios on Mars, so we favor an additional source for perchlorate.</text></s>
<s sid="376"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We suggest that gas-solid reactions are probably critical for enhancing the transformation of chlorides to perchlorate on Mars.</text></s>
<s sid="377"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Many important reactions in terrestrial atmospheric chemistry are heterogeneous.</text></s>
<s sid="378"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con34" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The most famous example is that the Antarctic ozone hole could not be explained until models incorporated the heterogeneous chlorine chemistry that occurs on very cold particles (Solomon, 1999).</text></s>
<s sid="379"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con35" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Another possibility is that perchlorate was formed in the past by heterogeneous reactions on atmospheric sulfate aerosols.</text></s>
<s sid="380"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con36" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Small amounts of HClO4 have been produced in the laboratory by reactions of ClO with H2SO4 aerosols (Martin et al., 1979).</text></s>
<s sid="381"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con37" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Jaegle et al. (1996) modeled the formation of HClO4, assuming a 40% yield from the reaction of ClO on the surface on sulfate aerosols.</text></s>
<s sid="382"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con38" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The authors concluded that, on Earth, over 50% (2ppbv) of stratospheric inorganic chlorine could be sequestered into HClO4 when significant amounts of sulfate aerosols are present.</text></s>
<s sid="383"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con39" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, subsequent work questioned the result and found insignificant uptake of ClO on sulfuric acid (Abbatt, 1996).</text></s>
<s sid="384"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con40" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Nonetheless, other heterogeneous reactions involving oxidizing radicals might be possible by analogy with ongoing research to understand the terrestrial atmosphere (George and Abbatt, 2010).</text></s>
Improving model accuracy
<s sid="385"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con41" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Finally, we note that the accuracy of the photochemical model used here could be improved with new data.</text></s>
<s sid="386"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con42" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>NASA's MAVEN (Mars Atmosphere and Volatile EvolutioN) mission will characterize the upper atmosphere of the planet, which will include measurements of neutral species and thermal ions.</text></s>
<s sid="387"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con43" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These data will be useful in constraining the odd-nitrogen flux into the neutral atmosphere, the loss of O from the neutral atmosphere, and the escape rate of hydrogen (Jakosky and MAVEN Science Team, 2011), all of which are adjustable parameters in the model.</text></s>
Conclusions
<s sid="388"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con44" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We used a 1-dimensional photochemical model to calculate the atmospheric production and deposition rate of sulfate, nitrate and perchlorate salts in the Amazonian martian atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="389"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con45" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The results suggest the following conclusions:•</text></s>
<s sid="390"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res186" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Sulfate production through gas to particle conversion in the atmosphere is a viable means to account for the measured concentration of sulfates on the martian surface.</text></s>
•
<s sid="391"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res187" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Nitrogen is continuously dry-deposited from the atmosphere of Mars even today mainly as pernitric acid.</text></s>
<s sid="392"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con46" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>During the Amazonian, 4.3×1018g NO4 could have been deposited across the martian surface if all of the nitrate is formed through atmospheric photochemistry and persists without decomposition or any further reactions.</text></s>
<s sid="393"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con47" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This corresponds to a concentration of 0.3wt.% N if it is mixed uniformly to a depth of 2m.</text></s>
<s sid="394"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con48" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This prediction can be confirmed or disproved by future in situ measurements.</text></s>
•
<s sid="395"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con49" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The production of perchlorate via the gas phase formation process first modeled by Catling et al. (2010) for the driest regions of Earth's atmosphere is insufficient to account for 0.4-0.6wt.% ClO4- measured by NASA's Phoenix Lander.</text></s>
<s sid="396"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con50" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Low atmospheric temperatures and a small inventory of oxygen and ozone limit the gas phase production rate of perchlorate.</text></s>
<s sid="397"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con51" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Consequently, purely gas phase reactions do not appear to explain high perchlorate:chloride ratios in martian soil.</text></s>
<s sid="398"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con52" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Instead, the efficient conversion of chloride to perchlorate may rely on heterogeneous reactions, i.e., gas-solid surface reactions.</text></s>
<s sid="399"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con53" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The limitation of gas phase reactions may be analogous to problems encountered in terrestrial atmospheric chemistry, such as the 'ozone hole' issue.</text></s>
<s sid="400"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con54" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Further theoretical and laboratory research into perchlorate production mechanisms under martian conditions is warranted.</text></s>
</BODY>
<OTHER>
Acknowledgments
This work was supported by NASA's Mars Fundamental Research Program through Grant NNX10AN67G awarded to DCC.
KJZ also acknowledges support from Mars Fundamental Research Program.
MLS acknowledges support from a National Science Foundation Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship, under NSF-IGERT Grant DGE-9870713, Astrobiology: Life in and beyond Earth's Solar System.
MWC acknowledges support from a 2011 NAI Director's Discretionary Fund award titled &quot;Perchlorate, Water, and Life&quot;, along with a NASA postdoctoral program award to work at the Virtual Planetary Laboratory.
MLS thanks Jim Kasting for helpful discussions about using the photochemical model.
We also thank two anonymous reviewers for improving the scientific content and clarity of the paper.
Bromine chemistry in an Earth photochemical model
There are many models for bromine chemistry in the troposphere and stratosphere, ranging from 3-D chemical transport models (e.g. von Glasow and Crutzen, 2006), to box models of the marine boundary layer (e.g. Sander and Crutzen, 1996), to 3-D stratospheric models (e.g. Hossaini et al., 2012).
One-dimensional models (Singh and Kasting, 1988; Yung et al., 1980) are able to match observed profiles of the most abundant bromine species.
Before we added bromine chemistry to the nominal Mars model, we added the chemistry to the terrestrial model of Catling et al. (2010).
Bromine reactions are listed in Table A.1.
Volcanic emission of HBr, release of bromine from sea salt aerosols, and emission of CH3Br from marine phytoplankton are all sources of atmospheric bromine on Earth (e.g. Lovelock, 1975).
Other sources of bromine, including anthropogenic and additional biological emissions, were not considered here because the sources are poorly constrained (von Glasow and Crutzen, 2006) and unlikely to apply for Mars.
We applied the terrestrial arc volcano HCl/HBr ratio of ∼103 to the terrestrial volcanic emissions (Pyle and Mather, 2009).
The HCl volcanic flux was set to 5×108moleculescm-2s-1 and the HBr volcanic flux was set to 5×105moleculescm-2s-1.
Bromine, in the form of BrCl and Br2, is released from sea salt aerosols at a rate of 1-10×1011gBryr-1 (von Glasow and Crutzen, 2006).
We took a rate of 5×1011gyr-1 and assumed all bromine is released as Br2.
For the third and last source of bromine, we assumed a CH3Br surface mixing ratio of 20pptv (Yung et al., 1980).
This value may be too high, compared with the nominal background concentration of CH3Br in the troposphere ∼10pptv (Quack and Wallace, 2003).
However, because we ignored other organic bromine sources, our assumption is justifiable.
The deposition velocities of bromine species were assumed to be equivalent to their chlorine counterparts, e.g., Br was given the same deposition velocity as Cl and HBr was given the same deposition velocity as HCl (Catling et al., 2010).
To validate the terrestrial model with bromine we compared satellite and in situ measurements of bromine species.
We compared measurements of four bromine species, BrO, BrONO2, HOBr, and HBr, with output from the 1-D model.
The model-derived BrO mixing ratio profile was compared with two separate measured profiles of BrO.
The first set of measurements was made with balloon-borne Differential Optical Absorption Spectroscopy (Dorf et al., 2008).
The balloon payload was launched at Teresina, Brazil (5.1°S, 42.9°W) on 17 June 2005 (Dorf et al., 2008).
The second set of measurements was taken by the Scanning Imaging Absorption Spectrometer for Atmospheric Chartography (SCIAMACHY) instrument aboard the European Envisat satellite (Sioris et al., 2006).
SCIAMACHY data plotted in Fig.
A.1 are from both low latitudes, 20-30°S, and high midlatitudes, 36-60°S, and correspond to early March 2003.
The data and model results compare relatively well, but it is clear that the modeled BrO concentrations are slightly lower than the observations (Fig.
A.1a).
This could be the result of several factors.
First, as noted previously, we have neglected some sources of organic and anthropogenic bromine.
Second, the model did not include heterogeneous chemistry.
In the model of von Glasow and Crutzen (2004), when only gas phase chemistry was considered, cycling of HOBr, HBr, and BrONO2 was slower than when heterogeneous chemistry was included, and as a result the BrO concentrations were systematically lower than they should have been.
We next compared the model output with measurements of BrONO2, HOBr, and HBr.
Measurements of BrONO2 were taken by the Michelson Interferometer for Passive Atmospheric Sounding aboard the European Envisat Satellite (Hopfner et al., 2009).
The measurements, both day and night, were taken in September 2003, across 40°S to 15°S.
The model accurately captured a diurnal average of BrONO2, within the limits of uncertainty (Fig.
A.1b).
Measurements of HOBr (Fig.
A.1c) and HBr (Fig.
A.1d) were from a far-infrared spectrometer aboard a balloon platform (Johnson et al., 1995).
The data reported in Fig.
A.1 are averages from several flights taken in 1988-1990.
There are only slight differences between the model results and observations, leading us to conclude that the calculation of bromine speciation is accurately captured by the addition of bromine reactions to the model of Catling et al. (2010).

</OTHER>
</PAPER>