<?xml version="1.0" ?><PAPER><mode2 hasDoc="yes" name="S0019103512004009.tmf1" version="elsevier"/>
<TITLE>The escape of heavy atoms from the ionosphere of HD209458b.
</TITLE>
<ABSTRACT>
I.
<s sid="1"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>A photochemical-dynamical model of the thermosphere</text></s>
</ABSTRACT>
<BODY>

Highlights
<s sid="2"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>► We developed a new model to explain the FUV transit observations of HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="3"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>► We find a qualitative agreement between the model and the observed atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="4"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>► We constrain the mass loss rate and escape mechanism based on stellar heating.</text></s>
<s sid="5"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>► We present density profiles for the detected heavy atoms and ions.</text></s>
<s sid="6"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>► Diffusive separation of heavy species is prevented by the escape of H and protons.</text></s>
Abstract
<s sid="7"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The detections of atomic hydrogen, heavy atoms and ions surrounding the extrasolar giant planet (EGP) HD209458b constrain the composition, temperature and density profiles in its upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="8"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus the observations provide guidance for models that have so far predicted a range of possible conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="9"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We present the first hydrodynamic escape model for the upper atmosphere that includes all of the detected species in order to explain their presence at high altitudes, and to further constrain the temperature and velocity profiles.</text></s>
<s sid="10"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>This model calculates the stellar heating rates based on recent estimates of photoelectron heating efficiencies, and includes the photochemistry of heavy atoms and ions in addition to hydrogen and helium.</text></s>
<s sid="11"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The composition at the lower boundary of the escape model is constrained by a full photochemical model of the lower atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="12"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We confirm that molecules dissociate near the 1μbar level, and find that complex molecular chemistry does not need to be included above this level.</text></s>
<s sid="13"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We also confirm that diffusive separation of the detected species does not occur because the heavy atoms and ions collide frequently with the rapidly escaping H and H+.</text></s>
<s sid="14"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This means that the abundance of the heavy atoms and ions in the thermosphere simply depends on the elemental abundances and ionization rates.</text></s>
<s sid="15"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We show that, as expected, H and O remain mostly neutral up to at least 3Rp, whereas both C and Si are mostly ionized at significantly lower altitudes.</text></s>
<s sid="16"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We also explore the temperature and velocity profiles, and find that the outflow speed and the temperature gradients depend strongly on the assumed heating efficiencies.</text></s>
<s sid="17"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Our models predict an upper limit of 8000K for the mean (pressure averaged) temperature below 3Rp, with a typical value of 7000K based on the average solar XUV flux at 0.047AU.</text></s>
<s sid="18"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>We use these temperature limits and the observations to evaluate the role of stellar energy in heating the upper atmosphere.</text></s>

Introduction
<s sid="19"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The detection of hot atomic hydrogen in the upper atmosphere of HD209458b (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003, 2004) has inspired numerous attempts to model physical and chemical processes in highly irradiated atmospheres, including rapid escape as one of the most challenging aspects.</text></s>
<s sid="20"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Subsequent detection of heavy atoms and ions (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2004; Linsky et al., 2010) point out the need for more complex models that include the chemistry associated with these species as well as the collision coupling between them and the major species.</text></s>
<s sid="21"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Indeed, close-in extrasolar planets offer a natural laboratory to constrain the theory of rapid escape, including hydrodynamic escape.</text></s>
<s sid="22"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This is important because aspects of the theory are controversial, and yet rapid escape is believed to have played a role in shaping the early evolution of the atmospheres in the Solar System (e.g., Zahnle and Kasting, 1986; Hunten et al., 1987).</text></s>
<s sid="23"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Escape may also be a crucial factor in determining atmospheric conditions and habitability of super-Earths and Earth-like planets around M dwarfs (e.g., Tarter et al., 2007) that may be amenable to spectroscopic studies in the near future (e.g., Charbonneau et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="24"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The basic ideas about the nature of the upper atmospheres around close-in EGPs were laid out almost as soon as the first planet, 51 Peg b (Mayor and Queloz, 1995), was detected.</text></s>
<s sid="25"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>For instance, Coustenis et al. (1998) argued that heating by the stellar EUV radiation and interaction with the stellar wind leads to high temperatures of several thousand Kelvins in the upper atmosphere and exosphere of close-in EGPs.</text></s>
<s sid="26"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>They also suggested that the upper atmosphere is primarily composed of atoms and ions, and that hydrodynamic escape might be able to drag species heavier than H and He into the exosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="27"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>At the same time, Schneider et al. (1998) argued that material escaping from the atmospheres of close-in EGPs would form a potentially observable comet-like tail.</text></s>
<s sid="28"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>When Vidal-Madjar et al. (2003, 2004) detected the transits of HD209458b in the stellar FUV emission lines, they also argued that the planet is followed by comet-like tail of escaping hydrogen, and that hydrodynamic escape is required to drag oxygen and carbon atoms to the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="29"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>The model of Yelle (2004, 2006) was the first attempt to model the aeronomy and escape processes in detail and most of the assumptions in that work have been adopted by subsequent investigators.</text></s>
<s sid="30"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>It solved the vertical equations of continuity, momentum, and energy for an escaping atmosphere, including photochemistry in the ionosphere and transfer of stellar XUV radiation.</text></s>
<s sid="31"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Based on a composition of hydrogen and helium, the results demonstrated that H2 dissociates in the thermosphere, which at high altitudes is dominated by H and H+.</text></s>
<s sid="32"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The model also showed that stellar heating leads to temperatures of ∼10,000K in the upper atmosphere, and predicted an energy-limited mass loss rate of 4.7×107kgs-1 (Yelle, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="33"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Yelle (2004) argued that conditions beyond ∼3Rp were too complex and uncertain to be modeled reliably and therefore chose an upper boundary at 3Rp, rather than at infinity, as adopted in early solar wind models.</text></s>
<s sid="34"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This led to a requirement for boundary conditions for the fluid equations at a finite radius.</text></s>
<s sid="35"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Yelle (2004) required consistency between fluid and kinetic simulations, based on the well established fact that kinetic and fluid approaches provide consistent results for the escape flux (e.g., Lemaire and Scherer, 1973).</text></s>
<s sid="36"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This led to subsonic velocities of a few kms-1 in his model - although the presence of a sonic point at a higher altitude was not ruled out.</text></s>
<s sid="37"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Many other models for the upper atmospheres of close-in EGPs have been published (e.g., Lammer et al., 2003; Lecavelier des Etangs et al., 2004; Jaritz et al., 2005; Tian et al., 2005; Erkaev et al., 2007; Garcia Munoz, 2007; Schneiter et al., 2007; Penz et al., 2008; Holström et al., 2008; Murray-Clay et al., 2009; Stone and Proga, 2009; Guo, 2011; Trammell et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="38"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These include one-dimensional, two-dimensional, and three-dimensional models that make different assumptions regarding heating efficiency, the effect of stellar tides, photochemistry, and the escape mechanism.</text></s>
<s sid="39"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Despite significant differences in the temperature and velocity profiles, almost all of the existing models agree that close-in EGPs such as HD209458b are surrounded by an extended, hot thermosphere that is undergoing some form of escape.</text></s>
<s sid="40"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Most of the models to date concentrate on the distribution of H and H+ in the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="41"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Garcia Munoz (2007) developed the only model to address the presence of O and C+ in the thermosphere (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2004; Linsky et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="42"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This model is otherwise similar to Yelle (2004), but it includes the photochemistry of heavy ions, atoms, molecules, and molecular ions.</text></s>
<s sid="43"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>It also extends to higher altitudes, and includes the effect of substellar tidal forces and stellar wind, albeit in an approximate manner.</text></s>
<s sid="44"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Koskinen et al. (2007a,b) developed a three-dimensional model for the thermospheres of EGPs at wide orbits.</text></s>
<s sid="45"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>They pointed out that the atmospheres of close-in EGPs do not escape hydrodynamically unless they receive enough stellar XUV energy to dissociate molecules in the EUV heating layer below the exobase.</text></s>
<s sid="46"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Although their results are limited to the specific case of H2, they can be generalized as follows.</text></s>
<s sid="47"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The most important molecules H2 (through the formation of H3+), CO, H2O, and CH4 act as strong infrared coolants in the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="48"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>High temperatures and rapid escape are only possible once these molecules are dissociated.</text></s>
<s sid="49"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Koskinen et al. (2007b) showed that H2 dissociates in the thermosphere of a Jupiter-type planet orbiting a Sun-like star within 0.2AU.</text></s>
<s sid="50"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Once H2 dissociates, it is reasonable to assume that other molecules dissociate too.</text></s>
<s sid="51"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>At this point the pressure scale height is enhanced by a factor of ∼10 when H becomes the dominant species in the thermosphere and temperatures reach 10,000K.</text></s>
<s sid="52"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>It should be noted that a composition of H and H+ with high temperatures does not guarantee that the atmosphere escapes hydrodynamically.</text></s>
<s sid="53"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>For instance, Koskinen et al. (2009) showed that hydrodynamic escape is extremely unlikely to occur on a planet such as HD17156b because of its high mass and eccentric orbit.</text></s>
<s sid="54"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>These types of results have implications on statistical studies that characterize the escape of planetary atmospheres by relying on the so-called energy-limited escape (e.g., Watson et al., 1981; Lecavelier des Etangs, 2007; Sanz-Forcada et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="55"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>These studies often include an efficiency factor in the mass loss rate that is based on the heating efficiency of the upper atmosphere (e.g., Lammer et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="56"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Unless the atmosphere is escaping rapidly, the heating efficiency could be considerably larger than the fraction of energy that actually powers escape through adiabatic cooling.</text></s>
<s sid="57"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Under diffusion-limited escape or in the Jeans regime the energy-limited escape rate is just an upper limit and the true escape rate can be lower.</text></s>
<s sid="58"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Ideally, the uncertainties in the models can be limited by detailed observations of the escaping species.</text></s>
<s sid="59"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>At present, multiple observations are only available for HD209458b, and they reveal the presence of H, O, C+, and Si2+ at high altitudes in the thermosphere (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003, 2004; Linsky et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="60"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Visible and infrared observations have also revealed the presence of Na, H2O, CH4, and CO2 in the lower atmosphere (Charbonneau et al., 2002; Knutson et al., 2008; Swain et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="61"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Taken together, these observations are beginning to reveal the composition and thermal structure in the atmosphere of HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="62"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The purpose of the current paper is to characterize the density profiles of all of the detected species in the thermosphere, and to explain the presence of the heavy atoms and ions at high altitudes in the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="63"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The results can be used to infer some basic properties of the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="64"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>To this end, we introduce a one-dimensional escape model for the upper atmosphere of HD209458b that includes the photochemistry of heavy atoms and ions.</text></s>
<s sid="65"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As pointed out above, previous models agree broadly on the qualitative nature of the thermosphere but the temperature, density, and velocity profiles predicted by them differ significantly (see Section 3.1).</text></s>
<s sid="66"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Some authors have argued that the density of H in the thermosphere is not sufficient to explain the observed transit depths (see Koskinen et al. (2010a) for a review), thus lending support to alternative interpretations of the observations such as the presence of energetic neutral atoms (Holström et al., 2008) or a comet-like tail of hydrogen shaped by radiation pressure (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003).</text></s>
<s sid="67"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Accurate modeling of the thermosphere is required to enable better judgment between different explanations of the observations.</text></s>
<s sid="68"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The differences between previous models arise from different assumptions regarding heating rates and boundary conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="69"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In addition to modeling the density profiles of the detected heavy species, we have improved these aspects of the calculations in our work.</text></s>
<s sid="70"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>For instance, the lower boundary conditions are constrained by results from a detailed photochemical model of the lower atmosphere (Lavvas et al., in preparation).</text></s>
<s sid="71"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>With regard to the upper boundary conditions, we demonstrate that for HD209458b the extrapolated 'outflow' boundary conditions (e.g., Tian et al., 2005) are consistent with recent results from kinetic theory (Volkov et al., 2011a,b) as long as the upper boundary is at a sufficiently high altitude - although uncertainties regarding the interaction of the atmosphere with the stellar wind may limit the validity of both boundary conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="72"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We highlight the effect of heating efficiency and stellar flux on the density and temperature profiles, and constrain the likely heating rates by using photoelectron heating efficiencies based on the results of Cecchi-Pestellini et al. (2009) and our own estimates (Section 3.1).</text></s>
<s sid="73"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>As a result we provide a robust qualitative description of the density profiles, and constrain the mean temperature and velocity profile in the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="74"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>A second paper by Koskinen et al. (2012) (Paper II) compares our results directly with the observations.</text></s>
Methods
Hydrodynamic model
<s sid="75"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We use a one-dimensional escape model for HD209458b (Rp=1.32RJ, Mp=0.69MJ, a=0.047AU) that is similar to the models of Yelle (2004) and Garcia Munoz (2007).</text></s>
<s sid="76"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Because such models are extensively discussed in the literature, we include only a brief overview of the model here, with the emphasis on how it differs from previous work.</text></s>
<s sid="77"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The model solves the one-dimensional equations of motion for an escaping atmosphere composed of several neutral and ionized species:(1)∂ρs∂t+1r2∂∂r(r2ρsv)+1r2∂∂r(r2Fs)=∑tRst(2)∂(ρv)∂t+1r2∂∂r(r2ρv2)=-ρg-∂p∂r+fμ(3)∂(ρE)∂t+1r2∂∂r(r2ρEv)=ρQR-p1r2∂∂r(r2v)+1r2∂∂rr2κ∂T∂r+Φμwhere ρs is the density of species s, v is the vertical velocity, Fs is the diffusive flux of species s, Rst is the net chemical source term for species s, fμ is a force term arising from viscous acceleration, E=cvT is the specific internal energy of the gas, QR is the specific net radiative heating rate, κ is the coefficient of heat conduction, and Φμ is the viscous dissipation functional (e.g., O'Neill and Chorlton, 1989).</text></s>
<s sid="78"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The total density and pressure are given by ρ=∑sρs and p=∑snskT, respectively, where electrons contribute to the total pressure.</text></s>
<s sid="79"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We assumed equal temperatures for the neutral species, ions and electrons, and calculated the electron density at each altitude from the requirement of charge neutrality.</text></s>
<s sid="80"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The model solves separate continuity equations for each species, but treats the atmosphere otherwise as a single fluid.</text></s>
<s sid="81"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The differences in the velocities of the individual species are taken into account by including the diffusive flux Fs.</text></s>
<s sid="82"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We calculated the fluxes by solving simultaneous equations for multiple species based on the diffusion equation given by Chapman and Cowling (1970) Eq.</text></s>
(18.2,6), p.344.
<s sid="83"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We also included a force term due to the ambipolar electric field given by eE=-(1/ne)dpe/dr, where the subscript e refers to electrons, that can be important in highly ionized flows.</text></s>
<s sid="84"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The collision terms account for neutral-neutral, resonant and non-resonant ion-neutral, and Coulomb collisions.</text></s>
<s sid="85"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>This method is in principle similar to those of Yelle (2004) and Garcia Munoz (2007).</text></s>
<s sid="86"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We verify that the single temperature and diffusion approximations are valid for HD209458b based on our results in Section 3.2.2.</text></s>
<s sid="87"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod16" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The model includes heat conduction and terms due to viscosity in both the momentum and energy equations.</text></s>
<s sid="88"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod17" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Thus the equations are consistent with the level of approximation in the Navier-Stokes (NS) equations.</text></s>
<s sid="89"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod18" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The NS equations themselves are a simplification of the 13-moment solution to the Boltzmann equation (e.g., Gombosi, 1994) that is valid when the Knudsen number Kn=Λ/L≪1, where Λ is the mean free path and L is the typical length scale for significant changes in density or temperature.</text></s>
<s sid="90"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod19" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Broadly speaking, the equations are valid below the exobase, and terms due to heat conduction and viscosity gain significance as Kn→1.</text></s>
<s sid="91"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod20" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We note that the exobase on HD209458b is typically located at a very high altitude (see Section 3.1), and viscosity and heat conduction are not particularly important.</text></s>
<s sid="92"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod21" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We included species such as H, H+, He, He+, C, C+, O, O+, N, N+, Si, Si+, Si2+, and electrons in the hydrodynamic model.</text></s>
<s sid="93"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We also generated simulations that included Mg, Mg+, Na, Na+, K, K+, S, and S+, but the presence of these species did not affect the density profiles of H, O, C+, or Si2+ significantly.</text></s>
<s sid="94"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The model includes photoionization, thermal ionization, and charge exchange between atoms and ions.</text></s>
<s sid="95"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The reaction rate coefficients for these processes are listed in Table 1.</text></s>
<s sid="96"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Multiply charged ions were included only if the ionization potential of their parent ion was sufficiently low compared to the thermal energy and radiation field in the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="97"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that our model also includes impact ionization by thermal electrons.</text></s>
<s sid="98"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In general, this can be important for species with low ionization potential such as alkali metals (e.g., Batygin and Stevenson, 2010), although we find photoionization to be more significant in the thermosphere (see Section 3.2).</text></s>
<s sid="99"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>In order to simulate photochemistry in a numerically robust fashion, we coupled the dynamical model with the ASAD chemistry integrator developed at the University of Cambridge (Carver et al., 1997).</text></s>
<s sid="100"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>In most cases we used the IMPACT integration scheme that is provided by ASAD.</text></s>
<s sid="101"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod22" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We did not include any molecules in the present simulations, and thus placed the lower boundary of the hydrodynamic model at p0=1μbar (see Section 2.1.1).</text></s>
<s sid="102"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Molecular chemistry is not significant in the thermosphere, where our results agree qualitatively with Garcia Munoz (2007) despite simpler chemistry (see Section 3.2).</text></s>
<s sid="103"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>This is an important result because it implies that complex molecular photochemistry does not need to be included in the models for the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="104"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>However, the chemistry of molecular ions may be important on HD209458b below the 0.1μbar level and it needs to be studied in greater detail.</text></s>
<s sid="105"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>The upper atmosphere is heated by stellar XUV radiation.</text></s>
<s sid="106"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We simulated heating and photoionization self-consistently by using the model density profiles and the UV spectrum of the average Sun.</text></s>
<s sid="107"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The spectrum covers wavelengths between 0.1 and 3000Å.</text></s>
<s sid="108"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The XUV spectrum between 0.1 and 1050Å was generated by the SOLAR2000 model (Tobiska et al., 2000).</text></s>
<s sid="109"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>It includes strong emission lines separately and weaker lines binned by 50Å.</text></s>
<s sid="110"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod23" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The Lyman α line was included with a wavelength spacing of 0.5Å from Lemaire et al. (2005) and the rest of the spectrum was taken from Woods and Rottman (2002).</text></s>
<s sid="111"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod24" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We assumed that most of the Lyman α radiation absorbed by H is resonantly scattered and does not contribute significantly to the heating of the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="112"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is because the lifetime of the 2p state of H is only 1.6ns, compared with the typical collision timescale of ∼1s near the temperature peak in the thermosphere of HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="113"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>References for photoabsorption cross sections of the different species are included in Table 1.</text></s>
<s sid="114"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod25" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In general, we divided the incident stellar flux by a factor of 4 to account for uniform redistribution of energy around the planet.</text></s>
<s sid="115"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod26" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>This is expected to be approximately valid in the lower thermosphere based on the three-dimensional simulations of Koskinen et al. (2010b).</text></s>
<s sid="116"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod27" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In the extended upper thermosphere, on the other hand, radiation passes through to the night side and leaves only a small region free of direct heating (e.g., see Fig. 2 of Koskinen et al. (2007b)).</text></s>
<s sid="117"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod28" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The current model also includes heating due to photoabsorption by C, O, N, and metals.</text></s>
<s sid="118"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>This is relatively insignificant - although it leads to some additional heating in the lower thermosphere by FUV radiation.</text></s>
<s sid="119"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Heating of the thermosphere is mostly driven by photoionization and the generation of photoelectrons, although direct excitation of atoms and molecules may also play a role.</text></s>
<s sid="120"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Photoelectrons excite, ionize, and dissociate atoms and molecules until they lose enough energy and become thermalized i.e., share their energy with thermal electrons in Coulomb collisions.</text></s>
<s sid="121"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Thermal electrons share their energy with ions and eventually, the neutral atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="122"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met5" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>In highly ionized atmospheres such as on HD209458b the photoelectron heating efficiency can be close to 100% (Cecchi-Pestellini et al., 2009), depending on the energy of the photoelectrons.</text></s>
<s sid="123"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met6" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We used scaled heating efficiencies that depend on photoelectron energy to estimate the net heating efficiency in the atmosphere (Section 3.1).</text></s>
<s sid="124"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>Generally, we refer to two different definitions of heating efficiency in Section 3.1 in order to highlight the effect of heating efficiency on the temperature and velocity profiles.</text></s>
<s sid="125"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod29" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The net heating efficiency ηnet is defined simply as the fraction of the absorbed stellar energy that heats the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="126"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod30" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Photoelectron heating efficiency, on the other hand, applies to photoelectrons with energy Ep=hν-Is, where Is is the ionization potential of species s and hν is the energy of the ionizing photon.</text></s>
<s sid="127"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod31" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The photoelectron heating efficiency is the fraction of Ep that heats the thermosphere, and it is generally higher than ηnet because it does not account for recombination.</text></s>
<s sid="128"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The net heating efficiency is often used to calculate mass loss rates for extrasolar planets (e.g., Lammer et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="129"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Therefore it is important not to confuse these two definitions of heating efficiency.</text></s>
<s sid="130"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We included radiative cooling by recombination under the assumption that the thermosphere is optically thin to the emitted photons.</text></s>
<s sid="131"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This implies that the ionization potential energy Is never contributes to heating at any levels.</text></s>
<s sid="132"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We also considered the influence of Lyman α cooling by excited H, although this cooling rate is uncertain and likely to be low for HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="133"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We discuss the effect of different cooling rates further in Section 3.1.</text></s>
Lower boundary conditions
<s sid="134"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod32" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>As stated above, we placed the lower boundary of the hydrodynamic model at p0=1μbar and did not include H2 or other molecules in the model.</text></s>
<s sid="135"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod33" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>This decision was motivated by photochemical calculations for HD209458b (Lavvas et al., in preparation) that we used to constrain the lower boundary condition.</text></s>
<s sid="136"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod34" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The photochemical model was originally developed for the atmosphere of Titan (Lavvas et al., 2008a,b) but it was recently expanded to simulate EGP atmospheres.</text></s>
<s sid="137"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>It calculates the chemical composition from the deep troposphere (1000bar) up to the thermosphere above the 0.1nbar level by solving the coupled continuity equations for all species based on a database of ∼1500 reaction rate coefficients and 103 photolysis processes.</text></s>
<s sid="138"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Forward and reverse rates are included for each reaction with the ratio of the rate coefficients defined by thermochemical data.</text></s>
<s sid="139"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus, the results are consistent with thermochemical equilibrium at deep atmospheric levels but differences develop at higher altitudes due to photolysis, diffusion, and eddy mixing.</text></s>
<s sid="140"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod35" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>At the lower boundary the chemical abundances of the main species (H, C, N, and O) are set to their thermodynamic equilibrium values and, depending on the vertical temperature profile and their abundances, species are allowed to condense.</text></s>
<s sid="141"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Fig. 1 shows the mixing ratios of H2, H, H2O, O, CH4, CO, CO2, and C as a function of altitude from the photochemical model.</text></s>
<s sid="142"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In general, the results are similar to those of Moses et al. (2011).</text></s>
<s sid="143"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The H2/H transition is located near 1μbar.</text></s>
<s sid="144"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>At lower pressures, the mixing ratio of H2 decreases rapidly with altitude and falls below 0.1 above the 0.1μbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="145"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In agreement with Garcia Munoz (2007), the dissociation of H2 is caused by dissociation of H2O, which leads to the production of OH radicals that attack the H2 molecules.</text></s>
<s sid="146"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that the exact location of the H2/H transition depends on the temperature profile and, depending on the thermal structure, it could occur even below the 1μbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="147"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The major oxygen-bearing molecules, CO and H2O, have roughly equal abundances from 10 to 10-5bar.</text></s>
<s sid="148"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is in line with thermochemical equilibrium at the temperatures and pressures relevant to HD209458b (Lodders and Fegley, 2002).</text></s>
<s sid="149"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>H2O and CO are effectively dissociated at pressures lower than 0.3 and 0.1μbar, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="150"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We note that molecular abundances could be significant at 0.1-1μbar, and technically the results of the hydrodynamic calculations are only valid above the 0.1μbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="151"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The presence of molecules such as H2, H2O, and CO can lead to enhanced UV heating as well as efficient radiative cooling by H3+, H2O and CO in the 0.1-1μbar region.</text></s>
<s sid="152"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The photochemical model also includes the chemistry of silicon.</text></s>
<s sid="153"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Due to condensation into forsterite and enstatite (e.g., Visscher et al., 2010), the abundance of Si in the observable atmospheres of giant planets was thought to be negligible and thus the photochemistry of silicon in planetary atmospheres has not been studied before.</text></s>
<s sid="154"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The photochemical calculations indicate that, in agreement with thermochemical calculations (Visscher et al., 2010), SiO is the dominant silicon-bearing gas.</text></s>
<s sid="155"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>SiO dissociates in the thermosphere at a similar pressure level as H2O and CO.</text></s>
<s sid="156"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that the detection of Si2+ in the thermosphere implies that silicon does not condense in the atmosphere of HD209458b (Paper II).</text></s>
<s sid="157"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met7" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>In addition to composition, lower boundary conditions are required for temperature and velocity.</text></s>
<s sid="158"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met8" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We specified T0 and p0 at the lower boundary, and used them to calculate ρ0 from the ideal gas law.</text></s>
<s sid="159"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod36" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The steady state continuity equation ρ0v0r2=Fc, where Fc is the flux constant, was used to calculate the velocity v0 at the lower boundary during each time step.</text></s>
<s sid="160"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod37" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The flux constant is solved self-consistently by the model, and it depends largely on the terms in the energy equation.</text></s>
<s sid="161"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod38" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In general we assumed that T0≈1300K, which is close to the effective temperature of the planet.</text></s>
<s sid="162"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that this temperature is largely unconstrained.</text></s>
<s sid="163"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met9" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Radiative transfer models for close-in EGPs (e.g., Showman et al., 2009 and references therein) do not account for heating by stellar UV radiation or possible opacity sources created by photochemistry (e.g., Zhanle et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="164"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met10" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Therefore these models may not accurately predict the temperature at the base of the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="165"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Sing et al. (2008a,b) used observations of the Na D line profile to constrain the temperature profile in the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="166"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>They suggested that Na condenses into clouds near the 3mbar level, and thus predicted a deep minimum in temperature in this region that is required for condensation.</text></s>
<s sid="167"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The detection of Si2+ implies that condensation of Na in the lower atmosphere is unlikely (Paper II), and thus this result is unreliable.</text></s>
<s sid="168"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Relying on the same observations, Vidal-Madjar et al. (2011a,b) predicted that the temperature increases steeply from 1300K to 3500K near the 1μbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="169"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, their method to retrieve the temperature relies on the density scale height of Na to express the optical depth along the line of sight (LOS).</text></s>
<s sid="170"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is not consistent with the argument that Na is depleted above the 3mbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="171"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>If such a depletion takes place, the density scale height of Na is not the same as the scale height of the atmosphere and it cannot be used to retrieve temperatures.</text></s>
Upper boundary conditions
<s sid="172"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Previous models of the thermosphere disagree on the details of the density and temperature profiles (e.g., Yelle, 2004; Tian et al., 2005; Garcia Munoz, 2007; Murray-Clay et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="173"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This is partly due to different boundary conditions, although assumptions regarding the heating rates and composition are probably more important (see Section 3.1).</text></s>
<s sid="174"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Unfortunately, the planetary wind equations can have an infinite number of both subsonic and supersonic solutions.</text></s>
<s sid="175"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In time-dependent models, the upper boundary conditions in particular can determine if the solution is subsonic or supersonic, and they can alter the temperature and velocity profiles (e.g., Garcia Munoz, 2007).</text></s>
<s sid="176"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The choice of proper boundary conditions is therefore important.</text></s>
<s sid="177"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met11" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Volkov et al. (2011a,b) studied the escape of neutral atmospheres under different circumstances by using the kinetic Monte Carlo (DSMC) method.</text></s>
<s sid="178"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Because the fluid equations are a simplification of the kinetic equations at low values of Kn, the hydrodynamic model should ideally be consistent with the DSMC results both above and below the exobase.</text></s>
<s sid="179"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Volkov et al. (2011a,b) found that the nature of the solutions depends on the thermal escape parameter X0=GMpm/kT0r0 and the Knudsen number Kn0 at the lower boundary r0 of a region where diabatic heating is negligible.</text></s>
<s sid="180"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>They argued that hydrodynamic escape is possible when X0&lt;2-3 (see also Opik, 1963; Hunten, 1973).</text></s>
<s sid="181"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>When X0≳3, on the other hand, the sonic point is at such a high altitude that the solution is practically subsonic and with X0≳6 the escape rate is similar to the thermal Jeans escape rate.</text></s>
<s sid="182"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The results of the DSMC calculations can be incorporated into hydrodynamic models with appropriate upper boundary conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="183"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Volkov et al. (2011a,b) suggest that the modified Jeans escape rate, which is based on the drifting Maxwellian velocity distribution function, is a good approximation of the DSMC results in fluid models, consistent with Yelle (2004).</text></s>
<s sid="184"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>In order to contrast the modified Jeans upper boundary conditions (hereafter, the modified Jeans conditions) with other possibilities, we used them and the extrapolated upper boundary conditions (hereafter, the 'outflow' conditions) adopted by Tian et al. (2005) and Garcia Munoz (2007) in our simulations.</text></s>
<s sid="185"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>In general, we placed the upper boundary at 16Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="186"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>The impact of the boundary conditions is discussed in Section 3.1.5.</text></s>
<s sid="187"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod39" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We formulated the outflow conditions simply by extrapolating values for density, temperature and velocity with a constant slope from below.</text></s>
<s sid="188"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod40" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>For the modified Jeans conditions, we calculated the effusion velocity vs at the upper boundary separately for each species by using Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="189"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod41" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>(9) from Volkov et al. (2011b).</text></s>
<s sid="190"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod42" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Using this equation violates the conservation of electric charge at the upper boundary because the small mass of the electrons causes their velocity to be much larger than the velocity of the protons.</text></s>
<s sid="191"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod43" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In reality charge separation is prevented by the generation of an ambipolar electric field that ensures that the vertical current is zero at the upper boundary.</text></s>
<s sid="192"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod44" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>This electric field causes the ions to escape faster while it slows the electrons down.</text></s>
<s sid="193"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod45" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Effectively this lowers the escape velocity vesc=2GM/r of the ions and increases the escape velocity of the electrons.</text></s>
<s sid="194"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod46" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In order to incorporate the ambipolar electric field in the modified Jeans conditions we expressed the Jeans parameters for ions and electrons as:(4)Xi=GMmikTr-ϕeqikT(5)Xe=GMmekTr+ϕe|qe|kTwhere ϕe is the ambipolar electric potential, qi,e is the electric charge and subscripts i and e stand for ions and electrons, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="195"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod47" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We used these Jeans parameters to calculate the effusion velocities for the electrons and ions, and then solved iteratively for ϕe by using the condition of zero current i.e., ne|qe|ve=∑iniqivi.</text></s>
<s sid="196"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod48" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>This approach is consistent with kinetic models for the solar and polar winds (Lemaire and Scherer, 1971a,b).</text></s>
<s sid="197"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod49" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Having obtained the correct effusion velocities for the charged and neutral species, we evaluated the mass weighted outflow velocity from:(6)v=1ρ∑sρsvsand used this velocity as an upper boundary condition.</text></s>
<s sid="198"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The values of temperature and density that are required for this calculation were extrapolated from below.</text></s>
<s sid="199"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As the model approaches steady state, the solution approaches a value of v at the upper boundary that is consistent with the modified Jeans velocity.</text></s>
Numerical methods
<s sid="200"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We solved the equations of motion on a grid of 400-550 levels with increasing altitude spacing.</text></s>
<s sid="201"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The radius rn from the center of the planet at level n is thus given by a geometric series (e.g., Garcia Munoz, 2007):(7)rn=r1+∑i=1n-1fciδz0where r1=1.08Rp, δz0=10km, and fc=1.014.</text></s>
<s sid="202"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met12" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We solved the equations of motions in two parts, separating advection (Eulerian terms) from the other (Lagrangian) terms.</text></s>
<s sid="203"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met13" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>The Lagrangian solution is performed first, and all variables are updated before advection.</text></s>
<s sid="204"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met14" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We used the flux conservative van Leer scheme (e.g., van Leer, 1979) for advection, and the semi-implicit Crank-Nicholson scheme (e.g., Jacobson, 1999) to solve for viscosity and conduction in the momentum and energy equations, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="205"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met15" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We employed a time step of 1s in all of our calculations.</text></s>
<s sid="206"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met16" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Despite the sophisticated numerical apparatus, the model is still occasionally unstable, particularly in the early stages of new simulations.</text></s>
<s sid="207"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met17" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>The primary source of the instabilities are pressure fluctuations (sound waves) that are not balanced by gravity.</text></s>
<s sid="208"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met18" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We used a two-step Shapiro filter (Shapiro, 1970) periodically to remove numerical instabilities.</text></s>
<s sid="209"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met19" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We assumed that a steady state has been reached once the flux constant Fc is constant with altitude and the flux of energy is approximately conserved.</text></s>
Results
Temperature and velocity profiles
<s sid="210"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>In this section we constrain the range of mean temperatures and velocities based on stellar heating in the thermosphere of HD209458b and similar close-in EGPs.</text></s>
<s sid="211"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj20" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We discuss the general dependency of the temperature and velocity profiles on the net heating efficiency and stellar flux, and relate this discussion to new temperature and velocity profiles for HD209458b that are based on realistic photoelectron heating efficiencies calculated specifically for close-in EGPs.</text></s>
<s sid="212"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>This discussion is necessary because the temperature and velocity profiles from previous models of the upper atmosphere differ significantly, and the differences affect the density profiles of the observed species (see Section 3.2).</text></s>
<s sid="213"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>As an example, Fig. 2 shows the temperature profiles based on several earlier models.</text></s>
<s sid="214"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In addition to boundary conditions, the discrepancies evident in this figure arise from different assumptions about the heating rates.</text></s>
General dependency
<s sid="215"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We note that the thermal structure in the upper atmospheres of the giant planets in the Solar System is not very well understood despite modeling and observations that are far more extensive than those available for extrasolar planets (e.g., Yelle and Miller, 2004).</text></s>
<s sid="216"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj21" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>It is therefore useful to test the reaction of the model to different heating rates and profiles.</text></s>
<s sid="217"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj22" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We used our model to calculate temperature and velocity profiles based on different heating efficiencies and stellar fluxes.</text></s>
<s sid="218"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>These profiles are shown in Fig. 3.</text></s>
<s sid="219"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met20" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>First, we used the average solar spectrum (Section 2.1) and varied the net heating efficiency ηnet from 0.1 to 1.</text></s>
<s sid="220"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met21" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Second, we multiplied the solar spectrum by factors of 2×, 10×, and 100×, and used ηnet=0.5.</text></s>
<s sid="221"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The range of enhanced fluxes covers solar maximum conditions and stars that are more active than the Sun.</text></s>
<s sid="222"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod50" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In each case we assumed that ηnet is constant and does not vary with altitude.</text></s>
<s sid="223"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod51" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We used planetary parameters of HD209458b and set the upper boundary to 16Rp with outflow boundary conditions, and the lower boundary to the 1μbar level with a temperature of 1300K.</text></s>
<s sid="224"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>A net heating efficiency of 50% is similar to the heating efficiency in the jovian thermosphere (Waite et al., 1983), and we may consider this as a representative case of a typical gas giant (hereafter, the H50 model).</text></s>
<s sid="225"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The maximum temperature in the H50 model is 11,500K and the temperature peak is located near 1.5Rp (p=0.3nbar).</text></s>
<s sid="226"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>As ηnet varies from 0.1 to 1, the peak shifts from 1.4Rp (0.5nbar) to 1.9Rp (0.1nbar) and the maximum temperature varies from 10,000K to 13,200K.</text></s>
<s sid="227"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>It is interesting to note that the temperature profile depends strongly on the heating efficiency but the location of the peak and the maximum temperature depend only weakly on ηnet.</text></s>
<s sid="228"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is because the vertical velocity increases with heating efficiency, leading to more efficient cooling by faster expansion that controls the peak temperature while enhanced advection and high altitude heating flatten the temperature gradient above the peak.</text></s>
<s sid="229"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As a result, the temperature profile is almost isothermal when ηnet=1.</text></s>
<s sid="230"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" type="Hyp"/><text>It is also interesting that the temperature profiles in the models that are based on ηnet=0.5 and the solar flux enhanced by factors of 2-100 differ from models with the average solar flux and a higher heating efficiency.</text></s>
<s sid="231"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" type="Hyp"/><text>For instance, one might naively assume that a model with ηnet=0.5 and 2× the average solar flux would be similar to a model with the average solar flux and ηeta=1.</text></s>
<s sid="232"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Surprisingly, this is not the case - despite the fact that the mass loss rates from these models are identical.</text></s>
<s sid="233"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is because of the way radiation penetrates into the atmosphere - doubling the incoming flux is not the same as doubling the heating rate at each altitude for the same flux.</text></s>
<s sid="234"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As the stellar flux increases further, the temperature peak shifts first to higher altitudes, and then to lower altitudes so that for the 100× case the peak is located again near 1.5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="235"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Despite the hugely increased stellar flux, the peak temperature is only 18,300K for the 100× case.</text></s>
<s sid="236"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This is again because the enhanced adiabatic and advective cooling driven by faster expansion control the temperature even in the absence of efficient radiative cooling mechanisms.</text></s>
<s sid="237"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Koskinen et al. (2010a) suggested that the mean temperature of the thermosphere below 3Rp can be constrained by observations, and used their empirical model to fit temperatures to the H Lyman α transit data (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003; Ben-Jaffel, 2007, 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="238"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A quantity that can be compared with their results is the pressure averaged temperature of the hydrodynamic model, which is given by:(8)Tp¯=∫p1p2T(p)d(lnp)ln(p2/p1)For ηnet ranging from 0.1 to 1, the pressure averaged temperature below 3Rp varies from 6200K to 7800K for the average solar flux.</text></s>
<s sid="239"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In the H50 model the pressure averaged temperature is 7000K.</text></s>
<s sid="240"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that T¯p is a fairly stable feature of our solutions - in contrast to the details of the temperature profile and velocities it is relatively insensitive to different assumptions about the boundary conditions and heating efficiencies.</text></s>
<s sid="241"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Obviously, T¯p depends on the stellar flux, although it only increases to 9800K in the 100× case.</text></s>
<s sid="242"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Koskinen et al. (2010a) inferred a mean temperature of 8250K in the thermosphere of HD209458b with p0=1μbar (the M7 model).</text></s>
<s sid="243"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Taken together with our results based on solar XUV fluxes, this implies a relatively high heating efficiency.</text></s>
<s sid="244"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Alternatively, with ηnet=0.5 it may imply that the XUV flux of HD209458b is 5-10 times higher than the corresponding solar flux.</text></s>
<s sid="245"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This type of an enhancement is not impossible.</text></s>
<s sid="246"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The activity level of the star depends on its rotation rate, and the rotation rate of HD209458 may be twice as fast as the rotation rate of the Sun (Silva-Valio, 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="247"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, the uncertainty of the observed H Lyman α transit depths accommodates a range of temperatures, and thus we are unable to derive firm constraints on the heating rates from the observations.</text></s>
<s sid="248"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In general, though, the pressure averaged temperature provides a useful connection between observations and temperatures predicted by models that can be exploited to constrain heating rates.</text></s>
<s sid="249"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The effect of changing the heating efficiency on the velocity profile is quite dramatic.</text></s>
<s sid="250"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As ηnet ranges from 0.1 to 1 (with the average solar flux), the velocity at the upper boundary increases from 2.6kms-1 to 25kms-1.</text></s>
<s sid="251"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>However, the velocity does not increase linearly with stellar flux or without a bound - in the 100× case the velocity at the upper boundary is only 30kms-1.</text></s>
<s sid="252"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>An interesting qualitative feature of the solutions is that the sonic point moves to a lower altitude with increasing heating efficiency or stellar flux.</text></s>
<s sid="253"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>With ηnet=0.1 the isothermal sonic point is located above the upper boundary whereas with ηnet=1 it is located at 4Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="254"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This behavior is related to the temperature gradient and it is discussed further in Section 3.1.3.</text></s>
<s sid="255"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Basically the sonic point, when it exists, moves further from the planet as the high altitude heating rate decreases.</text></s>
<s sid="256"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>It is now clear that assumptions regarding the heating efficiency and radiative transfer have a large impact on the temperature and velocity profiles and the results from the previous models reflect this fact (see Fig. 2).</text></s>
<s sid="257"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The differences between models have implications on the interpretation of observations.</text></s>
<s sid="258"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>For instance, Vidal-Madjar et al. (2003) and Linsky et al. (2010) suggested that the UV transit observations probe the velocity structure of the escaping gas.</text></s>
<s sid="259"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Obviously, the nature of this velocity structure depends on the properties of the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="260"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>On the other hand, Ben-Jaffel and Hosseini (2010) argued that the observations point to a presence of hot energetic atoms and ions within the Roche lobe of the planet.</text></s>
<s sid="261"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We believe that it is important to properly quantify the role of stellar heating in creating the hot, escaping material before other options are pursued.</text></s>
<s sid="262"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This means that detailed thermal structure calculations that rely on a proper description of photoelectron heating efficiencies are required.</text></s>
<s sid="263"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj23" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Below we discuss a new approach to modeling the temperature profile in the thermosphere of HD209458b and its impact on the velocity and density profiles.</text></s>
<s sid="264"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj24" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Energy balance and temperatures on HD209458b</text></s>
<s sid="265"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj25" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>In the previous section we discussed models where the net heating efficiency ηnet was fixed at a constant value at all altitudes.</text></s>
<s sid="266"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj26" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>In this section we discuss more realistic models of HD209458b that rely on new approximations of photoelectron heating efficiency and derive an estimate of ηnet based on these models.</text></s>
<s sid="267"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj27" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Here we also include radiative cooling from recombination and, in one case, H Lyman α emissions by excited H (Murray-Clay et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="268"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>Our aim was to calculate the most likely range of temperatures in the thermosphere of HD209458b based on average solar fluxes.</text></s>
<s sid="269"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Fig. 4 shows the temperature and velocity profiles at 1-5Rp based on different approximations (see Table 2 for the input parameters).</text></s>
<s sid="270"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Model C1 assumes a constant photoelectron heating efficiency of 93% at all altitudes and photoelectron energies.</text></s>
<s sid="271"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This heating efficiency is appropriate for photoelectrons created by 50eV photons at an electron mixing ratio of xe=0.1 (Cecchi-Pestellini et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="272"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res73" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Model C2 is otherwise similar to C1 but the heating efficiency varies with photoelectron energy and altitude (see below).</text></s>
<s sid="273"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res74" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Models C3 and C4 are also based on C1, but C3 includes the substellar tidal forces in the equations of motion (e.g., Garcia Munoz, 2007) and C4 includes Lyman α cooling.</text></s>
<s sid="274"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>All of these models are based on the outflow boundary conditions for temperature, velocity, and density.</text></s>
<s sid="275"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met22" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Cecchi-Pestellini et al. (2009) also estimated the heating efficiencies for photoelectrons released by photons of energy E≳50eV at different values of the electron mixing ratio xe.</text></s>
<s sid="276"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met23" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We used their heating efficiencies for xe=0.1 in the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="277"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res75" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>They parameterized their results in terms of the vertical column density NH of H.</text></s>
<s sid="278"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj28" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We fitted the heating efficiency as a function of NH for 50eV photons with a regular transmission function, and modified this function accordingly for different cutoff altitudes and heating efficiencies of photons with different energies (see Figs.</text></s>
<s sid="279"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>3 and 4 of Cecchi-Pestellini et al. (2009)).</text></s>
<s sid="280"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res76" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that xe≈0.1 near the temperature peak of our models and thus the results are appropriate for our purposes.</text></s>
<s sid="281"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res77" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, they are only applicable to photons with E≳50eV.</text></s>
<s sid="282"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res78" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We used simple scaling to estimate the heating efficiencies for low energy photons with E&lt;50eV.</text></s>
<s sid="283"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res79" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As NH increases, the heating efficiency for 50eV photons saturates at 93%.</text></s>
<s sid="284"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res80" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We assumed that the saturation heating efficiency for low energy photons is also 93%.</text></s>
<s sid="285"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res81" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In reality, this heating efficiency may be closer to 100% but the difference is small.</text></s>
<s sid="286"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod52" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In order to estimate the altitude dependence of the heating efficiency, we note that the rate of energy deposition by Coulomb collisions between photoelectrons of energy Ep and thermal electrons with a temperature T can be estimated from:(9)-dFEdr=L(Ep,e)Φpene(eVcm-3s-1)where FE is the flux of energy, Φpe is the photoelectron flux (cm-2s-1), ne is the density of thermal electrons (cm-3) andL(Ep,e)=3.37×10-12ne0.03Ep0.94Ep-EeEp-0.53Ee2.36(eVcm2)</text></s>
<s sid="287"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod53" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>with Ee=8.618×10-5Te is the stopping power (Swartz et al., 1971).1</text></s>
<s sid="288"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod54" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Due to a historical precedent, the units here are in cgs.</text></s>
<s sid="289"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod55" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>1 Assuming that all of the energy is deposited by electrons that are thermalized within a path element dr, we can estimate the e-folding length scale for thermalization of photoelectrons with different energies as follows:(10)Λpe≈EpneLWe calculated Λpe for different photoelectrons based on the C1 model, and compared the result with the vertical length scale H of the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="290"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod56" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The latter is either the scale height or Rp, depending on which is shorter.</text></s>
<s sid="291"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod57" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>When Λpe/H≳0.005-0.01 we assumed that the heating efficiency decreases with altitude according to the transmission function for 50eV photons.</text></s>
<s sid="292"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res82" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The limiting value was chosen to obtain a rough agreement with the results of Cecchi-Pestellini et al. (2009) for 50eV photons, and it implies that the heating efficiency approaches zero when Λpe/H≳0.1.</text></s>
<s sid="293"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res83" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We parameterized the result in terms of the column density of H based on the density profiles of the C1 model, and connected our results for low energy photoelectrons smoothly with the results of Cecchi-Pestellini et al. (2009) for photons with E≳50eV.</text></s>
<s sid="294"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We then generated the C2 model from the C1 model with the new heating efficiencies.</text></s>
<s sid="295"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Fig. 5 shows the resulting heating efficiencies for 20, 30, 48, and 100eV photons.</text></s>
<s sid="296"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Fig. 6 shows the volume heating rate due to EUV photons of different energies as a function of pressure based on the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="297"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The maximum temperature of 12,000K is reached near 1.5Rp (p=0.6nbar).</text></s>
<s sid="298"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>This region is heated mainly by EUV photons with wavelengths between 200 and 900Å (E=14-62eV).</text></s>
<s sid="299"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res84" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The saturation heating efficiency of 93% for these photons is higher than the corresponding heating efficiency in the jovian thermosphere (Waite et al., 1983).</text></s>
<s sid="300"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This is because of strong ionization that leads to frequent Coulomb collisions between photoelectrons and thermal electrons.</text></s>
<s sid="301"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Radiation with wavelengths shorter than 300Å (E&gt;40eV) or longer than 912Å (13.6eV) penetrates past the temperature peak to the lower atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="302"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The heating efficiency for photons with E&gt;25eV approaches zero at high altitudes where heating is mostly due to low energy EUV photons.</text></s>
<s sid="303"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The net heating efficiency for the C2 model is ηnet=0.44 (Table 2), which is close to the H50 model.</text></s>
<s sid="304"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The location of the peak and maximum temperature in the C2 model agree with the H50 model, but the temperature at higher altitudes in the C2 model decreases much more rapidly with altitude than in the H50 model.</text></s>
<s sid="305"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Fig. 7 shows the terms in the energy equation based on the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="306"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res85" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In line with previous studies, stellar heating is mainly balanced by adiabatic cooling.</text></s>
<s sid="307"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res86" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Advection cools the atmosphere at low altitudes below the temperature peak, whereas at higher altitudes it acts as a heating mechanism.</text></s>
<s sid="308"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res87" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In fact, above 2Rp the adiabatic cooling rate is higher than the stellar heating rate because thermal energy is transported to high altitudes by advection from the temperature peak.</text></s>
<s sid="309"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res88" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The radiative cooling term that is centered near 1.3Rp arises from recombination following thermal ionization.</text></s>
<s sid="310"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res89" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Recombination following photoionization is included implicitly in the model and the rate is not included in the output.</text></s>
<s sid="311"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res90" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Conduction is not significant at any altitude in the model.</text></s>
<s sid="312"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res91" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that the rates displayed in Fig. 7 balance to high accuracy, thus implying that the simulation has reached steady state.</text></s>
<s sid="313"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res92" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The differences between the C1 and C2 models are subtle.</text></s>
<s sid="314"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res93" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The peak temperatures are similar, and the temperature profiles generally coincide below 3Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="315"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res94" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Above this radius the temperature in the C2 model decreases more rapidly with altitude than in the C1 model and subsequently the sonic point moves to higher altitudes above the model domain.</text></s>
<s sid="316"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res95" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The results indicate that the assumption of a constant photoelectron heating efficiency is appropriate below 3Rp whereas at higher altitudes it changes the nature of the solution.</text></s>
<s sid="317"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res96" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This should not be confused with the assumption of a constant ηnet, which leads to a different temperature profile when compared with either C1 and C2 (see Fig. 3).</text></s>
<s sid="318"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res97" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In general, the maximum and mean temperatures in models C1-C4 are relatively similar.</text></s>
<s sid="319"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res98" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus we conclude that the mean temperature in the thermosphere of HD209458b is approximately 7000K and the maximum temperature is 10,000-12,000K.</text></s>
<s sid="320"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res99" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The substellar tide is included in the C3 model.</text></s>
<s sid="321"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res100" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We included it mainly to compare our results with previous models (Garcia Munoz, 2007; Penz et al., 2008; Murray-Clay et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="322"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res101" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The substellar tide is not a particularly good representation of the stellar tide in a globally averaged sense.</text></s>
<s sid="323"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod58" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In reality, including tides in the models is much more complicated than simply considering the substellar tide (e.g., Trammell et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="324"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod59" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>Compared to the C1 model, the maximum temperature in the C3 model is cooler by ∼1000K and at high altitudes the C3 model is cooler by 1000-2000K.</text></s>
<s sid="325"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs38" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The velocity is faster and hence adiabatic cooling is also more efficient.</text></s>
<s sid="326"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The substellar tide drives supersonic escape (see also, Penz et al., 2008) and the sonic point in the C3 model is at a much lower altitude than in the C1 model (see Section 3.1.3).</text></s>
<s sid="327"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, it is not clear how the sonic point behaves as a function of latitude and longitude.</text></s>
<s sid="328"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Given that the tide is also likely to induce horizontal flows, it cannot be included accurately in 1D models.</text></s>
<s sid="329"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res102" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Murray-Clay et al. (2009) argued that radiative cooling due to the emission of Lyman α photons by excited H is important on close-in EGPs.</text></s>
<s sid="330"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res103" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The photons are emitted when the 2p level of H, which is populated by collisions with thermal electrons and other species, decays radiatively.</text></s>
<s sid="331"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod60" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We included this cooling mechanism in the C4 model by using the rate coefficient from Glover and Jappsen (2007) that includes a temperature-dependent correction to the rate coefficient given by Black (1981).</text></s>
<s sid="332"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod61" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We also included an additional correction factor of 0.1 based on detailed level population and radiative transfer calculations by Menager et al. (2011).</text></s>
<s sid="333"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod62" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>The effect of Lyman α cooling is largest near the temperature peak where the C4 model is 1500K cooler than the C1 model, but generally the difference is not large.</text></s>
<s sid="334"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res104" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that the H Lyman α cooling rate here cannot be generalized as such to other EGPs because the level populations and opacities depend on the thermal structure and composition of the atmosphere.</text></s>
Critical points
<s sid="335"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res105" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As we have pointed out, the location of the sonic point depends on the energy equation through the temperature profile.</text></s>
<s sid="336"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Here we show that the use of the isothermal approximation in estimating the location of the sonic point can lead to significant errors unless the atmosphere really is isothermal.</text></s>
<s sid="337"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The inviscid continuity and momentum equations can be combined to give an expression for the critical point ξc of a steady-state solution (Parker, 1965):(11)-ddξc2ξ2=-1ξ2dc2dξ+2c2ξ3=W2ξ4where ξ=r/r0,c=kT/m is the isothermal speed of sound, W=GMp/r0, and m is the mean atomic weight.</text></s>
<s sid="338"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>It is often assumed that the vertical velocity at the critical point is given by v2=c2(ξc) so that the critical point coincides with the isothermal sonic point (Parker, 1958).</text></s>
<s sid="339"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, Parker (1965) suggested that subsonic solutions are also possible if the density at the base of the flow exceeds a critical value determined from the energy equation.</text></s>
<s sid="340"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In fact, he argued that conduction at the base of the corona may not be sufficient to drive a supersonic solar wind.</text></s>
<s sid="341"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This led him to suggest that supersonic expansion is possible only if there is significant heating of the corona over large distances above the base.</text></s>
<s sid="342"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res106" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For an isothermal atmosphere with a temperature T0, Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="343"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res107" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(11) reduces to the famous result for the altitude of the sonic point (Parker, 1958):(12)ξc=W22c02where W2/c02 is the thermal escape parameter X0 at the lower boundary r0.</text></s>
<s sid="344"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs39" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The isothermal sonic point in the C1 model is located at 7.2Rp where c(ξc)=7.2kms-1.</text></s>
<s sid="345"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res108" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The volume averaged temperature of the C1 model below this point is approximately 7100K.</text></s>
<s sid="346"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res109" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Assuming that r0=Rp, T0=7100K, and m=mH, X0∼16 and Eq.</text></s>
(12) yields ξc∼8.
<s sid="347"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res110" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In this case the analytic result agrees fairly well with the hydrodynamic model if one accounts for partial ionization of the atmosphere by assuming that the mean atomic weight2</text></s>
<s sid="348"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The mean atomic weight can be less than 1 because electrons contribute to the number density but not significantly to the mass density.</text></s>
2 is m=0.9mH.
<s sid="349"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>On the other hand, the isothermal sonic point in the C2 model is at 15.4Rp where c(ξc)=4.1kms-1.</text></s>
<s sid="350"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This is because the temperature gradient of the model is steeper than the corresponding gradient in the C1 model.</text></s>
<s sid="351"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The volume averaged mean temperature below 15Rp in the C2 model is 3900K.</text></s>
<s sid="352"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>With this temperature and m=mH, Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="353"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res111" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(12) predicts a sonic point at 14.6Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="354"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res112" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, at 15Rp the atmosphere is mostly ionized and m=0.6mH.</text></s>
<s sid="355"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res113" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>With this value, the sonic point from Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="356"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res114" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(12) would be located at 8.8Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="357"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res115" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These examples show that there are significant caveats to using Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="358"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>(12) to estimate the altitude of the sonic point on close-in EGPs without accurate knowledge of the temperature and density profiles.</text></s>
<s sid="359"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res116" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A variety of outcomes are possible and it is difficult to develop a consistent criteria for choosing values of T and m that would produce satisfactory results.</text></s>
<s sid="360"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res117" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Another problem is that the atmosphere is not isothermal.</text></s>
<s sid="361"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res118" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In fact, the temperature gradient above the heating peak in models C1-C4 (Table 2) is relatively steep, and in some cases it approaches the static adiabatic gradient (T∝r-1) as defined by Chamberlain (1961).</text></s>
<s sid="362"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res119" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Assuming that the temperature profile can be fitted with c2=c02/ξβ above the heating peak, the estimated values of β for the C1 and C2 models are 0.7 and 0.9, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="363"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We note that the velocity in the C1 model exceeds the isentropic speed of sound (cγ=γkT/m, where γ=5/3) at 9.8Rp, where cγ=8.7kms-1.</text></s>
<s sid="364"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This altitude is significantly higher than the altitude of the isothermal sonic point.</text></s>
<s sid="365"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res120" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The velocity in the C2 model does not exceed the isentropic speed of sound below the upper boundary of 16Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="366"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res121" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus the temperature profile has a significant impact on the nature of the solution and the escape mechanism.</text></s>
<s sid="367"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res122" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This means that estimating the altitude of the sonic point without observations and detailed models for guidance is almost certain to produce misleading results.</text></s>
<s sid="368"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res123" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Past models for the upper atmosphere of HD209458b have predicted a variety of altitudes for the sonic point.</text></s>
<s sid="369"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res124" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>On the other hand, Yelle (2004) pointed out that stellar heating in the thermosphere is mostly balanced by adiabatic cooling and our calculations confirm this.</text></s>
<s sid="370"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Parker (1965) argued that the critical point stretches to infinity when β→1 i.e., as the temperature gradient is close to adiabatic.</text></s>
<s sid="371"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con34" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Based on this, we should perhaps expect that the sonic point on close-in EGPs is located at a fairly high altitude.</text></s>
<s sid="372"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res125" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is confirmed by our hydrodynamic simulations.</text></s>
<s sid="373"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res126" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In all of our models except for one, the sonic point is located significantly above 5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="374"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res127" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The exception is the C3 model, which includes the substellar tide.</text></s>
<s sid="375"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs40" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The isentropic sonic point in this model is located at 3.9Rp, where cγ=8.2kms-1.</text></s>
<s sid="376"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res128" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is because the substellar tide leads to a lower effective value of the potential W.</text></s>
<s sid="377"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res129" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, the tidal potential depends on latitude and longitude, and the substellar results cannot be generalized globally.</text></s>
Mass loss rates
<s sid="378"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res130" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Here we evaluate the mass loss rates based on our models.</text></s>
<s sid="379"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res131" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We define the mass loss rate simply as:(13)Ṁ=4πr2ρv</text></s>
<s sid="380"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res132" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that the solar spectrum that we used in this study contains the total flux of 4×10-3Wm-2 at wavelengths shorter than 912Å (the ionization limit of H) when normalized to 1AU.</text></s>
<s sid="381"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res133" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This value is close to the average solar flux of 3.9×10-3Wm-2 at the same wavelengths (e.g, Ribas et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="382"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>In order to simulate a global average, we divided the flux by a factor of 4 in the model.</text></s>
<s sid="383"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con35" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This means that the incident flux on HD209458b at 0.047AU with wavelengths shorter than 912Å in our model is 0.45Wm-2.</text></s>
<s sid="384"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res134" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The net heating efficiencies given in Table 2 are based on this value.</text></s>
<s sid="385"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res135" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Considering first the models with constant ηnet ranging from 0.1 to 1 (see Section 3.1.1), the mass loss rate varies almost linearly with ηnet from 107kgs-1 and 108kgs-1 while the pressure averaged temperature below 3Rp changes only by 1500K.</text></s>
<s sid="386"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res136" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is because in a hydrodynamic model such as ours the net energy has nowhere else to go but adiabatic expansion and cooling, and thus escape is energy-limited.</text></s>
<s sid="387"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res137" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The bulk of the energy is absorbed below 3Rp, and the mass loss rate is largely set by radiative transfer in this region.</text></s>
<s sid="388"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res138" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The mass loss rate for HD209458b predicted by the C2 model is 4.1×107kgs-1 (ηnet=0.44).</text></s>
<s sid="389"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res139" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The C3 model has the highest mass loss rate, although this rate is only higher by a factor of 1.13 than the mass loss rate in the C1 model.</text></s>
<s sid="390"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res140" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus we predict a mass loss rate of 4-6×107kgs-1 from HD209458b based on the average solar flux at 0.047AU.</text></s>
<s sid="391"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res141" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Garcia Munoz (2007) demonstrated that the mass loss rate is insensitive to the upper boundary conditions even when they have a large impact on the temperature and velocity profiles, particularly at high altitudes.</text></s>
<s sid="392"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res142" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Indeed, complex hydrodynamic models are not required to calculate mass loss rates under energy-limited escape as long as reasonable estimates of the net heating efficiency are available.</text></s>
<s sid="393"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res143" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>It is also important to note that the current estimates of mass loss rates based on the observations (e.g., Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003) are not direct measurements.</text></s>
<s sid="394"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res144" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Instead, they are all based on different models.</text></s>
<s sid="395"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res145" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, models that predict the same mass loss rate can predict different transit depths and models predicting different mass loss rates can match the observations equally well.</text></s>
<s sid="396"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res146" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus the models should not be judged on how well they agree with published mass loss rates but rather on how well they agree with the observed density profiles or transit depths.</text></s>
<s sid="397"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res147" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Hydrodynamic models with realistic heating rates are required to match the observations, and the mass loss rate then follows.</text></s>
<s sid="398"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res148" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The globally averaged mass loss rate of about 4-6×107kgs-1 from HD209458b agrees well with similar estimates calculated by Yelle (2004, 2006) and Garcia Munoz (2007), respectively, but it is significantly larger than the value calculated by Murray-Clay et al. (2009).</text></s>
<s sid="399"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res149" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These authors report a mass loss rate of 3.3×107kgs-1 based on the substellar atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="400"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res150" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>When multiplied by 1/4 this corresponds to a global average rate of about 8.3×106kgs-1.</text></s>
<s sid="401"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res151" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, the substellar mass loss rate is also enhanced by tides, so a comparable global average taking this into account would be even less than 8.3×106kgs-1, which is already roughly a factor of 6 smaller than our calculations.</text></s>
<s sid="402"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res152" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The Murray-Clay et al. (2009) models differ in many respects from the models described here including the treatment of boundary conditions and radiative cooling, the numerical approach, and the adoption of a gray approximation for stellar energy deposition.</text></s>
<s sid="403"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>In order to explore the reason for the disagreement in escape rates, we have modified our model to implement the gray assumption by using the approach described in Murray-Clay et al. (2009) (see Section 3.2).</text></s>
<s sid="404"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Specifically, we adopted an incident flux3</text></s>
<s sid="405"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>By chance the incident flux is equal to the mean solar flux divided by 4 that we used as a 'globally averaged' value.</text></s>
<s sid="406"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res153" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Here, however, it is taken to be the substellar value.</text></s>
<s sid="407"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res154" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>3 of 0.45Wm-2 and a mean photon energy of 20eV.</text></s>
<s sid="408"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res155" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The mass loss rate based on the substellar atmosphere for this model is 2.8×107kgs-1, in good agreement with the Murray-Clay et al. (2009) results.</text></s>
<s sid="409"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res156" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus, the difference between the Murray-Clay et al. (2009) models and the others is due to the gray assumption, and the fact that they estimated the incident flux on HD209458b based on the solar flux integrated between 13eV and 40eV.</text></s>
<s sid="410"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res157" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This energy range contains only about 25% of the total solar flux at energies higher than 13.6eV.</text></s>
<s sid="411"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res158" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Although not discussed by Murray-Clay et al. (2009), the restricted energy range is likely an attempt to account for the fact that the absorption cross section decreases with energy implying that photons of sufficiently high energy will be absorbed too deep in the atmosphere to affect escape or the thermal structure, or composition of the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="412"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res159" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Whether this is true, however, depends on the composition and temperature of the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="413"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res160" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The gray assumption also fails to include the fact that the net heating efficiency increases with higher photon energy.</text></s>
<s sid="414"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res161" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These difficulties highlight the basic problem with a gray model, that the results can only be accepted with confidence if verified by a more sophisticated calculation or direct observations.</text></s>
Constraints from kinetic theory
<s sid="415"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res162" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Hydrodynamic models should be consistent with kinetic theory of rarefied media even if the modeled region is below the exobase.</text></s>
<s sid="416"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res163" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is because the atmosphere is escaping to space, and the density decreases with altitude, falling below the fluid regime at some altitude above the exobase.</text></s>
<s sid="417"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res164" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Therefore the conditions in the exosphere affect the flow solutions even below the exobase.</text></s>
<s sid="418"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con36" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Inappropriate use of the hydrodynamic equations can lead one to overestimate the flow velocity and mass loss rate, and these errors also affect the temperature and density profiles.</text></s>
<s sid="419"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con37" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus it is important to demonstrate that the hydrodynamic solutions agree with constraints from kinetic theory (e.g., Volkov et al., 2011a,b).</text></s>
<s sid="420"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj29" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>As an example, we calculated Kn0 and X0 (see Section 2.1.2) based on the C1 and C2 models.</text></s>
<s sid="421"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res165" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The Knudsen number Kn depends on the mean collision frequency, and it is much smaller than unity at all altitudes below 16Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="422"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res166" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus the exobase is located above the model domain (see also Murray-Clay et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="423"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res167" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Calculating values for X0 is complicated by the broad stellar heating profile.</text></s>
<s sid="424"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res168" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We consider the region where stellar heating is negligible to be where the flux of energy(14)E∞=FccpT+12v2-GMpr-κr2∂T∂ris approximately constant.</text></s>
<s sid="425"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res169" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This criteria is consistent with the equations of motion, and it means that r0 that should be used to calculate X0 is above the upper boundary of our model because significant stellar heating persists at all altitudes.</text></s>
<s sid="426"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj30" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Thus we evaluated values of X near the upper boundary for guidance.</text></s>
<s sid="427"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj31" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We also calculated the values with both the mass of the proton (XH) and the mean atomic weight (X).</text></s>
<s sid="428"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs41" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In the C1 model, XH decreases with altitude, and above 11.4Rp it has values of less than 3.</text></s>
<s sid="429"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs42" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The mean atomic weight near the upper boundary is ∼0.6amu, and thus the general value of X&lt;2 above 11.1Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="430"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs43" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The sonic point in the C1 model is below 11Rp, and it is in a region where stellar heating is significant.</text></s>
<s sid="431"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res170" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In the C2 model, both X and XH are greater than 3 at all altitudes below 16Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="432"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res171" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In fact, X increases with altitude above 9Rp because the temperature gradient parameter exceeds unity.</text></s>
<s sid="433"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con38" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus the values X in the C1 and C2 models are consistent with the difference in altitude between the sonic points in these models (see Section 3.1.3).</text></s>
<s sid="434"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con39" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Indeed, our results show, in line with Parker's original ideas about the solar wind, that supersonic escape is possible if there is significant heating of the atmosphere over large distances above the temperature peak.</text></s>
<s sid="435"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con40" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Such heating flattens the temperature gradient and brings the sonic point closer to the planet.</text></s>
<s sid="436"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res172" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that there are some caveats to applying the simple criteria based on Kn0 and X0 to close-in extrasolar planets.</text></s>
<s sid="437"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res173" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The upper atmospheres of these planets are strongly ionized, and the DSMC simulations of Volkov et al. (2011a,b) apply only to neutral atmospheres.</text></s>
<s sid="438"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res174" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Partly due to ionization, the collision frequencies in the thermospheres of close-in planets are also high.</text></s>
<s sid="439"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res175" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Further, the atmospheres are affected by a broad stellar heating profile in altitude whereas the DSMC calculations do not include any diabatic heating.</text></s>
<s sid="440"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res176" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, the results of Volkov et al. (2011a,b) also indicate that consistency with kinetic theory can be enforced approximately by applying the modified Jeans conditions to the hydrodynamic model at some altitude close to the exobase.</text></s>
<s sid="441"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res177" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This result is likely to be more general, and it applies to ionized atmospheres as long as ambipolar diffusion is taken into account (see Section 2.1.2).</text></s>
<s sid="442"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res178" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We compared the temperature and velocity profiles from the C1 and C2 models with results from similar models C5 and C6 that use the modified Jeans conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="443"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res179" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Note again that our version of the modified Jeans conditions includes the polarization electrostatic field that is required in strongly ionized media.</text></s>
<s sid="444"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs44" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Fig. 8 shows the temperature and velocity profiles from the models.</text></s>
<s sid="445"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res180" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>There is no difference between the C5 model and the C1 model as long as the upper boundary of the C5 model is at a sufficiently high altitude.</text></s>
<s sid="446"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res181" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In this case we extended it to 36Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="447"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res182" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>When the upper boundary is placed at lower altitudes, the flow decelerates and the temperature increases near the upper boundary.</text></s>
<s sid="448"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res183" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A comparison between the C2 and C6 models provides an example of the difference that can arise when the modified Jeans boundary conditions are used significantly below the exobase.</text></s>
<s sid="449"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con41" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>A better agreement is achieved if the upper boundary of the C6 model is placed at a slightly higher altitude.</text></s>
<s sid="450"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con42" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In summary, we have shown that the C1 and C2 models are both consistent with kinetic theory.</text></s>
<s sid="451"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con43" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We note that extending the models to 16Rp or higher is not necessarily justified because it ignores the complications arising from the possible influence of the stellar tide, the stellar wind, and interactions of the flow with the magnetic field of the planet or the star.</text></s>
<s sid="452"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con44" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We placed the upper boundary at a relatively high altitude to make sure that the boundary is well above the region of interest, but generally we do not consider our results to be accurate above 3-5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="453"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con45" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Instead, our results provide robust lower boundary conditions for multidimensional models of the escaping material outside the Roche lobe of the planet.</text></s>
<s sid="454"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con46" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Such models often cannot include detailed photochemical or thermal structure calculations.</text></s>
<s sid="455"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con47" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The results from the more complex models can then be used to constrain the upper boundary conditions in 1D models.</text></s>
<s sid="456"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con48" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This type of an iteration is a complex undertaking, and it will be pursued in future work.</text></s>
Density profiles
<s sid="457"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con49" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In this section we provide a qualitative understanding of the density profiles and transition altitudes that affect the interpretation of the observations.</text></s>
<s sid="458"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con50" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Based on the gas giants in the Solar System it might be expected that heavy species undergo diffusive separation in the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="459"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con51" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>If this were the case, the transit depths in the O I, C II, and Si III lines (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2004; Linsky et al., 2010) should not be significantly higher than the transit depth at visible wavelengths.</text></s>
<s sid="460"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con52" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>It is therefore important to explain why diffusive separation does not take place in the thermosphere of HD209458b, and to clarify why H and O remain mostly neutral while C and Si are mostly ionized.</text></s>
<s sid="461"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con53" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Also, doubly ionized species such as Si2+ are not common in planetary ionospheres, and their presence needs to be explained.</text></s>
<s sid="462"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con54" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In order to do this, we modeled the ionization and photochemistry of the relevant species, and prove that diffusive separation does not take place.</text></s>
<s sid="463"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res184" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In order to illustrate the results, Fig. 9 shows the density profiles of H, H+, He, He+, O, O+, C, C+, Si, Si+, and Si2+ from the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="464"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res185" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The location of the H/H+ transition obviously depends on photochemistry, but it also depends on the dynamics of escape.</text></s>
<s sid="465"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res186" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>With a fixed pressure at the lower boundary, a faster velocity leads to a transition at a higher altitude.</text></s>
<s sid="466"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res187" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus the transition occurs near 3.1Rp in the C2 model whereas in the C1 and C3 models it occurs at 3.8Rp and 5Rp, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="467"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res188" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These results disagree with Yelle (2004) and Murray-Clay et al. (2009) who predicted a lower transition altitude, but they agree qualitatively with the solar composition model of Garcia Munoz (2007).</text></s>
<s sid="468"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res189" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>They also agree with the empirical constraints derived by Koskinen et al. (2010a) from the observations.</text></s>
<s sid="469"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con55" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Once again, the differences between the earlier models and our work arise from different boundary conditions, and assumptions regarding heating rates and photochemistry.</text></s>
<s sid="470"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res190" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We demonstrate this by reproducing the results of Murray-Clay et al. (2009) with our model.</text></s>
<s sid="471"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod63" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In order to do so, we set the lower boundary to 30nbar with a temperature of 1000K, and included the substellar tide in the equations of motion.</text></s>
<s sid="472"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod64" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We only included H, H+, and electrons in the model, and used the recombination rate coefficient and Lyman α cooling rate from Murray-Clay et al. (2009).</text></s>
<s sid="473"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod65" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>We also calculated the heating and ionization rates with the gray approximation by assuming a single photon energy of 20eV for the stellar flux of 0.45Wm-2 at the orbital position of HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="474"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs45" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Fig. 10 shows the density profiles of H and H+ based on this model (hereafter, the MC09 model).</text></s>
<s sid="475"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs46" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The H/H+ transition in the MC09 model occurs near 1.4Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="476"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res191" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>If we replace the gray approximation with the full solar spectrum in this model, the H/H+ transition moves higher to 2-3Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="477"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res192" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is because photons with different energies penetrate to different depths in the atmosphere, extending the heating profile in altitude around the heating peak.</text></s>
<s sid="478"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con56" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This is why the temperature at the 30nbar level in the C2 model is 3800K and not 1000K.</text></s>
<s sid="479"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa7" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>In order to test the effect of higher temperatures in the lower thermosphere, we extended the MC09 model to p0=1μbar (with T0=1300K) and again used the full solar spectrum for heating and ionization.</text></s>
<s sid="480"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res193" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>With these conditions, the H/H+ transition moves up to 3.4Rp, in agreement with the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="481"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res194" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We conclude that the unrealistic boundary conditions and the gray approximation adopted by Murray-Clay et al. (2009) and Guo (2011) lead to an underestimated overall density of H and an overestimated ion fraction.</text></s>
<s sid="482"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res195" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus their density profiles yield a H Lyman α transit depth of the order of 2-3% i.e., not significantly higher than the visible transit depth.</text></s>
<s sid="483"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res196" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that Yelle (2004) also predicted a relatively low altitude of 1.7Rp for the H/H+ transition - despite the fact that his model does not rely on the gray approximation and the lower boundary is in the deep atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="484"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res197" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The reason for the low altitude of the H/H+ transition in this case is the neglect of heavy elements.</text></s>
<s sid="485"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs47" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In the absence of heavy elements, H3+ forms near the base of the model and subsequent infrared cooling balances the EUV heating rates.</text></s>
<s sid="486"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res198" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This prevents the dissociation of H2 below the 10nbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="487"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res199" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In reality, reactions with OH and thermal decomposition dissociate H2 near the 1μbar level (see Section 2.1.1) and cooling by H3+ is negligible at all altitudes.</text></s>
<s sid="488"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res200" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>It should be noted that even if H2 does not initially dissociate, H3+ can be removed from the lower thermosphere in reactions with carbon and oxygen species (e.g., Garcia Munoz, 2007) unless these species undergo diffusive separation.</text></s>
<s sid="489"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res201" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The subsequent lack of radiative cooling will then dissociate H2 again near the 1μbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="490"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res202" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In our models, charge exchange with oxygen (reactions R14 and R15 in Table 1) dominates the photochemistry of H below 3Rp and charge exchange with silicon (R25, R26) is also important below 1.4Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="491"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res203" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These reactions are secondary in a sense that they require the ions to be produced by some other mechanism.</text></s>
<s sid="492"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res204" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In fact, H+ is mainly produced by photoionization (P1), although thermal ionization (R3) is also important near the temperature peak.</text></s>
<s sid="493"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res205" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The production rates are mainly balanced by loss to radiative recombination (R1).</text></s>
<s sid="494"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res206" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The net chemical loss timescale for H is longer than the timescale for advection above 1.7Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="495"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res207" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This allows advection from below to replenish H at higher altitudes.</text></s>
<s sid="496"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res208" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The density profiles of O and O+ are strongly coupled to H and H+ by charge exchange (see also Garcia Munoz, 2007).</text></s>
<s sid="497"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res209" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As a result, the O/O+ transition occurs generally near the H/H+ transition.</text></s>
<s sid="498"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res210" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For instance, in the C2 model it is located near 3.4Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="499"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res211" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The same is not true of carbon.</text></s>
<s sid="500"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res212" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The C/C+ transition occurs at a much lower altitude than the H/H+ and O/O+ transitions.</text></s>
<s sid="501"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res213" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For instance, in the C2 model it is located near 1.2Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="502"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res214" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>C+ is mainly produced by photoionization (P4), although thermal ionization (R8) and charge exchange with He+ (R13) are also important near the temperature peak.</text></s>
<s sid="503"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res215" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The production is balanced by loss to radiative recombination (R10).</text></s>
<s sid="504"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res216" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The chemical loss timescale for C is shorter than the timescale for advection below 1.8Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="505"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res217" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus advection is unable to move the C/C+ transition to altitudes higher than 1.2Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="506"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res218" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Silicon is almost fully ionized near the lower boundary of the model.</text></s>
<s sid="507"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res219" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Much of the Si+ below 4Rp is produced by charge exchange of Si with H+, He+, and C+ (R22, R23, R24).</text></s>
<s sid="508"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con57" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The low ionization potential of Si (8.2eV) means that Si+ can also be produced by thermal ionization (R18), and photoionization (P6) by stellar FUV radiation and X-rays that propagate past the EUV heating peak.</text></s>
<s sid="509"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con58" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Above 4Rp, Si+ is mostly produced by photoionization.</text></s>
<s sid="510"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res220" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Linsky et al. (2010) suggested that the balance of Si+ and Si2+ depends on charge exchange with H+ and H, respectively, and our results confirm this.</text></s>
<s sid="511"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res221" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, the location of the Si+/Si2+ transition also depends on the dynamics.</text></s>
<s sid="512"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res222" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For instance, in the C2 model it occurs near 5.8Rp while in the C1 model it occurs near 8.5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="513"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res223" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus slow outflow and high temperatures favor Si2+ as the dominant silicon species as long as the flux constant is high enough to overcome diffusive separation (Paper II).</text></s>
<s sid="514"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res224" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We have now explained the presence of the atoms and ions that have been detected in the thermosphere of HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="515"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res225" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Due to advection and charge exchange, H and O are predominantly neutral up to about 3Rp and give rise to the observed transit depths in the H Lyman α and O I lines.</text></s>
<s sid="516"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res226" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Carbon, on the other hand, is ionized at a low altitude and thus C+ is also detectable in the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="517"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res227" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Si+ is the dominant silicon species below 5Rp, but charge exchange with H ensures that there is also a significant abundance of Si2+ in the atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="518"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res228" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that these conclusions are only valid if the heavier species are carried along to high altitudes by the escaping hydrogen.</text></s>
<s sid="519"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res229" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We show that this is the case below in Section 3.2.2.</text></s>
<s sid="520"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res230" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The EUV ionization peak (EIP) layer</text></s>
<s sid="521"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met24" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Koskinen et al. (2010b) explored the properties of the ionospheres of EGPs at different orbital distances from a Sun-like host star by using a hydrostatic general circulation model (GCM) that also includes realistic heating rates, photochemistry, and transport of constituents.</text></s>
<s sid="522"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res231" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>They predicted that the EIP layer on HD209458b is centered at 1.35Rp where the electron density is ne=6.4×1013m-3 and xe∼3×10-2.</text></s>
<s sid="523"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res232" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In the C2 model, the EIP layer is centered at 1.3Rp (p=2nbar) where ne=4.4×1013m-3 and xe=3.7×10-2.</text></s>
<s sid="524"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res233" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The vertical outflow velocity at 1.3Rp is 90ms-1.</text></s>
<s sid="525"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res234" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus the results of Koskinen et al. (2010b) were not significantly affected by the simplifying assumptions of the GCM.</text></s>
<s sid="526"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res235" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This means that hydrostatic GCMs can be extended to relatively low pressures as long as the escape rates are incorporated as boundary conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="527"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj32" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We also calculated the plasma frequency based on the electron densities in the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="528"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con59" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This constrains the propagation of possible radio emissions from the ionosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="529"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res236" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The ordinary plasma frequency ωp/2π exceeds 12MHz at all altitudes below 5Rp and reaches a maximum of almost 64MHz in the EIP layer.</text></s>
<s sid="530"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con60" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This presents a limitation on the detection of radio emissions from the ionospheres of close-in EGPs.</text></s>
<s sid="531"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con61" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Any emissions that originate from the ionosphere at 1-5Rp and have frequencies lower than 10-70MHz can be screened out by the ionosphere itself.</text></s>
<s sid="532"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>We note that a detection of radio emissions from an EGP has not yet been achieved (e.g., Bastian et al., 2000; Lazio and Farrell, 2007; Lecavelier des Etangs et al., 2011; Grieß meier et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="533"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Such a detection would be an important constraint on the magnetic field strength and the ionization state of the source region (e.g., Grieß meier et al., 2007).</text></s>
<s sid="534"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con62" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Models of the ionosphere are required to predict radio emissions from the possible targets.</text></s>
<s sid="535"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con63" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The escape of heavy atoms and ions</text></s>
<s sid="536"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con64" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In this section we verify a posteriori that the velocity and temperature differences between different species in the thermosphere of HD209458b are small.</text></s>
<s sid="537"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con65" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This demonstrates that the single fluid approximation of the momentum and energy equations is valid, and that diffusive separation of the heavy species does not take place.</text></s>
<s sid="538"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con66" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our model includes velocity differences between different species by including all of the relevant collisions between them through the inclusion of diffusive fluxes in the continuity equations.</text></s>
<s sid="539"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con67" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, we have explicitly assumed that Tn=Ti=Te, and this assumption in particular needs to be verified.</text></s>
<s sid="540"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con68" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Also, the diffusion approach to the continuity equation is only valid if the velocity differences between the species are reasonably small.</text></s>
<s sid="541"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res237" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We calculated the collision frequencies based on the C2 model, and found that collisions with neutral H dominate the transport of heavy neutral atoms such as O below 3.5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="542"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con69" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>At altitudes higher than this, collisions with H+ are more frequent.</text></s>
<s sid="543"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con70" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In Paper II we demonstrate that a mass loss rate of 6×106kgs-1 is required to prevent diffusive separation of O (the heaviest neutral species detected so far) in the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="544"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res238" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The mass loss rate in our models is Ṁ&gt;107kgs-1 and thus O is dragged along to high altitudes by H.</text></s>
<s sid="545"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con71" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>On the other hand, collisions with H+ dominate the transport of heavy ions such as Si+ as long as the ratio [H+]/[H]≳10-4 (Paper II).</text></s>
<s sid="546"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con72" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This explains why Coulomb collisions in our models are more frequent than heavy ion-H collisions at almost all altitudes apart from the immediate vicinity of the lower boundary.</text></s>
<s sid="547"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res239" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These collisions are much more efficient in preventing diffusive separation than collisions with neutral H.</text></s>
<s sid="548"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res240" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Fig. 11 compares the timescale for diffusion τD for O and Si+ with the timescale for advection τv based on the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="549"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res241" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In both cases, τD≫τv and thus diffusion is not significant.</text></s>
<s sid="550"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res242" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This implies that there are no significant velocity differences between heavy atoms and hydrogen.</text></s>
<s sid="551"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res243" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that Coulomb collisions of doubly ionized species with H+ are more frequent than collisions between a singly ionized species and H+.</text></s>
<s sid="552"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res244" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus diffusion is even less significant for a species like Si2+.</text></s>
<s sid="553"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res245" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We verified these results from our simulations by switching diffusion off in the model and rerunning the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="554"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res246" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As a result the density of the heavy atoms and ions increased slightly at high altitudes, but the differences are not significant - the results were nearly identical to the density profiles of the original simulation.</text></s>
<s sid="555"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con73" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We note that the atmosphere can also be mixed by vertical motions associated with circulation that are sometimes parameterized in one-dimensional models by the eddy diffusion coefficient Kzz (e.g., Moses et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="556"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con74" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This mechanism is efficient in bringing the heavy elements to the lower thermosphere but it is unlikely to mix the atmosphere up to 3Rp and beyond.</text></s>
<s sid="557"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con75" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Also, there is no generally accepted method of estimating the degree of global mixing based on circulation models, and most circulation models for EGPs do not adequately treat the relevant energy deposition and forcing mechanisms in the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="558"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res247" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus there is considerable uncertainty over the values of Kzz and rapid escape is a much more likely explanation for the lack of diffusive separation on HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="559"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res248" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In fact, the calculations of Koskinen et al. (2007b) show that the temperature in the thermosphere of planets such as HD209458b is high enough to practically guarantee an effective escape rate.</text></s>
<s sid="560"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res249" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The only way to prevent this is to provide enough radiative cooling to offset most of the XUV flux, but there are no radiative cooling mechanisms efficient enough to achieve this in a thermosphere composed of atoms and ions.</text></s>
<s sid="561"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res250" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As we noted above, the temperatures of the electrons, ions, and neutrals are roughly equal in the thermosphere of HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="562"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod66" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In order to show this, we assumed that photoelectrons share their energy with thermal electrons, which then share this energy further with ions and neutrals.</text></s>
<s sid="563"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res251" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We also assumed that the collisions frequencies between the species are higher than the timescale for advection.</text></s>
<s sid="564"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con76" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>If the velocity differences between the species are negligible, the steady state 5-moment energy equations for thermal electrons and ions (Schunk and Nagy, 2000) can be used to obtain the following approximations4</text></s>
<s sid="565"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con77" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Note that conduction and viscosity are not important in the thermosphere of HD209458b.</text></s>
<s sid="566"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con78" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>4:(15)Te-Ti≈13mimeqRkneνei(16)Ti-Tn≈13mi+mnmiqRkniνinwhere qR is the volume heating rate, and νei and νin are the electron-ion and ion-neutral momentum transfer collision frequencies, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="567"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj33" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We calculated the temperature differences for H, H+, and electrons based on the C2 model.</text></s>
<s sid="568"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res252" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The difference between the electron and ion temperatures decreases with altitude and is mostly less than 2K.</text></s>
<s sid="569"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res253" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The difference between the ion and neutral temperatures, on the other hand, increases with altitude.</text></s>
<s sid="570"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res254" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The ion temperature is approximately 10K higher than the neutral temperature near 5Rp and the difference reaches 150K at 16Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="571"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res255" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In both cases, the temperature differences are negligible compared to the temperature of the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="572"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con79" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Further, the timescale for advection in the C2 model is always significantly longer than the relevant collision timescales.</text></s>
<s sid="573"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con80" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus we have shown that Te≈Ti≈Tn and that Eqs.</text></s>
<s sid="574"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res256" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>(15) and (16) are approximately valid.</text></s>
Discussion and conclusions
<s sid="575"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res257" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We have constructed a new model for the upper atmosphere of HD209458b in order to explain the detections of H, O, C+, and Si2+ at high altitudes around the planet (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003, 2004; Linsky et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="576"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>There are many different interpretations of the observed transits in the H Lyman α line (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003; Ben-Jaffel, 2007, 2008; Holström et al., 2008; Koskinen et al., 2010a), and these interpretations rely on results from models of the upper atmosphere that are based on many uncertain assumptions (see Section 3.1.1 and Koskinen et al. (2010a) for a review).</text></s>
<s sid="577"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res258" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Also, the detection of heavy atoms and ions in the thermosphere is not without controversy, and the detection of Si2+ is particularly intriguing.</text></s>
<s sid="578"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res259" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus these observations present several interesting challenges to modelers.</text></s>
<s sid="579"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res260" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The observed transit depths are large, and substantial abundances of the relevant species are required to explain the observations.</text></s>
<s sid="580"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res261" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, on every planet in the Solar System heavier species are removed from the thermosphere by molecular diffusion and doubly ionized species are not commonly observed.</text></s>
<s sid="581"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res262" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Also, the observations imply that H and O remain mostly neutral in the thermosphere while C and Si are mostly ionized at a relatively low altitude.</text></s>
<s sid="582"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res263" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Hydrodynamic models coupled with chemistry and thermal structure calculations are required to explain the detection of these species in the upper atmosphere and the differences between their density profiles.</text></s>
<s sid="583"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res264" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Ours is the first such model that benefits from repeated detections of both neutral atoms and ions to constrain the composition and temperature.</text></s>
<s sid="584"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res265" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Koskinen et al. (2010a) demonstrated that the H Lyman α transit observations (Ben-Jaffel, 2007, 2008) can be explained with absorption by H in the thermosphere if the base of the hot layer of H is near 1μbar, the mean temperature within the layer is about 8250K, and the atmosphere is mostly ionized above 3Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="585"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res266" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These parameters are based on fitting the data with a simple empirical model of the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="586"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res267" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The density and temperature profiles from our new hydrodynamic model agree qualitatively with these constraints, demonstrating that the basic assumptions of Koskinen et al. (2010a) are reasonable.</text></s>
<s sid="587"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res268" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This confirms once again that a comet-like tail (Vidal-Madjar et al., 2003) or energetic neutral atoms (Holström et al., 2008) are not necessarily required to explain the H Lyman α observations.</text></s>
<s sid="588"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res269" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In line with recent results by Moses et al. (2011) and the empirical constraints mentioned above, we used a photochemical model of the lower atmosphere to show that H2 dissociates near the 1μbar level.</text></s>
<s sid="589"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con81" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Above this level, the lack of efficient radiative cooling and strong stellar EUV heating lead to high temperatures.</text></s>
<s sid="590"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met25" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We constrained the range of possible mean (pressure averaged) temperatures based on the average solar flux by using the hydrodynamic model to calculate temperatures with different heating efficiencies.</text></s>
<s sid="591"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res270" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For net heating efficiencies between 0.1 and 1, the mean temperature below 3Rp varies from 6000K to 8000K.</text></s>
<s sid="592"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res271" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This means that 8000K is a relatively strict upper limit on the mean temperature if the XUV flux of HD209458 is similar to the corresponding flux of the Sun.</text></s>
<s sid="593"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res272" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A mean temperature of 8250K estimated from the observations implies the presence of an additional non-radiative heat source, or that the XUV flux from HD209458 is higher than the average solar flux.</text></s>
<s sid="594"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con82" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Given that our best estimate of the net heating efficiency is 0.44 (see Section 3.1.2), the XUV flux of H209458 would have to be 5-10 times higher than the average solar flux to cause a mean temperature of 8250K (see Section 3.1.1).</text></s>
<s sid="595"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con83" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>If the mean XUV flux of HD209458 is generally higher than the solar flux and the observations took place during stellar maximum, such an enhancement is not impossible.</text></s>
<s sid="596"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con84" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This would also lead to higher outflow velocity and mass loss rate.</text></s>
<s sid="597"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con85" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, the uncertainty in the observed transit depths is also large (Ben-Jaffel, 2008, 2010), and it can accommodate a range of temperatures.</text></s>
<s sid="598"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con86" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Therefore our reference model C2 with a mean temperature of 7200K also agrees qualitatively with the empirical constraints.</text></s>
<s sid="599"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con87" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In this respect, it is interesting to note that with 100× solar flux, the mean temperature is still only 9800K.</text></s>
<s sid="600"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con88" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Temperatures significantly higher than 8000K (e.g., Ben-Jaffel and Hosseini, 2010) therefore imply a strong non-radiative heat source.</text></s>
<s sid="601"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con89" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In contrast to the mean temperature, the velocity and details of the temperature profile depend strongly on the heating efficiency and stellar flux (see Section 3.1.1).</text></s>
<s sid="602"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con90" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>They are also sensitive to the upper and lower boundary conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="603"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con91" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This explains the large range of temperature and density profiles predicted by earlier models that arise from different boundary conditions and assumptions about the stellar flux, radiative transfer, and heating efficiencies.</text></s>
<s sid="604"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con92" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The differences highlight the need for accurate thermal structure calculations that are constrained by the available observations.</text></s>
<s sid="605"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con93" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These calculations are important because the density profiles of the detected species depend on the temperature and velocity profiles, and inappropriate assumptions made by the models can bias the interpretation of the observations.</text></s>
<s sid="606"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con94" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In the absence of stellar gravity, the location of the sonic point and the outflow speed also depend on the heating efficiency.</text></s>
<s sid="607"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res273" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As the heating efficiency increases from 0.1 (in models with the average solar flux), the high altitude temperature increases and the sonic point moves to lower altitudes, reaching down to 4Rp with a net heating efficiency of 1.</text></s>
<s sid="608"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con95" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We found that supersonic solutions are possible as long as there is significant heating over a large altitude range above the temperature peak.</text></s>
<s sid="609"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con96" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This conclusion is supported both by the hydrodynamic model and new constraints from kinetic theory (Volkov et al., 2011a,b).</text></s>
<s sid="610"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con97" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, the isentropic sonic point of the C2 model is located above the model domain.</text></s>
<s sid="611"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con98" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In principle, this is an interesting result but it should be treated with caution.</text></s>
<s sid="612"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con99" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We used parameterized heating efficiencies for low energy photons, and the location of the sonic point is very sensitive to the temperature profile.</text></s>
<s sid="613"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con100" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Also, the stellar tide can enhance the escape rates at the substellar and antistellar points.</text></s>
<s sid="614"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con101" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We did not include this effect because it may produce horizontal flows that cannot be modeled in 1D.</text></s>
<s sid="615"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con102" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>As long as the upper boundary is at a sufficiently high altitude, we found that the results based on the outflow boundary conditions and modified Jeans conditions are identical (see Section 3.1.5).</text></s>
<s sid="616"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con103" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This shows that our simulations are roughly consistent with kinetic theory.</text></s>
<s sid="617"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con104" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>An agreement between these two types of boundary conditions on HD209458b is an interesting theoretical result.</text></s>
<s sid="618"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con105" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>It shows that the boundary conditions for hydrodynamic escape are appropriate in this case.</text></s>
<s sid="619"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con106" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, an upper boundary at 16Rp or higher is not necessarily justified for other reasons because we did not consider the effect of the possible planetary magnetic field, interaction of the atmosphere with the stellar wind, or horizontal transport (e.g., Stone and Proga, 2009; Trammell et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="620"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con107" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We chose an upper boundary at a high altitude in order to preserve the integrity of the solution in our region of interest below 5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="621"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con108" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The purpose of this work is to model energy deposition and photochemistry in this region.</text></s>
<s sid="622"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con109" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These aspects are often simplified in more complex models to a degree that it may be difficult to separate the effect of multiple dimensions and other complications from differences arising simply because of different assumptions about heating efficiencies and chemistry.</text></s>
<s sid="623"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con110" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Also, the uncertainty in the observations does not necessarily justify the introduction of more free parameters to the problem until the basic properties of the thermosphere are better understood.</text></s>
<s sid="624"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con111" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, technically we do not consider our solutions to be accurate far above 3-5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="625"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con112" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Instead, our results provide robust lower boundary conditions for more complex multidimensional models that characterize the atmosphere outside the Roche lobe of the planet.</text></s>
<s sid="626"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con113" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Results from such models can then be used to constrain the upper boundary conditions of the 1D models further.</text></s>
<s sid="627"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mod67" novelty="None" type="Mod"/><text>In order to model the density profiles of the detected species in the ionosphere, we assumed solar abundances of the heavy elements (Lodders, 2003), although this assumption can be adjusted as required to explain the observations (Paper II).</text></s>
<s sid="628"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res274" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As we already stated we found that H2, H2O, and CO dissociate above the 1μbar level, releasing H, O, and C to the thermosphere (see also Moses et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="629"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res275" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We note that the detection of Si2+ in the upper atmosphere implies that silicon does not condense into clouds of forsterite and enstatite in the lower atmosphere as argued by e.g., Visscher et al. (2010).</text></s>
<s sid="630"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res276" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The dominant Si species is then SiO, which dissociates at a similar pressure level as the other molecules.</text></s>
<s sid="631"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res277" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In fact, practically all molecules dissociate below 0.1μbar.</text></s>
<s sid="632"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con114" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This leads to an important simplification in hydrodynamic models of the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="633"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con115" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The complex chemistry of molecular ions does not need to be included as long as the lower boundary is above the dissociation level.</text></s>
<s sid="634"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con116" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We found that the H/H+ transition occurs near 3Rp or, depending on the velocity profile, at even higher altitudes.</text></s>
<s sid="635"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res278" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The O/O+ transition is coupled to the H/H+ transition through charge exchange reactions.</text></s>
<s sid="636"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res279" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus both H and O are mostly neutral up to the boundary of the Roche lobe at 3-5Rp.</text></s>
<s sid="637"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res280" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In contrast, C is ionized near the 1μbar level and C+ is the dominant carbon species in the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="638"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res281" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Si is also ionized near the 1μbar level, and the balance between Si+ and Si2+ is determined by charge exchange with H+ and H, respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="639"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res282" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Si+ is the dominant silicon ion below 5Rp but the abundance of Si2+ is also significant.</text></s>
<s sid="640"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res283" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We found that neutral heavy atoms are dragged to the thermosphere by the escaping H, while heavy ions are transported efficiently by the escaping H+.</text></s>
<s sid="641"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res284" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Thus the advection timescale is much shorter than the diffusion timescale of the detected species, and diffusive separation does not take place in the thermosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="642"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res285" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We also verified that the neutral, ion, and electron temperatures are roughly equal.</text></s>
<s sid="643"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con117" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Taken together, these results imply that the thermospheres of close-in EGPs can differ fundamentally from the gas giant planets in the Solar System.</text></s>
<s sid="644"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con118" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>For instance, the thermosphere of HD209458b is composed mainly of atoms and atomic ions, and diffusive separation of the common heavy species is prevented by the escape of H and H+.</text></s>
<s sid="645"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con119" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>It is important to note, however, that results such as these cannot be freely generalized to other extrasolar planets.</text></s>
<s sid="646"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con120" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>As in the Solar System, each planet should be studied separately.</text></s>
<s sid="647"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con121" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>For instance, the dissociation of molecules depends on the temperature profile that is shaped by the composition through radiative cooling and stellar heating.</text></s>
<s sid="648"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con122" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The mass loss rate and escape velocity, that determine whether diffusive separation takes place or not, depends on the escape mechanism that again depends on the temperature and composition of the upper atmosphere.</text></s>
<s sid="649"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con123" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The results from different models can only be verified by observations that are therefore required for multiple planets if we are to characterize escape in different systems and under different conditions.</text></s>
</BODY>
<OTHER>
Acknowledgments
We are grateful to A.
Volkov for reading the manuscript and providing useful feedback.
We thank H.
Menager, M. Barthelemy, J.-M.
Grießmeier, N.
Lewis, D.
S.
Snowden, and C.
Cecchi-Pestellini for useful discussions and correspondence.
We also acknowledge the &quot;Modeling atmospheric escape&quot; workshop at the University of Virginia and the International Space Science Institute (ISSI) workshop organized by the team &quot;Characterizing stellar and exoplanetary environments&quot; for interesting discussions and an opportunity to present our work.
The calculations for this paper relied on the High Performance Astrophysics Simulator (HiPAS) at the University of Arizona, and the University College London Legion High Performance Computing Facility, which is part of the DiRAC Facility jointly funded by STFC and the Large Facilities Capital Fund of BIS.
SOLAR2000 Professional Grade V2.28 irradiances are provided by Space Environment Technologies.

</OTHER>
</PAPER>