<?xml version="1.0" ?><PAPER><mode2 hasDoc="yes" name="S0925443913001385.tmf1" version="elsevier"/>
<TITLE>Mutations in mitochondrial ribosomal protein MRPL12 leads to growth retardation, neurological deterioration and mitochondrial translation deficiency
</TITLE>
<ABSTRACT>

Abstract
<s sid="1"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Multiple respiratory chain deficiencies represent a common cause of mitochondrial diseases and are associated with a wide range of clinical symptoms.</text></s>
<s sid="2"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We report a subject, born to consanguineous parents, with growth retardation and neurological deterioration.</text></s>
<s sid="3"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Multiple respiratory chain deficiency was found in muscle and fibroblasts of the subject as well as abnormal assembly of complexes I and IV.</text></s>
<s sid="4"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>A microsatellite genotyping of the family members detected only one region of homozygosity on chromosome 17q24.2-q25.3 in which we focused our attention to genes involved in mitochondrial translation.</text></s>
<s sid="5"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>We sequenced MRPL12, encoding the mitochondrial ribosomal protein L12 and identified a c.542C&gt;T transition in exon 5 changing a highly conserved alanine into a valine (p.Ala181Val).</text></s>
<s sid="6"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This mutation resulted in a decreased steady-state level of MRPL12 protein, with altered integration into the large ribosomal subunit.</text></s>
<s sid="7"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Moreover, an overall mitochondrial translation defect was observed in the subject's fibroblasts with a significant reduction of synthesis of COXI, COXII and COXIII subunits.</text></s>
<s sid="8"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Modeling of MRPL12 shows Ala181 positioned in a helix potentially involved in an interface of interaction suggesting that the p.Ala181Val change might be predicted to alter interactions with the elongation factors.</text></s>
<s sid="9"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These results contrast with the eubacterial orthologues of human MRPL12, where L7/L12 proteins do not appear to have a selective effect on translation.</text></s>
<s sid="10"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Therefore, analysis of the mutated version found in the subject presented here suggests that the mammalian protein does not function in an entirely analogous manner to the eubacterial L7/L12 equivalent.</text></s>
Highlights
•
<s sid="11"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>MRPL12 function is not entirely analogous to the eubacterial L7/L12 equivalent.</text></s>
•
<s sid="12"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Mutations in MRPL12 cause translation defects.</text></s>
•
<s sid="13"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Mutations in apparently universal translation factors can affect different OXPHOS complexes.</text></s>
</ABSTRACT>
<BODY>

Introduction
<s sid="14"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The mitochondrial machinery responsible for oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) comprises five enzyme complexes containing approximately 80 proteins of which only 13 are encoded by the mitochondrial genome (mtDNA) [1].</text></s>
<s sid="15"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>OXPHOS deficiencies affecting a single or multiple complexes can result from mutations in either mitochondrial or nuclear genes and are associated with a variety of disease mechanisms [2,3].</text></s>
<s sid="16"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>With the advent of Next Generation Sequencing there is an increasing number of pathogenic mutations being identified that are not solely restricted to the 80 genes encoding OXPHOS components, thus highlighting the importance of mechanisms impacting on mitochondrial gene expression [4,5].</text></s>
<s sid="17"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Combined OXPHOS deficiencies can arise from alterations in mtDNA, its maintenance [6], cardiolipin levels [7,8], or where none of these are affected, from direct defects in synthesis of mitochondrially encoded proteins [9].</text></s>
<s sid="18"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This last group constitutes a heterogeneous mix of patients suffering from a wide range of clinical symptoms making clinical diagnosis difficult [10].</text></s>
<s sid="19"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Genetic diagnosis is yet more elusive in children with mitochondrial disease where unidentified nuclear mutations account for the majority of cases [11].</text></s>
<s sid="20"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This diagnostic problem is compounded by our relatively poor understanding of the complex molecular machinery that drives translation in mitochondria.</text></s>
<s sid="21"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This machinery comprises over a hundred proteins [12], all of which are putative candidate genes for translation deficiencies in human.</text></s>
<s sid="22"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Indeed, translation deficiencies represent a growing cause of multiple OXPHOS deficiencies with several published pathogenic mutations in genes related to the intra-organellar protein synthesis.</text></s>
<s sid="23"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Although many mutations associated with impaired mitochondrial translation currently map to tRNA genes [13] and a few ribosomal RNA (rRNA) [14], the list of nuclear gene mutations is steadily growing as mutations in genes encoding mitochondrial translation factors such as GFM1 (OMIM: 606639) [15,16], TSFM (OMIM: 604723) [17] and TUFM (OMIM: 602389) [18]; mitochondrial aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (RARS2 (OMIM: 611524) [19], DARS2 (OMIM: 610956) [20], YARS2 (OMIM: 610957) [21], SARS2 (OMIM: 612804) [22], HARS2 (OMIM: 600783) [23], AARS2 (OMIM: 612035) [24], MARS2 (OMIM: 609728) [25], EARS2 (OMIM: 612799) [26]), FARS2 (OMIM: 611592) [27]; tRNA-modifying enzymes (PUS1 (OMIM: 608109) [28], TRMU (OMIM: 610230) [29], MTO1 (OMIM: 614667) [30]); other factors (C12orf65 (OMIM: 613541) [31], TACO1 (OMIM: 612958) [32], LRPPRC (OMIM: 607544) [33], C12orf62 (OMIM: 614478) [34]) and mitochondrial ribosomal proteins (MRPS16 (OMIM: 609204) [35], MRPS22 (OMIM: 605810) [36], MRPL3 (OMIM: 607118) [5]) have been successively reported (reviewed in Ref.</text></s>
[14]).
<s sid="24"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Relatively few cases of OXPHOS deficiencies associated with mutations in mitochondrial ribosomal proteins (MRPs) have been described so far.</text></s>
<s sid="25"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>MRPS16 mutations have been described in only one family with agenesis of corpus callosum and dysmorphism.</text></s>
<s sid="26"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>MRPS22 mutations lead to cardiomyopathy, hypotonia and tubulopathy in a first family and Cornelia de Lange-like dysmorphic features, brain abnormalities and hypertrophic cardiomyopathy in another family.</text></s>
<s sid="27"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Finally, we recently identified MRPL3 mutations in four siblings of the same family presenting cardiomyopathy and psychomotor retardation.</text></s>
<s sid="28"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Since the mammalian mitoribosome (55S) is ~2megadalton machine consisting of approximately 80 components that make up the 28S small (SSU) and 39S large subunit (LSU), it is likely that more pathogenic mutations in the constituent polypeptides will be uncovered.</text></s>
<s sid="29"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>One of the substantial differences between the mammalian mitoribosome and those of eubacteria (70S) or the eukaryotic cytosol (80S) is the reversal in the protein to rRNA ratio.</text></s>
<s sid="30"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The 70S and 80S particles contain ~70% rRNA, whilst human mitoribosomes contain ~70% protein.</text></s>
<s sid="31"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This change in the ratio represents both an acquisition of new MRPs as well as loss of bacterial orthologues [37,38].</text></s>
<s sid="32"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>MRPL12 does have a bacterial orthologue, which through its interactions with translation factors is important in protein synthesis regulating both speed and accuracy [39-41].</text></s>
<s sid="33"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Here we investigate the genetic basis of disease in a subject born to consanguineous parents, who initially presented with growth retardation and then neurological distress, with evidence of compromised mitochondrial protein synthesis.</text></s>
<s sid="34"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We have identified the causative mutation to be in MRPL12, encoding a protein of the large subunit of mitochondrial ribosome.</text></s>
<s sid="35"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is an important finding indicating that the function and consequence of dysfunction cannot automatically be extrapolated from an apparent orthologue.</text></s>
<s sid="36"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We show that proteins involved in mitochondrial translation, even close orthologues as submitted here, can defy predictions.</text></s>
<s sid="37"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Moreover, mutations in such genes that should affect all mitochondrially encoded gene products can exert respiratory chain complex specific defects.</text></s>
Materials and methods
<s sid="38"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Analysis of oxidative phosphorylation activities</text></s>
<s sid="39"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Spectrophotometric assays of respiratory chain and complex V enzymes were carried out as previously described [42].</text></s>
<s sid="40"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Mitochondrial suspension from cultured skin fibroblasts was obtained after suspending 50μl of frozen cells in 1ml of mitochondria extraction medium (20mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.2), 250mM sucrose, 2mM EGTA, 40mM KCl, 1mg/ml BSA) supplemented with 0.01% (w/v) digitonin and 10% Percoll (v/v).</text></s>
<s sid="41"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>After 10min at 4°C, the sample was pelleted, washed in extraction medium and pelleted before resuspension in 30μl of extraction medium for respiratory chain enzyme measurements.</text></s>
<s sid="42"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Microsatellite genotyping and mutation screening</text></s>
<s sid="43"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>A genome-wide search for homozygosity was undertaken with 382 pairs of fluorescent oligonucleotides from the Genescan Linkage Mapping Set, version II (Perkin-Elmer) under conditions recommended by the manufacturer.</text></s>
<s sid="44"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Amplified fragments were electrophoresed and analyzed with an automatic sequencer (ABI 377).</text></s>
<s sid="45"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The polymorphic markers had an average spacing of 10cM throughout the genome.</text></s>
<s sid="46"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Genes encoding mitochondrial proteins were selected in Mitocarta [43].</text></s>
<s sid="47"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The exons and exon-intron boundaries of the MRPL12 gene were amplified using specific primers (sequences available on request) with initial denaturation at 96°C - 5min, followed by 30 cycles of 96°C - 30s, 55°C - 30s, 72°C - 30s, and a last extension at 72°C for 10min.</text></s>
<s sid="48"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Amplification products were purified by ExoSapIT (Amersham, Buckinghamshire, UK) and directly sequenced using the PRISM Ready Reaction Sequencing Kit (Perkin-Elmer, Oak Brook, IL) on an automatic sequencer (ABI 3130xl; PE Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA).</text></s>
Cell culture
<s sid="49"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Human skin fibroblasts were cultured in DMEM medium (Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium, Gibco) supplemented with 10% (v/v) fetal calf serum (FCS), 2mM l-glutamine, 50μg/ml uridine, 110μg/ml pyruvate, 10,000U/ml penicillin G and 10,000μg/ml streptomycin.</text></s>
Protein analysis
<s sid="50"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>For blue native-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (BN-PAGE), mitochondria and OXPHOS complexes were isolated as described [44].</text></s>
<s sid="51"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Solubilized OXPHOS proteins (20μg) were loaded on a 4-16% (w/v) polyacrylamide non-denaturing gradient gel (Invitrogen).</text></s>
<s sid="52"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>SDS-PAGE analysis was performed on either solubilized mitochondrial proteins (40μg) or cell lysate (50μg) extracted from cultured skin fibroblasts.</text></s>
<s sid="53"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>After electrophoresis, gels were transferred to a PVDF membrane (GE-Healthcare) and processed for immunoblotting.</text></s>
<s sid="54"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Metabolic labelling of mitochondrial translation products</text></s>
<s sid="55"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>In vitro labeling of mitochondrial translation products was a modification from Chomyn et al. [45].</text></s>
<s sid="56"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Essentially, cultured skin fibroblasts were preincubated in methionine/cysteine-free DMEM (2×10min) followed by a 10min in the presence of emetine (100μg/ml).</text></s>
<s sid="57"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Radiolabel (125μCi/ml EasyTag™ express35S protein labelling mix - NEG772002MC, PerkinElmer) was then added for 1h at 37°C and chased for 1h.</text></s>
<s sid="58"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Cells were harvested in cold 1mM EDTA/PBS, washed 3 times in cold PBS and the pellet resuspended in 30μl PBS containing 1× EDTA free protease inhibitors (Roche) and 1mM PMSF.</text></s>
<s sid="59"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Samples were treated with 2× dissociation buffer (20% (v/v) glycerol, 4% (w/v) SDS, 250mM Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 100mM DTT) and 12U Benzonase nuclease (Novagen) for 1h and separated on a 15% (w/v) SDS-PAGE.</text></s>
<s sid="60"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The gel was fixed overnight (3% (v/v) glycerol, 10% (v/v) acetic acid, 30% (v/v) methanol) and vacuum dried (60°C, 2h).</text></s>
<s sid="61"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Radiolabelled proteins were visualized by PhosphorImage and analyzed with Image-Quant software (Molecular Dynamics, GE Healthcare).</text></s>
<s sid="62"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Homology modeling of the human MRPL12 protein</text></s>
<s sid="63"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The three dimensional structure of the human MRPL12 (residues 64 to 198) was modeled by comparative protein modeling and energy minimization, using the Swiss-Model program (http://swissmodel.expasy.org/) in the automated mode.</text></s>
<s sid="64"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The 2Å coordinate set for the ribosomal protein L12 from Thermotoga maritima (PDB code: 1dd3) was used as a template for modeling the human MRPL12 protein.</text></s>
<s sid="65"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Swiss-Pdb Viewer 3.7 (http://www.expasy.org/spdbv) was used to analyze the structural insight into MRPL12 mutation and visualize the structures.</text></s>
<s sid="66"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Cell lysates, Westerns and isokinetic sucrose gradients</text></s>
<s sid="67"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Cell lysates were prepared from fibroblasts by addition of cold lysis buffer (50mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 130mM NaCl, 2mM MgCl2, 1mM PMSF, 1% (v/v) NP-40) to cell pellets, which were vortexed for 30s, centrifuged at 600g for 2min (4°C) to remove nuclei and the supernatant retained.</text></s>
<s sid="68"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>These were used for standard westerns as described [46].</text></s>
<s sid="69"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Mitochondria were prepared as above and lyzed in 50mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 150mM NaCl, 1mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, protease inhibitor mix (EDTA free, Roche), 1mM PMSF, 10mM MgCl2.</text></s>
<s sid="70"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Mitochondrial lysates (0.3mg) were loaded on a isokinetic sucrose gradient (1ml 10-30% (v/v)) in 50mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.2), 10mM Mg(OAc)2, 40mM NH4Cl, 0.1M KCl, 1mM PMSF, 50μg/ml chloramphenicol), and centrifuged for 2h 15min at 100,000g at 4°C.</text></s>
<s sid="71"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Fractions (100μl) were collected and 10μl aliquots were analyzed directly by western blotting [47].</text></s>
<s sid="72"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Immunodetection was performed using the following primary antibodies: anti-CI-Grim19, CII-SDHA 70kDa, CIII-core2, CIV-COXI, CIV-COXII, CV-subunit β, cyt c, NDUFB8 (mouse monoclonal antibodies, MitoSciences); anti-MRPL3 goat polyclonal, MRPS18B rabbit polyclonal, MRPS25 rabbit polyclonal and ICT1 rabbit polyclonal antibodies (Protein Tech Group, Inc., Chicago); anti-DAP3 mouse monoclonal, POLRMT rabbit polyclonal (Abcam); and anti-Porin, mouse monoclonal antibodies (Invitrogen).</text></s>
<s sid="73"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Anti-MRPL12 rabbit polyclonal antibody was custom made (Eurogentec).</text></s>
<s sid="74"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp35" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Secondary antibody detection was performed using peroxidase-conjugated anti-rabbit, anti-goat or anti-mouse IgG (Abcam or Dako).</text></s>
<s sid="75"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp36" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The signal was generated using ECL+ (Pierce, Rockford, USA) and visualised by phosphorimaging and analyzed by ImageQuant software.</text></s>
RNA and Northern blotting
<s sid="76"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp37" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>RNA was isolated from fibroblasts using Trizol following manufacturer's protocol (Invitrogen).</text></s>
<s sid="77"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp38" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Northern blots were performed as described [48].</text></s>
<s sid="78"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp39" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Briefly, aliquots of RNA (5μg) were electrophoresed through 1.2% (w/v) agarose under denaturing conditions and transferred to GenescreenPlus membrane (NEN duPont) following the manufacturer's protocol.</text></s>
<s sid="79"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Radiolabelled probes were generated using random hexamers on PCR-generated templates corresponding to internal regions of the relevant genes.</text></s>
Results and discussion
Clinical report
<s sid="80"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The subject, a boy, was born to first cousin Roma/Gypsy parents by cesarean section, at 41weeks of pregnancy with severe general hypotrophy (birth weight 2250g, height 48cm, Occipitofrontal Circumference 34cm).</text></s>
<s sid="81"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>His clinical examination at birth was normal and initial investigations failed to identify the cause of his severe hypotrophy (normal blood caryotype, heart ultrasound, bone age, CT scan and metabolic workup).</text></s>
<s sid="82"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>He failed to thrive thereafter and was repeatedly admitted in the first 12months for gradual worsening of his condition (weight and height: -4SD, OFC: -2SD).</text></s>
<s sid="83"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Clinical examination at 10months showed severe denutrition, muscle weakness but detectable deep tendon reflexes and no major trunk hypotonia.</text></s>
<s sid="84"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>He started walking with aid at 12months.</text></s>
<s sid="85"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Basal growth hormone (GH) levels in plasma were normal (0.5ng/ml) but plasma IGF1 was very low (0.07U/ml, normal 0.2).</text></s>
<s sid="86"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Stimulation by ornithine triggered an adequate elevation of plasma GH with correction of plasma IGF1 (GH: 46.9ng/ml, IGF1: 0.2U/ml, and 0.45U/ml following GH administration).</text></s>
<s sid="87"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These results ruled out a dwarfism of endocrine origin.</text></s>
<s sid="88"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Yet, high plasma lactate (3.5 to 4.4mmol/l, normal below 2.2) prompted skeletal muscle, liver and skin biopsies that revealed a multiple respiratory chain enzyme deficiency in muscle and liver homogenate and cultured skin fibroblasts (Table 1) [42].</text></s>
<s sid="89"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>He had a first episode of generalized tonic seizure aged 2years and his neurological condition rapidly worsened following an episode of acute fever (40°C) caused by a respiratory infection.</text></s>
<s sid="90"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>At that age, he had severe denutrition, flat weight curve, no weight and height gain (-5 SD) and a mildly enlarged liver.</text></s>
<s sid="91"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Neurological examination revealed overt psychomotor retardation, severe trunk hypotonia, inability to sit and stand unaided and no speech.</text></s>
<s sid="92"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Intermittent horizontal nystagmus, with cerebellar ataxia and tremor were noted.</text></s>
<s sid="93"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>He had a mild facial dysmorphism, with round face, epicanthic folds, arched palate, short neck, low-set ears and a unique bilateral median palmar crease.</text></s>
<s sid="94"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Brain MRI showed T1 hyposignal and T2 hypersignal of white matter and basal ganglia.</text></s>
<s sid="95"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Rapid aggravation of respiratory conditions required endotracheal intubation and assisted ventilation.</text></s>
<s sid="96"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Plasma lactates rose to 3.3-4.2mmol/l, he gradually developed abnormal limb movements then fell into a deep coma, and died following a cardiac arrest.</text></s>
<s sid="97"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>During the next pregnancy, the mother expected dizygotic twin fetuses.</text></s>
<s sid="98"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A prenatal diagnosis based on assessment of respiratory chain enzyme activities in cultured skin fibroblasts on amniotic fluid was offered.</text></s>
<s sid="99"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Hemoglobin contamination of the samples rendered the very low respiratory chain activities; despite this the activity ratios clearly showed a severe complex IV deficiency in cells from the fetus twins leading to termination of the second pregnancy.</text></s>
<s sid="100"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The same test was normal in the third pregnancy and a normal baby girl was born, now 14years old (Table 1).</text></s>
Blue native-PAGE analysis
<s sid="101"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Whilst skin fibroblasts were propagated for enzyme analysis it was clear that those from the subject harboring the mutation had a reduced doubling time on glucose medium compared to control lines (data available on request).</text></s>
<s sid="102"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Cell extracts were subsequently prepared and SDS-PAGE/western blot analysis revealed reduced steady-state level of COXII subunit, consistent with the decreased CIV activity (Fig. 1A).</text></s>
<s sid="103"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Moreover, we also observed a decreased amount of nuclear encoded protein NDUFB8 (Fig. 1A), which joins late in complex I assembly [44] and is consistent with the low CI activity in the biopsies.</text></s>
<s sid="104"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These decreases were consistent with the BN-PAGE data from fibroblast mitoplasts (Fig. 1B, method as described [49]).</text></s>
<s sid="105"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Both complexes I and IV, detected by anti-GRIM19 antibody or mitochondrially-encoded COXI, were severely decreased in the subject, which in contrast exhibited control levels of complex II (70kDa SDHA subunit) and complex III (Core 2 subunit) (Fig. 1B).</text></s>
<s sid="106"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>No partial complexes were observed.</text></s>
<s sid="107"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Identifying the causative mutation by Microsatellite genotyping and mutation screening</text></s>
<s sid="108"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>In order to identify the causative mutation a genome-wide search for homozygosity was undertaken using 382 polymorphic microsatellite markers (Genescan Linkage Mapping Set, version II (Perkin-Elmer).</text></s>
<s sid="109"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We obtained evidence for homozygosity in all affected individuals at loci D17S785, D17S784, and D17S928 on chromosome 17q24.2-q25.3 (Fig. 2A).</text></s>
<s sid="110"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>No other homozygous region was found with other markers.</text></s>
<s sid="111"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This 32.7cM region was then refined by additional microsatellite markers reducing the critical region to the 25cM interval, defined by loci D17S1352 and D17S928.</text></s>
<s sid="112"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This corresponds to a 8.4Mb physical region containing more than 170 genes, 10 of which encode mitochondrial proteins or proteins predicted to be mitochondrially targeted (FDXR (MIM 103270), ICT1 (MIM 603000), ATP5H (MIM 607196), MRPS7 (MIM 611974), SLC25A19 (MIM 606521), MRPL38 (MIM 611844), PGS1 (NM_024419), MRPL12 (MIM 602375), SLC25A10 (MIM 606794), FASN (MIM 600212)).</text></s>
<s sid="113"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Considering the multiple RC deficiency observed in patient muscle, liver and fibroblasts and the abnormal BN-PAGE pattern reminiscent of translation deficiencies, we focused on genes involved in mitochondrial translation, excluding mutations in MRPS7, MRPL38 and ICT1 by direct sequencing.</text></s>
<s sid="114"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Sequencing of MRPL12 exons and exon-intron boundaries on genomic DNA (primer sequences available on request) from the affected child identified a homozygous c.542C&gt;T transition in exon 5 (RefSeq accession number NM_002949.3, Fig. 2B).</text></s>
<s sid="115"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This mutation changed a highly conserved alanine into a valine (p.Ala181Val, Fig. 2C) and was predicted by Polyphen2 (http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2/) and SIFT (http://sift.jcvi.org/) software to be &quot;probably damaging&quot; and &quot;deleterious&quot; respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="116"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The parents were heterozygous for the mutation, both twin fetuses were homozygous and the healthy girl was wild-type homozygous.</text></s>
<s sid="117"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This mutation was absent from 100 controls of the same ethnic origin and from all SNP databases.</text></s>
<s sid="118"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Further, no additional MRPL12 mutation could be identified in two other unrelated subjects with similar clinical presentation and biochemical defect.</text></s>
<s sid="119"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>To demonstrate the deleterious nature of the p.Ala181Val MRPL12 substitution we used, overexpression of wild-type or mutant human MRPL12 cDNA in the SV40-immortalized fibroblasts but rather recapitulating the respiratory phenotype of the patient fibroblasts, this was found to be lethal.</text></s>
<s sid="120"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Cells stopped growing, became polynucleated and progressively died.</text></s>
<s sid="121"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In silico analysis of the putative impact of A181V substitution</text></s>
<s sid="122"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Human MRPL12 is 27.5% identical in amino acid sequence to the previously crystallized T. maritima L12 ribosomal protein.</text></s>
<s sid="123"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The C-terminal domain (CTD) (107 to end in Escherichia coli) is conserved in evolution [50] and is required for initial binding and GTPase activation for both EF-Tu and EF-G.</text></s>
<s sid="124"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Indeed, both EF-Tu and EF-G have greatly diminished GTPase activity on ribosomes lacking the CTD of L12 [51,52].</text></s>
<s sid="125"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Superimposition of MRPL12 with the Thermus thermophilus 70S ribosome (PDB code: 2WRL) lacking L7/L12 stalk proteins shows that MRPL12 Ala181 is located within this highly conserved region (Fig. 3A).</text></s>
<s sid="126"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Moreover, modeling of MRPL12 shows Ala181 positioned in a helix potentially involved in translation factor interactions (Fig. 3A/B).</text></s>
<s sid="127"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Bacterial L7/L12 CTDs also contain a number of strictly conserved residues that are involved in the initial contact with elongation factors [52,53] and crucial for translation [54].</text></s>
<s sid="128"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Alanine is one of the best helix forming residues and substitutions can therefore have profound energetic effects by perturbing packing interactions or tertiary contacts [55].</text></s>
<s sid="129"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus, the p.Ala181Val change might be predicted to alter interactions with the elongation factors, and since MRPL7/12 bound to elongation factors is predicted to have a higher affinity for the ribosome [54], the mutation may in turn affect both rate and accuracy of mitochondrial translation.</text></s>
Ribosome assembly
<s sid="130"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The steady state level of MRPL12 in the subject's fibroblasts was reduced to 30% of control value (Fig. 4A and B).</text></s>
<s sid="131"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The mt-LSU protein ICT1 was also decreased (~30% of control values) as was MRPL3 (by 37%) suggesting that a consequence of the MRPL12 mutation is a global defect in assembly of the large ribosomal subunit (mt-LSU).</text></s>
<s sid="132"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>In order to estimate the effect of the MRPL12 mutation on assembly of the whole ribosome, we also tested three proteins of the small ribosomal subunit (SSU), MRPS18B, MRPS25 and DAP3.</text></s>
<s sid="133"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These were modestly decreased with levels of ~60-80% of control (Fig. 4A and B).</text></s>
<s sid="134"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Correspondingly, 16S and 12S rRNA levels were decreased by 35% and 22% respectively (Fig. 7A).</text></s>
<s sid="135"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Since porin indicated that there was no compensatory mitochondrial biogenesis and staining of the mitochondrial network with tetramethylrhodamine methyl ester showed no significant alteration in amount or distribution of mitochondria (AR and ZCL unpublished observation) we conclude that the MRPL12 mutation destabilizes the protein resulting in less mt-LSU and to a lesser extent of the small subunit.</text></s>
<s sid="136"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In order to determine whether the MRPL12 mutation also induced changes in composition and assembly of the mitochondrial ribosomal large and small subunits, mitochondrial lysates from cultured fibroblasts (subject and control) were fractionated on isokinetic sucrose gradients (10-30%, as in Ref.</text></s>
[47]).
<s sid="137"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>If assembly of either the large subunit or the entire ribosome was affected then the distribution of individual ribosomal proteins would change within the gradient profile.</text></s>
<s sid="138"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>On analysis MRPL12 from the patient was substantially decreased in all fractions but detectable in the fractions consistent with mt-LSU; however it was noticeably absent from the free pool (fractions 1 and 2, Fig. 5).</text></s>
<s sid="139"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This was in contrast to the control that exhibited a pool of free MRPL12, which has been reported to interact with POLRMT [56].</text></s>
<s sid="140"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>MRPL3 was also slightly reduced in subject cells but remained in fractions consistent with the large subunit.</text></s>
<s sid="141"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The MRPL12 mutation impacted more modestly on the small ribosomal subunit, with DAP3 apparently unaffected and MRPS18B found in lower amounts only in fractions 4 and 5 but otherwise with similar steady state levels and distribution profile compared to control.</text></s>
<s sid="142"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>Since POLRMT and MRPL12 have been published as interactors, we analyzed both the steady state level and gradient distribution of POLRMT to see if these were affected by the MRPL12 mutation.</text></s>
<s sid="143"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Overall levels in the subject sample were decreased to 63% of control value (Fig. 5B) but distribution in the gradient appeared largely unaffected with the exception of fraction 11, where levels were lower than control (Fig. 5A bottom panels).</text></s>
In vitro translation
<s sid="144"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>To identify any effect on global mitochondrial protein synthesis, we studied de novo mitochondrial translation in cultured skin fibroblasts, as described in Ref.</text></s>
[45].
<s sid="145"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Although there was an overall decrease in mitochondrial translation compared to control, densitometric profiles showed that certain polypeptides were more affected than others (Fig. 6).</text></s>
<s sid="146"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In particular, there was a significant reduction of synthesis of COXI, COXII and COXIII subunits.</text></s>
<s sid="147"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Consistent with the respiratory chain activities, complex I polypeptides were affected to a lesser extent and cytochrome b from complex III appears to be spared.</text></s>
<s sid="148"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Despite the potential role of MRPL12 in translational accuracy, no aberrant translation product could be detected.</text></s>
<s sid="149"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Steady-state level of mitochondrial transcripts</text></s>
<s sid="150"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>MRPL12 has been shown to interact with the mitochondrial RNA polymerase (POLRMT) and to stimulate mitochondrial transcription [56,57].</text></s>
<s sid="151"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Since the steady-state level of POLRMT in subject fibroblasts was modestly decreased, we analyzed the steady-state level of mitochondrial transcripts to see if these were similarly affected.</text></s>
<s sid="152"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Northern blots on control and subject fibroblast RNA did not show a decrease that paralleled the reduced levels of POLRMT.</text></s>
<s sid="153"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In fact there was a slight increase of MTND1 in subject cells compared to control, whilst MTCOI and MTCYB transcripts appeared unaffected (Fig. 7A).</text></s>
<s sid="154"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Conversely, as mentioned earlier, the levels of 16S and 12S rRNA were modestly decreased (Fig. 7A) in a proportion that was consistent with the loss of MRPs with which they would associate.</text></s>
<s sid="155"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Analysis of the distribution on 10-30% (w/v) sucrose gradients (as in Ref.</text></s>
<s sid="156"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>[58]) of two mt-mRNAs, MTCOI and MTND1, showed a relatively similar pattern for subject and control but in each case a smaller proportion of the subject transcript sedimented to the final fraction (data available on request).</text></s>
<s sid="157"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This was also true for the 16S and 12S rRNA.</text></s>
<s sid="158"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>As no major redistribution in the sucrose gradient was observed, it is unlikely that the MRPL12 mutation causes a global defect in assembly of the mitoribosome.</text></s>
<s sid="159"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Since the levels of POLRMT were slightly decreased with normal or slightly elevated levels of mt-mRNA, we assessed the stability of transcripts to see if the half-lives were extended to compensate for reduced synthesis in order to maintain normal steady state levels.</text></s>
<s sid="160"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Mitochondrial transcription was poisoned by addition of low levels of ethidium bromide and RNA prepared at numerous time points thereafter (0-16h).</text></s>
<s sid="161"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Densitometry of the subsequent Northern demonstrated that half-lives of MTCOI and MTND1 were extended, the latter more so, consistent with the modest increase in steady state levels (data available on request).</text></s>
<s sid="162"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>MRPL12 dimerization and interaction with the mitoribosome</text></s>
<s sid="163"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>MRPL12 is the orthologue of eubacterial L7/L12, where L7 is identical to L12 except that it is N-terminal acetylated.</text></s>
<s sid="164"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>L7/L12 is also phosphorylated, which can affect both conformation and binding to partner ribosomal proteins (reviewed in Ref.</text></s>
[37]).
<s sid="165"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This modification has now been confirmed to be present in mammalian MRPL12 [59].</text></s>
<s sid="166"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In eubacteria, association of L7/12 to the large subunit takes place via the L10 protein such that two L7/L12 heterodimers normally associate per LSU [60].</text></s>
<s sid="167"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Interestingly these dimers are actively exchanged on the 70S molecule without disruption of the ribosomal particle [54,61].</text></s>
<s sid="168"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The dimerization status and number of dimers attached to the human 55S has not been clarified.</text></s>
<s sid="169"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>In order to identify if the stoichiometry of MRPL12 per mt-LSU was altered as a consequence of the mutation, we performed immunoprecipitation (IP) analysis on subject and control fibroblasts using antibodies to MRPL12.</text></s>
<s sid="170"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Analysis of the immunoprecipitate demonstrated similar levels small subunit polypeptides including DAP3 and MRPS18B in subject and control samples.</text></s>
<s sid="171"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In contrast, the total amount of MRPL12 was reduced (Fig. 7B).</text></s>
<s sid="172"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In the patient the IP is restricted to MRPL12 in the large subunit or the fully assembled 55S with the total amount of MRPL12 being reduced as it lacks the &quot;free&quot; population.</text></s>
<s sid="173"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The densitometric measurements indicate that the patient IP has ~49% MRPL12 compared to control, in accordance with the gradient and steady state data.</text></s>
<s sid="174"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>ICT1 appears to be sensitive to the MRPL12 levels and so is reduced in both the IP (~58% of control) and in the steady state westerns (Fig. 4).</text></s>
<s sid="175"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The lower levels of MRPL12 could reflect loss of multimerization but since the region in the bacterial protein involved in multimerization is towards the N-terminus [62], this mutation is unlikely to have an impact on dimer/multimer formation.</text></s>
<s sid="176"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The translation factor bound dimer has been suggested to have an increased affinity for the ribosome [54,61].</text></s>
<s sid="177"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con34" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus a possible explanation is that the mutation affects translation factor binding, thereby reducing the affinity of the mutant MRPL12 for the ribosome.</text></s>
<s sid="178"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con35" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>If this were the case, however, then we would expect an increase in the pool of free MRPL12 whereas the subject exhibits a reduced pool of free MRPL12, which interacts with POLRMT [57].</text></s>
<s sid="179"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con36" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The immunoprecipitation was performed using an MRPL12 specific antibody and so should contain all free MRPL12, MRPL12 associated with uncomplexed mt-LSU and MRPL12 as part of the fully assembled 55S.</text></s>
<s sid="180"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con37" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Since the levels of small and large subunit proteins appeared to be similar in subject and control, these data suggest that the mt-LSU and 55S assembly are unaffected by the mutation consistent with the gradient data for the protein and RNA components.</text></s>
<s sid="181"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con38" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus the reduced levels of mutant MRPL12 in this subject correspond to i) loss of stability, ii) a decrease in the free pool that is believed to interact with the mitochondrial RNA polymerase and iii) reduced translation potentially resulting from decreased interactions with translation factors, but with no detectable increase in aberrant translation products.</text></s>
<s sid="182"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con39" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In conclusion, we report a mutation in human MRPL12 that results in growth retardation and neurological distress.</text></s>
<s sid="183"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con40" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>It is interesting to note that whereas the eubacterial orthologue is not essential for in vitro translation assays, this MRPL12 mutation induces a mitochondrial translation defect in human.</text></s>
<s sid="184"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con41" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This lack of predictability between orthologous proteins makes it important to examine and not assume what impact mutant forms or loss of MRPs may have on mitochondrial homeostasis and the resulting clinical manifestation.</text></s>
<s sid="185"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con42" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The data presented here provide another example, amongst a growing list of translation factors, which despite their apparent universal contribution to the synthesis of all mitochondrially encoded proteins, has a selective effect on the different oxidative phosphorylation complexes.</text></s>
</BODY>
<OTHER>
Acknowledgments
This research was supported in part by the Association Française contre les Myopathies (A.F.M.) and the French Agence Nationale pour la Recherche (A.N.R.).
Z.M.A.C.-L. would like to thank The Wellcome Trust [096919/Z/11/Z], and the BBSRC [BB/F011520/1] for continuing support.
We thank Alexander Tzagoloff for studies on ΔMRPL12 yeast strain.

</OTHER>
</PAPER>