<?xml version="1.0" ?><PAPER><mode2 hasDoc="yes" name="S0967064513002774.tmf1" version="elsevier"/>
<TITLE>Short-term metabolic and growth responses of the cold-water coral Lophelia pertusa to ocean acidification
</TITLE>
<ABSTRACT>

Abstract
<s sid="1"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Cold-water corals are associated with high local biodiversity, but despite their importance as ecosystem engineers, little is known about how these organisms will respond to projected ocean acidification.</text></s>
<s sid="2"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Since preindustrial times, average ocean pH has decreased from 8.2 to ~8.1, and predicted CO2 emissions will decrease by up to another 0.3 pH units by the end of the century.</text></s>
<s sid="3"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This decrease in pH may have a wide range of impacts upon marine life, and in particular upon calcifiers such as cold-water corals.</text></s>
<s sid="4"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Lophelia pertusa is the most widespread cold-water coral (CWC) species, frequently found in the North Atlantic.</text></s>
<s sid="5"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Here, we present the first short-term (21 days) data on the effects of increased CO2 (750ppm) upon the metabolism of freshly collected L. pertusa from Mingulay Reef Complex, Scotland, for comparison with net calcification.</text></s>
<s sid="6"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Over 21 days, corals exposed to increased CO2 conditions had significantly lower respiration rates (11.4±1.39 SE, µmolO2g-1tissuedryweighth-1) than corals in control conditions (28.6±7.30 SE µmolO2g-1tissuedryweighth-1).</text></s>
<s sid="7"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>There was no corresponding change in calcification rates between treatments, measured using the alkalinity anomaly technique and 14C uptake.</text></s>
<s sid="8"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The decrease in respiration rate and maintenance of calcification rate indicates an energetic imbalance, likely facilitated by utilisation of lipid reserves.</text></s>
<s sid="9"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>These data from freshly collected L. pertusa from the Mingulay Reef Complex will help define the impact of ocean acidification upon the growth, physiology and structural integrity of this key reef framework forming species.</text></s>
</ABSTRACT>
<BODY>

Introduction
<s sid="10"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Cold-water corals are among the most three-dimensionally complex deep-sea habitats known and are associated with high local biodiversity (Roberts et al., 2006, 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="11"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>However, their remoteness and the relatively short history of ecological research in these habitats mean that to date, we have little information on how these ecosystems will fare in the face of predicted future climate change.</text></s>
<s sid="12"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>Similar to their tropical counterparts, cold-water corals (referred to as CWC herein) are under potential threat from increasing sea temperatures and ocean acidification.</text></s>
<s sid="13"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Ocean acidification, also referred to as the 'other CO2 problem' or the 'evil twin of global warming', is caused by CO2 dissolving into the oceans.</text></s>
<s sid="14"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>As atmospheric CO2 levels increase, more CO2 dissolves into the oceans and forms carbonic acid, which dissociates to form hydrogen and bicarbonate ions.</text></s>
<s sid="15"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>This process has led to a decrease in pH by 0.1 units since the industrial revolution, and increasing amounts of atmospheric CO2 are projected to further decrease ocean pH by another 0.3-0.4 pH units by the end of the century in addition to altering seawater carbonate chemistry (Caldeira and Wickett, 2003; Guinotte et al., 2006; Kleypas et al., 1999; Orr et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="16"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The shift in carbonate chemistry associated with ocean acidification also reduces the saturation state of aragonite, which is a naturally occurring polymorph of calcium carbonate from which most framework-building corals build their skeletons.</text></s>
<s sid="17"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The aragonite saturation depth or 'horizon' (ASH) (Guinotte et al., 2006) is predicted to become shallower (shoal), making it more difficult for calcifying organisms near this depth to maintain their calcified structures, thus affecting net reef growth.</text></s>
<s sid="18"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>CWC are under particular threat as they inhabit a much larger bathymetric range than tropical corals, and as such are closer to the ASH (Fautin et al., 2009; Form and Riebesell, 2012; Guinotte et al., 2006; Kleypas, 2006; McCulloch et al., 2012a; Roberts et al., 2006; Thresher et al., 2011; Turley et al., 2007).</text></s>
<s sid="19"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Only 5% of CWC are found below the ASH at present (Form and Riebesell, 2012), as net calcification below the ASH would require considerable energetic input at the detriment of other energetic processes.</text></s>
<s sid="20"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Shoaling of the horizon could thus have potentially severe consequences for CWC.</text></s>
<s sid="21"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>To date, only a handful of studies have been conducted on the responses of Lophelia pertusa to ocean acidification.</text></s>
<s sid="22"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>These focus on growth rate, ranging from very short term 24 hour experiments (Maier et al., 2009) on freshly collected coral, to longer-term 6 month (Form and Riebesell, 2012) experiments on laboratory-kept specimens.</text></s>
<s sid="23"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Ocean acidification has very varied effects on the growth of calcifying organisms, with different phyla, and even species within phyla showing highly variable responses in experimental studies to date (Ries et al., 2009; Wicks and Roberts, 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="24"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>For scleractinian corals (i.e. calcareous skeleton forming corals), many studies demonstrate a reduction in growth (net calcification rates) in response to ocean acidification (Gattuso et al., 1998; Kleypas and Langdon, 2006; Krief et al., 2010; Langdon and Atkinson, 2005; Marubini et al., 2003).</text></s>
<s sid="25"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>However, corals can actively increase the pH in the organic matrix where calcification occurs.</text></s>
<s sid="26"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Thus even in situations where the surrounding water is undersaturated with respect to aragonite, calcification can still occur (McCulloch et al., 2012a, 2012b).</text></s>
<s sid="27"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The process of increasing pH at calcification sites within corals is driven by Ca2+ATPase, which pumps Ca2+ ions into the sub-calicoblastic space in exchange for H+ ions (Allemand et al., 2004; Cohen and McConnaughey, 2003; Mass et al., 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="28"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>However, this process is energy intensive and thus may require increased food intake (Edmunds, 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="29"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The low abundance of CWC below the ASH suggests that increased energetic demands cannot usually be met, and that dissolution of exposed skeletal framework may be greater that net calcification by tissue-covered skeleton.</text></s>
<s sid="30"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>To fully understand the impact of increased CO2 on live CWC, it is important to combine growth rates with measures of metabolism, which has not been done previously.</text></s>
<s sid="31"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>The research presented here addressed the question of whether ocean acidification will impact upon the metabolism and net calcification rate of the CWC Lophelia pertusa in a short-term experiment.</text></s>
<s sid="32"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>To this end, respiration and net calcification rates were calculated in corals exposed to increased CO2 conditions every 7 days for a total period of 21 days.</text></s>
Methods
Sample collection
<s sid="33"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Colonies of Lophelia pertusa were collected from Area 1 within the Mingulay Reef Complex (Roberts et al., 2005, 2009), 56° 49.38 N, 7° 22.56 W (Figs.</text></s>
<s sid="34"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>1 and 2), during RRS Discovery cruise 366/7 in July 2011 (Achterberg and Richier, 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="35"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The Mingulay complex is a relatively shallow inshore seascape of Lophelia reefs that developed through the Holocene with oldest currently dated coral from within the reef mounds at 7.68ka (Douarin et al., in press).</text></s>
<s sid="36"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>They are the only known inshore Lophelia reef in UK waters.</text></s>
<s sid="37"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Colonies were collected using a modified video assisted van-Veen grab (Dodds et al., 2007).</text></s>
<s sid="38"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>All colonies were collected from 141-167m.</text></s>
<s sid="39"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Upon return to the surface, corals were placed in a holding tank at ambient seabed temperature for 2 days, to recover from collection.</text></s>
<s sid="40"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Corals were then carefully fragmented into smaller pieces for experiments.</text></s>
<s sid="41"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>These fragments had 5-20 polyps, and were taken from the top of sampled colonies to ensure that relatively young polyps were used consistently, as polyp age can determine physiological response with younger polyps known to be the fastest-growing (Maier et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="42"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Fragments were attached to pre-labelled bases made of PVC pipe with Grotech Korafix epoxy.</text></s>
Treatments
<s sid="43"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Two tanks (each ~350L seawater within 430L volume (0.9×0.6×0.8m)) were established for experiments; one at ambient reef conditions of 9.5°C, 380ppm and the other at 9.5°C, 750ppm in accordance with the IPCC IS92a CO2 emission scenario.</text></s>
<s sid="44"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Elevated CO2 750ppm gas was purchased pre-mixed (BOC) and generously bubbled directly into a corner of the experimental tank near a powerhead to ensure gas and water mixing and dispersal throughout the tank.</text></s>
<s sid="45"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>To check that bubbling was sufficient, tank pH was checked with a Mettler-Toledo SevenGo SG2 pH meter.</text></s>
<s sid="46"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Ambient air was pumped into the control tank and checked for consistency with a Li-820 gas analyser (Licor).</text></s>
<s sid="47"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Both tanks were equipped with chillers, filtration units and powerheads to provide adequate temperature control, filtration and circulation.</text></s>
<s sid="48"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Water circulation in this closed system from the tank to the filtration unit and chiller was 300lh-1.</text></s>
<s sid="49"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Thirty per cent water changes were conducted on each tank every 2 days.</text></s>
<s sid="50"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Tank temperatures and salinity were checked throughout the experimental period with a YSI (30) salinity and temperature meter.</text></s>
<s sid="51"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Salinity and temperature for the control and experimental tanks were 35.2±0.04 and 35.3±0.03, and 9.72±±0.13°C and 9.86±0.07°C respectively.</text></s>
<s sid="52"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Corals (n=32 in each treatment) were fed a mixture of live Artemia and Skeletonema marinoi every two days.</text></s>
<s sid="53"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Time points were Time Zero, +7 days, +14 days and +21 days.</text></s>
<s sid="54"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Following measurements at time zero, 750ppm gas bubbling was initiated in the treatment tank.</text></s>
<s sid="55"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Fragments from individual colonies were split evenly between treatments and time points to avoid colony pseudo replication.</text></s>
<s sid="56"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Site and experimental carbonate chemistry</text></s>
<s sid="57"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Mingulay carbonate chemistry was assessed on two cruises; on D366/7 (July-August 2011) and on RRS James Cook 073 (Roberts et al., 2013) (May-June 2012) in surface waters (&lt;20m) and near the reef crest (~120m).</text></s>
<s sid="58"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Borosilicate glass bottles with ground glass stoppers were used to collect seawater from Niskin bottles on the CTD rosette, and sample bottles were rinsed and filled according to standard procedures detailed in Dickson et al. (2007).</text></s>
<s sid="59"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Samples were poisoned with mercuric chloride, and duplicate samples were taken from the same Niskin bottle.</text></s>
<s sid="60"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Samples were bought to room temperature (approx.</text></s>
<s sid="61"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>23°C) and analysed for total inorganic carbon and total alkalinity within 24h of collection.</text></s>
<s sid="62"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Total Alkalinity (AT) and Dissolved Inorganic Carbon (CT) were calculated according to depth-specific salinity, and also normalised to a salinity of 35 for comparative purposes across depths where salinity changed.</text></s>
<s sid="63"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>AT was corrected for the addition of mercuric chloride.</text></s>
<s sid="64"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Carbonate parameters were calculated using CO2sys (Pierrot et al., 2006) with dissociation constants from Mehrbach et al. (1973), refit by Dickson and Millero (1987) and KSO4 using Dickson (1990).</text></s>
<s sid="65"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met5" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>AT and CT samples were collected (as described above) from the middle of experimental tanks at each time point.</text></s>
<s sid="66"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Although there was only one experimental tank per treatment, the turnover of seawater between time points (through regular maintenance water changes) ensured that carbonate chemistry was not pseudo-replicated across time points.</text></s>
<s sid="67"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>For full details of instruments used to assess AT and CT for experimental purposes, and for site carbonate chemistry, please refer to Supplementary Material.</text></s>
Physiology
<s sid="68"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Rates of oxygen consumption were assessed in coral fragments placed within 220mL incubation chambers fitted with oxygen optodes connected to a temperature-compensated oxygen analyser (Oxy-4 Mini with Temp-4, Presens &amp; Loligo systems).</text></s>
<s sid="69"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Magnetic stirrers ensured homogeneity of oxygen around the coral fragments.</text></s>
<s sid="70"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Chambers were filled with tank seawater and corals were allowed to acclimate to the conditions for 2h.</text></s>
<s sid="71"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Ten chambers were used per treatment at each time point; 8 for respiration, and 2 as seawater 'blanks' in order to measure (and subsequently subtract) background microbial respiration.</text></s>
<s sid="72"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Prior to respiration measures, corals were not fed for 48h.</text></s>
<s sid="73"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Once chamber lids were attached ensuring no headspace, oxygen consumption was recorded for a 40-min period for each fragment, during which oxygen saturation did not fall below 80%.</text></s>
<s sid="74"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Following incubations at T+21 days, fragments were removed and preserved at -20°C for subsequent weight determination.</text></s>
<s sid="75"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The ash-free dry mass (AFDM) of each sample was determined by adding homogenised material to a pre-weighed porcelain crucible and noting the weight of the crucible and the sample.</text></s>
<s sid="76"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The crucibles were covered and placed in a muffle furnace (Nabertherm Controller B170).</text></s>
<s sid="77"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The temperature of the furnace increased to 450°C over a 30-min period and then remained at that temperature for a further 4h.</text></s>
<s sid="78"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>After this time the crucibles were re-weighed and the difference in the weight of the sample minus the ashed weight gave the amount of organic matter or AFDM.</text></s>
Net calcification
<s sid="79"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met6" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Two methods were used to assess L. pertusa growth through net calcification; the alkalinity anomaly technique (Smith and Key, 1975) and uptake of labelled carbon (Marshall and Wright, 1998).</text></s>
<s sid="80"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met7" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>To determine if there was any increase or decrease in tissue mass, the AFDM was compared to dry coral weight.</text></s>
<s sid="81"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met8" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>For additional comparison to recent CWC studies (Form and Riebesell, 2012; Maier et al., 2012, 2009), coral polyp numbers were also counted to determine calcification per polyp.</text></s>
<s sid="82"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met9" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Different fragments were used for both techniques (Table 1).</text></s>
Alkalinity anomaly
<s sid="83"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met10" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Following techniques from Smith and Key (1975), and Ohde and Hossain (2004) calcification rates were calculated in L. pertusa by measuring the change in seawater alkalinity in respiration chambers housing coral fragments for 4h.</text></s>
<s sid="84"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met11" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Samples of incubation water were taken at the beginning and end of the experimental period, and total alkalinity determined using an automatic titrator (Metrohm 702 SM Titrino).</text></s>
<s sid="85"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met12" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Calcification (µmolCaCO3g-1h-1) was estimated following Eq.</text></s>
<s sid="86"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met13" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>(1),(1)Calcification=0.5(ΔTA)·V/ΔT/AFDMwhere ΔTA is the change of total alkalinity (µmol/l), V is the volume of experimental seawater (L) and ΔT is the experimental period (h).</text></s>
<s sid="87"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met14" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Calcification rates were calculated per hour (and extrapolated to per day) through a linear function.</text></s>
<s sid="88"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met15" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>However, this may potentially underestimate growth rates if all newly accreted material contributes to calcification.</text></s>
<s sid="89"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met16" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Further study is needed to calculate whether L. pertusa growth over time is better represented by linear or exponential growth functions.</text></s>
<s sid="90"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met17" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>With regard to nutrients, corrections applied to total alkalinity to account for the release of nutrients during incubations are considered negligible, especially for tropical corals (Riebesell et al., 2010; Smith, 1995).</text></s>
<s sid="91"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Considering that the ~10% underestimation of net calcification rate due to nutrient omission is small compared to natural variation in CWC calcification (Maier et al., 2012), nutrients were considered negligible for experiments here.</text></s>
<s sid="92"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Changes in aragonite, CT and pH during incubation were not quantified.</text></s>
<s sid="93"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp35" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>For comparison to other CWC studies, calcification rates were also expressed as a percentage compared to initial skeletal weight of the corals to give growth as %d-1.</text></s>
Radioisotope
<s sid="94"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp36" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Calcification rates were measured by incorporation of 14C (from sodium bicarbonate, CHNaO3), into new coral skeleton.</text></s>
<s sid="95"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp37" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Fragments of live corals (different from those used for respiration/alkalinity anomaly) from both treatments were placed in 30ml filtered seawater (FSW) maintained at tank temperature (9.5°C) in 50ml falcon tubes (20ml headspace).</text></s>
<s sid="96"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp38" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>After 1h acclimation, 120μl of 14C stock solution was added to each tube to a final activity of 3kBq/ml (0.08101uCi/ml) (Al-Horani et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="97"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp39" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Two controls were included; one of a dead coral fragment (previously placed in a 4% formalin solution), and one of Filtered Sea Water (FSW).</text></s>
<s sid="98"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp40" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Tubes were kept in floating tube racks, so ship movement and a pump maintained gentle movement of the tubes to ensure isotope mixing.</text></s>
<s sid="99"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp41" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Immediately following addition of the radioisotope, 100µl of sample water was removed and added to 4ml of Optisafe scintillation cocktail with 200µl ß-phenylethylamine to assess total activity.</text></s>
<s sid="100"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp42" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Following 6h incubation, another 100µl was taken to assess the decrease in total activity in incubation water.</text></s>
<s sid="101"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp43" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Coral fragments were then placed in FSW for 1h to remove unbound tracer.</text></s>
<s sid="102"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp44" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>This step was repeated before corals were preserved at -20°C for analysis following the expedition.</text></s>
<s sid="103"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp45" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>No samples of water carbonate chemistry were taken from the experiment tubes before or after incubation.</text></s>
<s sid="104"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp46" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>To determine the amount of 14C incorporated in skeleton, frozen samples were dried overnight at 60°C.</text></s>
<s sid="105"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp47" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Samples were weighed and tissue was then hydrolysed with a known volume of 2N NaOH at 90°C.</text></s>
<s sid="106"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp48" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Hydrolysate (100µl) was sampled for uptake of 14C in coral tissue.</text></s>
<s sid="107"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp49" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The skeleton was rinsed with distilled water and dried overnight again for re-weighing.</text></s>
<s sid="108"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp50" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Tissue dry weight was calculated as the difference between skeleton and tissue weight, and skeleton weight.</text></s>
<s sid="109"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp51" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>To calculate uptake of 14C, skeletons were placed in flasks fitted with an outlet to a swinnex filter holder which contained a GF/C filter impregnated with ß-phenylethlyamine.</text></s>
<s sid="110"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp52" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Excess acid (HCl) was added to flasks to dissolve the skeleton and evolve CO2.</text></s>
<s sid="111"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp53" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Evolved 14C was trapped in the GF/C filter, and following complete skeletal dissolution, the filter was placed in 4ml of Optisafe scintillation cocktail for counting on a Packard 1900CA Tri-Carb Liquid Scintillation Analyser.</text></s>
Results
Mingulay seawater parameters
<s sid="112"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>From CTD casts in June 2012, salinity increased with depth at Mingulay whereas temperature slightly decreased from the surface to the reef crest (ca.</text></s>
120m) (Table 2).
<s sid="113"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>CT increased with depth, both when normalised to the changing salinity and when normalised to 35 for comparison with surface values (Table 2).</text></s>
<s sid="114"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>AT increased with depth when using depth-specific salinity values, but when normalised to 35, a decrease in AT was observed with depth.</text></s>
<s sid="115"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In situ pHT decreased with depth as pCO2 increased (Table 2).</text></s>
<s sid="116"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Deeper CTD casts taken in July 2011 at the side of the Mingulay Reef mounds correlate with Table 1; such that AT and CT increased with depth (AT 2332.7±1.18; DIC 2149.0±2.08 at 172m).</text></s>
Physiology
<s sid="117"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The respiration rates for coral fragments at Time Zero before fragments were exposed to experimental conditions was 23µmolO2g-1h-1.</text></s>
<s sid="118"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For fragments in the control treatment at 380ppm, 9.5°C, pH 8.07 (Table 3), there was no significant change in respiration rates from Time Zero to 21 days.</text></s>
<s sid="119"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>For fragments exposed to increased CO2 at 750ppm, 9.5°C, pH 7.77 (Table 3), respiration rates were significantly lower than control fragments at 14 days with 12.1±1.30 SE at 750ppm versus 23.7±5.13 SE at 380ppm, and at 21 days with 11.441.39 SE at 750ppm versus 28.6±7.30 SE at 380ppmµmolO2g-1tissuedryweighth-1 (two sample t-test; t=2.19, p&lt;0.05; t=2.31, p&lt;0.05 respectively), see Fig. 3.</text></s>
<s sid="120"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Microbial respiration typically ranged from 0.005 to 1.3µmolO2h-1, but on average was ~0.5µmolO2h-1 in the experimental chambers.</text></s>
<s sid="121"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>There was no difference in the relationship between AFDM and whole coral (skeleton+tissue) dry weight between 380ppm and 750ppm treatments after 21 days, so tissue mass did not change in coral fragments under acidified conditions compared to control individuals.</text></s>
<s sid="122"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Fragments from 380ppm and 750ppm were thus combined for correlation analysis between AFDM and whole coral dry weight.</text></s>
<s sid="123"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The linear regression was strong (r2=0.85, Fig. 4A, at T+21 days; y=0.0428x+0.08473) even with the presence of one anomalous point.</text></s>
<s sid="124"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>If this point was removed from the regression, y=0.0415x+0.0849, r2=0.97, p&lt;0.0001, with tissue dry weight approximately 5% of dry coral weight.</text></s>
<s sid="125"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Respiration rates for each treatment at T+21 days were compared to AFDM, with positive relationships for both 380ppm (r2=0.62, p=0.04) and 750ppm (r2=0.78, p=0.008) fragments (Fig. 4C).</text></s>
<s sid="126"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, these regressions were partially driven by one larger coral in each treatment.</text></s>
<s sid="127"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Comparisons of AFDM and respiration rates to fragment polyp numbers elicited poor relationships; 380ppm (r2=0.14, p=0.40), 750ppm (r2=0.08, p=0.59) (Fig. 4D).</text></s>
Net calcification
<s sid="128"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Net calcification rates at time zero, measured with the alkalinity anomaly technique, were ca.</text></s>
1.5µmolCaCO3g-1tissuedryweighth-1.
<s sid="129"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>This did not change significantly for either treatment over the 21 days, or between treatments at any time point (Fig. 5A).</text></s>
<s sid="130"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Changes in AT (blank corrected) across both treatments were on average 34.7 (±3.34)µmolkg-1 and ranged from 9 to 59µmolkg-1.</text></s>
<s sid="131"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Growth rates measured as %d-1 did not change significantly over the 21 days either, and averaged~0.028%d-1 (Fig. 5B).</text></s>
<s sid="132"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Calcification rate as determined by 14C uptake did not differ between treatment and control fragments at either the experiment start (380ppm; 19.3×10-2 (±SE 2.76), 750ppm; 21.8×10-2 (±SE 7.36)µmolCaCO3g-1tissuedryweighth-1) or end (380ppm; 1.68×10-2 (±SE 0.60), 750ppm; 4.38×10-2 (±SE 1.6)µmolCaCO3g-1tissuedryweighth-1).</text></s>
<s sid="133"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, there was a significant decrease in calcification rates measured by 14C uptake in 380ppm fragments over time (380ppm, two sample t-test; t=7.28, p=0.001), which was not significant in 750ppm fragments due to very high variability.</text></s>
<s sid="134"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This decrease was not observed through the alkalinity anomaly technique.</text></s>
<s sid="135"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>14C uptake into L. pertusa tissue was approximately the same for all treatments and time points (ca.</text></s>
<s sid="136"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>60×10-2µmol14Cg-1tissuedryweighth-1) and did not significantly change between treatments or over time.</text></s>
Discussion
<s sid="137"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Physiology, calcification and ocean acidification</text></s>
<s sid="138"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Lophelia pertusa respiration rate was significantly lower in fragments exposed to increased CO2 than in control fragments after 2 weeks.</text></s>
<s sid="139"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Metabolic respiration is needed to produce ATP, which in turn is used to support energy-requiring processes (Al-Horani et al., 2003).</text></s>
<s sid="140"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This includes calcification, tissue production, mucus-production (Wild et al., 2009) (which accounts for a large proportion of tropical corals' carbon budget (Muscatine et al., 1984)) and driving the transport protein Ca2+ATP-ase.</text></s>
<s sid="141"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This transport protein is essential for calcification to occur, as it actively pumps Ca2+ ions into the sub-calicoblastic space in exchange for H+ ions, thereby increasing Ca2+ concentration and making conditions favourable for calcification to occur by increasing pH (McCulloch et al., 2012a).</text></s>
<s sid="142"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The decreased respiration found in the present study under acidified conditions may indicate a decreased requirement of ATP production by L. pertusa under increased levels of CO2 after a few weeks.</text></s>
<s sid="143"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This may be due to a change in energetic requirements, a reallocation of resources, or changing metabolic pathways (Findlay et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="144"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Form and Riebesell (2012) noted discrepancies in L. pertusa physiology between very short (24h) and longer-term (months) experiments; whereby responses observed during the first 24h were no longer exhibited after some months.</text></s>
<s sid="145"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This indicates that L. pertusa may have both 'shock' and acclimation responses to changes in CO2 conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="146"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The two-week period observed here before any noticeable differences were observed between experimental and control fragments may indicate a switching of metabolic pathways cued by extended exposure to elevated CO2.</text></s>
<s sid="147"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, due to coral respiration in closed-system experimental chambers, it is likely that there will have been a significant rise in CT and corresponding decrease in pH during the respiration incubation periods (Form and Riebesell, 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="148"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Although unquantified in this experiment, reductions in pH may have matched those reported by Maier et al. (2009) where decreases over 24h (in smaller vessels) ranged from 0.1-0.5 pH units.</text></s>
<s sid="149"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>For low pH treatments (such as the 750ppm), reductions could be potentially larger due to the reduced buffering capacity.</text></s>
<s sid="150"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Although this is important to consider, the fact that respiration was not significantly lower than T0 in the experimental treatment at T+7 days, but only after 14 days, indicates that it was likely to be a result of experimental conditions rather than changes during incubations.</text></s>
<s sid="151"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is supported by observations that there are no significant differences in respiration rates in corals in the first 30min of respiration incubation compared to after T+4h in the same incubation water (Hennige, S., personal observation).</text></s>
<s sid="152"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Respiration rates for L. pertusa documented in this study are higher than those reported by Dodds et al. (2007).</text></s>
<s sid="153"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met18" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>However, this experiment was conducted on freshly collected L. pertusa fragments, and not on colonies kept in aquaria conditions for several months.</text></s>
<s sid="154"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Indeed, respiration rates by Dodds et al. (2007) are very comparable to rates observed in L. pertusa fragments that have been maintained in aquaria at Heriot-Watt University for more than a year (Hennige, S., personal observation).</text></s>
<s sid="155"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This is likely due to the feeding limitations of aquaria in comparison to the in situ food supply.</text></s>
<s sid="156"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Freshly collected fragments will be acclimated to the conditions they were removed from in situ, but may exhibit an unquantified and unknown element of stress due to collection and pressure differences.</text></s>
<s sid="157"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, while long-term aquarium fragments may not have any unknown 'stress' and can be kept at very specific conditions, they may be acclimated to some unrepresentative aquarium conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="158"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Both approaches are equally valid but it has to be considered that freshly collected corals may not always exhibit similar physiological responses to long-term aquarium corals.</text></s>
<s sid="159"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Results here were normalised to AFDM in preference to polyp number, as respiration rates of fragments from both treatments significantly correlated with tissue mass, and not polyp number.</text></s>
<s sid="160"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Although coral polyps are the centres of heterotrophic feeding, dry tissue weight, which includes both polyp tissue and the surrounding coenosarc (which also respires), is therefore a potentially more useful normalisation parameter than polyp number.</text></s>
<s sid="161"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The relationship between AFDM and dry coral weight means that dry skeletal weight can provide a convenient proxy of tissue weight, without the need to kill the coral.</text></s>
<s sid="162"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Net calcification rates as measured by the alkalinity anomaly technique and 14C uptake, did not differ between control and experimental fragments, even though experimental fragments were at a much lower aragonite saturation level (still&gt;1).</text></s>
<s sid="163"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This complements a 24-h study by Maier et al. (2012) and a longer-term experiment by Form and Riebesell (2012), where growth rates of L. pertusa did not significantly change under different CO2 conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="164"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The stable net calcification rates reported in this study are in contrast to the reduced respiration in experimental fragments.</text></s>
<s sid="165"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This suggests an energetic imbalance between the production of ATP, and the use of ATP to actively provide Ca2+ needed for calcification.</text></s>
<s sid="166"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In a recent study, Kaniewska et al. (2012) found that under high CO2 conditions, metabolic activity in the tropical coral Acropora millepora was suppressed after a period of weeks, and changes were observed in genes regulating membrane cytoskeletal interactions and cytoskeletal remodelling.</text></s>
<s sid="167"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Results by Kaniewska et al. (2012) also indicated a possible breakdown of lipid reserves, which could provide the energy needed to maintain net calcification rates even with suppressed metabolism as observed.</text></s>
<s sid="168"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This highlights the importance of considering energetic budgets and wider cellular processes in studies such as this (Findlay et al., 2009; Kaniewska et al. 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="169"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The consistent AFDM: coral dry weight between fragments exposed here to ambient and 750ppm conditions did not indicate any major change in tissue mass in coral fragments from either treatment.</text></s>
<s sid="170"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, it is probable that an increase in lipid breakdown would not be apparent through changes in tissue mass over this relatively short time period.</text></s>
<s sid="171"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Net calcification rates reported here from the alkalinity anomaly technique are comparable to previously published rates by Maier et al. (2012, 2009), and Form and Riebesell (2012).</text></s>
<s sid="172"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Net calcification rates reported here for L. pertusa were slightly lower than those reported by Maier et al. (2009) where 45Ca was used to determine net calcification, within variability of alkalinity anomaly derived data in Maier et al. (2012), and slightly higher than those reported in Form and Riebesell (2012).</text></s>
<s sid="173"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Net calcification rates in L. pertusa are often highly variable, even within studies where fragments are collected from the same locale and time of year.</text></s>
<s sid="174"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>It is perhaps expected then, that differences exist between L. pertusa from different reefs, depths, and age.</text></s>
<s sid="175"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Further differences may be elicited through irregular growth episodes or 'spurts' (Form and Riebesell, 2012; Mortensen et al., 2001), which is typical in scleractinian corals.</text></s>
<s sid="176"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The calcification rates measured by 14C uptake were significantly lower than rates calculated through the alkalinity anomaly technique.</text></s>
<s sid="177"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This is not surprising, as labelled bicarbonate is not guaranteed to be taken up solely into the coral skeleton as calcium carbonate, and its uptake can be significantly less than 45Ca (Marshall and Wright, 1998).</text></s>
<s sid="178"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The reduction in 14C uptake from time zero to the end of the experiment in both control and experimental fragments indicates that some physiological process may have altered during this time.</text></s>
<s sid="179"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This may indicate a degree of acclimation to tank conditions (changing food source/change in circulation) that may have impacted the control of internal coral chemistry and cellular processes, so less 14C bicarbonate was incorporated into the skeleton.</text></s>
<s sid="180"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Non-quantified changes in carbonate chemistry during radioisotope experimental incubations may also have impacted upon these calcification rates.</text></s>
<s sid="181"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Considering the similarity of 14C incubations to the 45Ca incubations by Maier et al. (2009), it is possible that pH may have changed during incubations by up to 0.5 units, even though incubations here were four times shorter.</text></s>
<s sid="182"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, considering that calcification rates (as measured through the alkalinity anomaly technique) did not change over the course of the 21 days, it is likely the reduction in 14C uptake from T0 represents experimentally induced and not incubation induced changes.</text></s>
<s sid="183"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In general, the impact of ocean acidification upon scleractinian corals; both tropical and cold, seems to be inconsistent, with different species exhibiting negative (Ohde and Hossain, 2004), no measureable response (Reynaud et al., 2003), or variable responses (Gattuso et al., 1998) to a change in conditions (Wicks and Roberts, 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="184"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This is further complicated by suggestions that corals may be more or less susceptible to ocean acidification depending upon their ontogenetic stage.</text></s>
<s sid="185"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Albright et al. (2010) demonstrated that the tropical coral Acropora palmata is negatively impacted by increasing CO2 with respect to fertilisation, settlement of larvae, and growth of juveniles.</text></s>
<s sid="186"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Impacts on these aspects in L. pertusa, and indeed any CWC remain unknown to date.</text></s>
<s sid="187"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Scleractinian responses to ocean acidification may also not be observable in physiology, and may be enacted through changes in biomineralisation (Cohen and Holcomb, 2009; Holcomb et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="188"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>However, when comparing existing ocean acidification studies, care has to be taken, as methodologies often differ with respect to length of exposure to increased CO2 levels, the speed at which organisms are subjected to change (instantly versus increasing intermediate levels) and the way in which pH is reduced, i.e. acid addition versus CO2 bubbling (Wicks and Roberts, 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="189"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>A particularly interesting area for future focus may be whether the internal pH upregulation noted in certain coral species (Anagnostou et al., 2012; McCulloch et al., 2012a; McCulloch et al., 2012b; Venn et al., 2009) is consistent across species, and across different simulated future conditions.</text></s>
Environmental conditions at Mingulay
<s sid="190"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The increases observed in CT and AT from the surface to the reef crest were primarily driven by increasing salinity with depth.</text></s>
<s sid="191"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>When normalised to a salinity of 35, AT decreased from the surface to the reef.</text></s>
<s sid="192"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Proximity to the reef, where active calcification is occurring, would explain this decrease in alkalinity through calcification (Kleypas and Langdon, 2006), as for every mole of CaCO3 produced by the coral, total alkalinity of the water decreases by two moles.</text></s>
<s sid="193"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Differences observed between normalised CT indicate that there is either an addition of CT at the reef, or a drawdown of CT at the surface.</text></s>
<s sid="194"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This may be a combination of phytoplankton photosynthesis at the surface (Riebesell, 2004), and respiration from the coral reef, which would act to increase CT.</text></s>
<s sid="195"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>It has been noted in tropical corals that as ΩAragonite decreases from 3 or 4 (Kleypas and Langdon, 2006) to ca.</text></s>
<s sid="196"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>2, significant reduction in calcification rates can occur (Wicks and Roberts, 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="197"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The ΩAragonite at Mingulay (Table 1), which is considered relatively shallow for a Lophelia pertusa reef (Roberts et al., 2006), is about half that of many tropical reefs (Kleypas and Langdon, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="198"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, ΩAragonite is still &gt;1, so dissolution should not occur.</text></s>
<s sid="199"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>At Mingulay Reef, corals experience a periodic downwelling of surface water (Davies et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="200"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Recently characterised in terms of changing seawater carbonate chemistry (Findlay et al., 2013), this surface water will bring with it an influx of food from the surface, as well as periods of warmer water.</text></s>
<s sid="201"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus, corals at Mingulay are exposed to regularly fluctuating water conditions, both in terms of temperature and also water chemistry.</text></s>
<s sid="202"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This raises the possibility that corals at Mingulay may have higher tolerance for changing seawater conditions than those in more stable, bathyal environments.</text></s>
<s sid="203"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These and related questions form the basis of on-going investigations.</text></s>
Conclusions
<s sid="204"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>From this experiment, we present the first short-term data on the effects of increased CO2, (750ppm) upon the metabolism of freshly collected L. pertusa from Mingulay Reef Complex, Scotland, and its comparison with net calcification rates.</text></s>
<s sid="205"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The sustained net calcification rates of L. pertusa under elevated CO2 conditions corresponds with other studies, but the observed decrease in respiration rate highlights an energetic imbalance, whereby L. pertusa may be forced to use energetic reserves to maintain calcification rates.</text></s>
<s sid="206"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, the observed decrease in respiration in response to ocean acidification is potentially detrimental in the longer term, as expending energetic reserves is a finite strategy.</text></s>
<s sid="207"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus, it is crucial to perform longer-term experiments on Lophelia pertusa metabolism and growth to assess the acclimation potential, and ultimately the success, of this deep-sea ecosystem engineer to predicted increases of CO2 and warming.</text></s>
<s sid="208"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Finally it is important to note that the rapid rise in atmospheric CO2 is not only causing ocean acidification but warming.</text></s>
<s sid="209"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Further studies examining the combined effects of warming and acidification alongside other predicted stressors are urgently needed if we are to truly appreciate the significance of global climatic change on cold-water corals and other vulnerable marine ecosystems.</text></s>
</BODY>
<OTHER>
Acknowledgments
This paper is a contribution to the UK Ocean Acidification Research Programme (NE/H017305/1 to JMR; funded by the Natural Environment Research Council, the Department for Energy and Climate Change, and the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs) and the European Commission's Seventh Framework Programme projects EPOCA (Grant agreement no.
211384) and HERMIONE (Grant agreement no.
226354).
SJH, LCW and JMR acknowledge support from Heriot-Watt University's Climate Change Theme.
We thank Juan Moreno-Navas for GIS assistance and multibeam maps, the Scottish Association for Marine Science for the loan of coral sampling equipment, and the captains, crew and scientific participants of RRS Discovery cruise 366/7 and RRS James Cook cruise 073 for assistance at sea.
Supplementary Information
Supplementary data associated with this article can be found in the online version at 10.1016/j.dsr2.2013.07.005.
Supplementary materials
Supplementary Material

</OTHER>
</PAPER>