<?xml version="1.0" ?><PAPER><mode2 hasDoc="yes" name="S2211124713006475.tmf1" version="elsevier"/>
<TITLE>Specification of Functional Cranial Placode Derivatives from Human Pluripotent Stem Cells
</TITLE>
<ABSTRACT>

Summary
<s sid="1"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Cranial placodes are embryonic structures essential for sensory and endocrine organ development.</text></s>
<s sid="2"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>Human placode development has remained largely inaccessible despite the serious medical conditions caused by the dysfunction of placode-derived tissues.</text></s>
<s sid="3"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>Here, we demonstrate the efficient derivation of cranial placodes from human pluripotent stem cells.</text></s>
<s sid="4"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Timed removal of the BMP inhibitor Noggin, a component of the dual-SMAD inhibition strategy of neural induction, triggers placode induction at the expense of CNS fates.</text></s>
<s sid="5"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Concomitant inhibition of fibroblast growth factor signaling disrupts placode derivation and induces surface ectoderm.</text></s>
<s sid="6"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Further fate specification at the preplacode stage enables the selective generation of placode-derived trigeminal ganglia capable of in vivo engraftment, mature lens fibers, and anterior pituitary hormone-producing cells that upon transplantation produce human growth hormone and adrenocorticotropic hormone in vivo.</text></s>
<s sid="7"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Our results establish a powerful experimental platform to study human cranial placode development and set the stage for the development of human cell-based therapies in sensory and endocrine disease.</text></s>
Graphical Abstract
Highlights
•
<s sid="8"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Timed withdrawal of BMP inhibitor is sufficient to induce placode fates from hESCs</text></s>
•
<s sid="9"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Timed FGF inhibition suppresses placode fate and induces epidermal lineage</text></s>
•
<s sid="10"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Placode-derived trigeminal neurons are functional in vitro and engraft in vivo</text></s>
•
<s sid="11"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Pituitary placode-derived cells are capable of hormone release in vitro and in vivo</text></s>
<s sid="12"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Cranial placodes are essential for the development of sensory and endocrine organs.</text></s>
<s sid="13"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Here, Studer and colleagues report the efficient derivation of cranial placodes from human pluripotent stem cells.</text></s>
<s sid="14"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>They demonstrate how to obtain specific placode derivatives such as trigeminal ganglia capable of in vivo engraftment, mature lens fibers, and anterior pituitary cells capable of producing human GH and ACTH in vivo.</text></s>
<s sid="15"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Their results establish a platform for studying human cranial placode development and for applications of placode derivatives in regenerative medicine.</text></s>
</ABSTRACT>
<BODY>

Introduction
<s sid="16"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Cranial placodes give rise to cells of the sensory organs, including the optic lens, the nasal epithelium, otic structures, the adenohypophysis, and a subset of cranial nerves such as the trigeminal ganglia.</text></s>
<s sid="17"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>During development, sensory placodes are formed at the interface of the nonneural ectoderm and neural plate, surrounding the anterior portion of the future CNS (Figure S1A).</text></s>
<s sid="18"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Defects in placode development cause a wide spectrum of human congenital malformations ranging from blindness and deafness to hormone imbalance or loss of smell (Abdelhak et al., 1997; Baker and Bronner-Fraser, 2001; Ruf et al., 2004).</text></s>
<s sid="19"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>To date, cranial placode development has been characterized in model organisms, including the frog, zebrafish, chicken, and, to a lesser extent, the mouse (Baker and Bronner-Fraser, 2001; Bhattacharyya and Bronner-Fraser, 2004; Schlosser, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="20"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>However, human placode development has remained largely unexplored due to lack of access to early human tissue and specific placode markers.</text></s>
<s sid="21"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Human pluripotent stem cells (hPSCs), including human embryonic (hESCs), and human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs) have the potential to self-renew, while retaining a very broad differentiation potential.</text></s>
<s sid="22"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Over the last few years, protocols have been developed for directing the fate of hESCs into specific cell lineages.</text></s>
<s sid="23"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The derivation of CNS cells was among the first hESC differentiation protocols developed in the field (Reubinoff et al., 2001; Zhang et al., 2001).</text></s>
<s sid="24"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The differentiation of hESCs into cells of the peripheral nervous system has also been achieved (Lee et al., 2007; Menendez et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="25"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" type="Mot"/><text>In contrast to the successful derivation and application of defined CNS-and neural-crest (NC)-derived cell types, there has been limited success on modeling cranial placode development in hPSCs.</text></s>
<s sid="26"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Recently, we developed a neural induction strategy based on the concomitant inhibition of the Bone Morphogenetic Protein (BMP) and TGF-β/Activin/Nodal signaling pathways (dual-SMAD inhibition [dSMADi] (Chambers et al., 2009).</text></s>
<s sid="27"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Exposure to Noggin (N) and SB431542 (SB) leads to the synchronized, rapid and efficient differentiation of hPSCs into CNS fates.</text></s>
<s sid="28"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Here, we report that derepression of endogenous BMP signaling during dSMADi is sufficient for the selective induction of human cranial placodes.</text></s>
<s sid="29"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Using the placode induction protocol (PIP) &gt;70% of all cells adopt a SIX1+ cranial placode precursor fate by day 11 of differentiation.</text></s>
<s sid="30"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We further identify a preplacodal lineage competent to differentiate into selective placode fates including trigeminal sensory neurons, mature lens fibers, and hormone-producing anterior pituitary cells.</text></s>
<s sid="31"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Trigeminal sensory neurons are characterized by marker expression, electrophysiology, and by transplantation into the developing chick embryo and the adult mouse CNS.</text></s>
<s sid="32"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Finally, we report the derivation of human pituitary cells producing growth hormone (GH) and adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) hormones in vitro and in vivo.</text></s>
Results
<s sid="33"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Derepression of Endogenous BMP Signaling Induces Placode at the Expense of Neuroectoderm</text></s>
<s sid="34"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>To address whether the dSMADi protocol is suitable for the derivation of placodal cells, we first defined a set of appropriate placode markers.</text></s>
<s sid="35"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Based on studies in model organisms, we hypothesized that members of the SIX, EYA, and DLX family of transcription factors (Baker and Bronner-Fraser, 2001; Schlosser, 2006) mark human placode fate.</text></s>
<s sid="36"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Within the ectodermal lineage, SIX1 is placode specific, marking both the early preplacodal region and the various specific placodes (Schlosser, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="37"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Based on studies in the chick embryo, placode induction relies on a complex interplay of fibroblast growth factor (FGF), BMP, and WNT signals during early ectodermal patterning in vivo (Litsiou et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="38"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Activity of BMPs within the ectoderm is thought to be particularly critical in allocating fates.</text></s>
<s sid="39"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>A model has been proposed initially whereby high levels of signaling promote an epidermal fate, moderate levels induce placodes, intermediate levels specify NC, and a complete absence of BMP activity is required for neural plate formation (Wilson et al., 1997).</text></s>
<s sid="40"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>More recent studies have revised the original model by confirming an early role for BMP signaling in establishing placode competence (Kwon et al., 2010), whereas the subsequent stage was shown to require BMP inhibition rather than BMP activation (Ahrens and Schlosser, 2005; Kwon et al., 2010; Litsiou et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="41"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>To test whether early BMP exposure promotes the derivation of SIX1+ placodal cells, we exposed SB (the TGF-β inhibitor) -treated hESCs to various concentrations of BMP4.</text></s>
<s sid="42"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>However, addition of BMP4 in the presence of SB caused a dramatic morphological change and triggered induction of CDX2 (Figures S1B and S1C), similar to the BMP-mediated induction of trophectoderm-like lineages reported previously (Xu et al., 2002).</text></s>
<s sid="43"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>We next tested whether timed withdrawal of the BMP inhibitor Noggin during Noggin/SB431542 (N-SB)-mediated differentiation could induce placodal fates via derepressing endogenous BMP signaling.</text></s>
<s sid="44"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>We performed a time-course analysis during which we removed Noggin at different time points of the N-SB protocol (Figure 1A).</text></s>
<s sid="45"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Gene expression analysis at day 11 revealed a robust induction of DLX3, SIX1, and EYA1 (Figure 1B) upon withdrawal of Noggin at days 2 or 3 of differentiation.</text></s>
<s sid="46"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In contrast, Noggin withdrawal at day 1 of differentiation led to the induction of EYA1 in the absence of SIX1 expression and triggered morphological changes as well as CDX2 expression, suggesting trophectodermal differentiation (though CDX2 and EYA1 can also be expressed in hESC-derived mesodermal lineages [Bernardo et al., 2011]).</text></s>
<s sid="47"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Our data indicate that EYA1 is expressed in both trophectodermal and placodal lineages, and that coexpression with SIX1 is required to define placodal lineage.</text></s>
<s sid="48"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Immunocytochemical analysis of hESC progeny at day 11 of differentiation demonstrated that Noggin withdrawal at day 3 (PIP conditions) induced a switch from 82% PAX6+ neuroectodermal cells under N-SB conditions to 71% SIX1+ putative placode precursor cells under PIP (Figures 1C, 1D, and S1D).</text></s>
<s sid="49"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>SIX1+ clusters expressed other placodal markers such as EYA1, DACH1, and FOXG1 (BF1) (Figure 1E).</text></s>
<s sid="50"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>DACH1 is also expressed in anterior neuroectodermal cells (Elkabetz et al., 2008) marking neural rosettes, whereas in PIP-treated cultures DACH1 marks placodal clusters (Figure S1E).</text></s>
<s sid="51"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Temporal analysis of gene expression under PIP conditions revealed rapid downregulation of pluripotency markers (OCT4, NANOG), as well as markers of trophectoderm (CDX2) (Figure 1F), mesoderm (T), and endoderm (SOX17) (Figure 1G).</text></s>
<s sid="52"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>SIX1 expression in placode was confirmed in human primary tissue (Carnegie Stage 15, ∼5.5 weeks postconception [p.c.]; data not shown).</text></s>
<s sid="53"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>SIX1 is also expressed in precursors of skeletal muscle, thymus, and kidney cells.</text></s>
<s sid="54"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, we did not detect expression of skeletal muscle (MYOD), endoderm (SOX17), or mesoderm (Brachyury [T]) markers during PIP confirming that the hESC-derived SIX1+ cells are of placode identity.</text></s>
<s sid="55"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We also observed very few (&lt;1%) NC lineage cells under PIP conditions based on SOX10 expression by immunocytochemistry and SOX10::GFP (Chambers et al., 2012; Mica et al., 2013) reporter line expression (Figure S1F).</text></s>
<s sid="56"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Induction of cranial placode markers was observed by day 5 with FOXG1 preceding expression of SIX1 and DLX3 (Figure 1H).</text></s>
<s sid="57"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The PIP protocol was validated in multiple hESC and hiPSC lines (Figures S1G and S1H).</text></s>
<s sid="58"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>To further validate the identity of hESC-derived placodal precursors, we made use of a conserved Eya1 enhancer element (Ishihara et al., 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="59"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We readily observed GFP expression following nucleofection of the enhancer in olfactory placode but not in age-matched midbrain cultures (Figures S1I-S1J) confirming specificity.</text></s>
<s sid="60"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In hESC-derived placode, we observed an 8-fold increase in the percentage of cells with enhancer activity in PIP versus N-SB (Figure S1K).</text></s>
<s sid="61"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Microarray Analysis Reveals Human Placode Progenitor Gene Expression</text></s>
<s sid="62"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We next performed temporal transcriptome analysis to establish an unbiased molecular assessment of the in vitro placode induction process.</text></s>
<s sid="63"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>RNA was collected at five time points in triplicates (days 1, 3, 5, 7, and 11) in control N-SB- versus PIP-treated cultures (Figures 2A-2E; all raw data are available at GEO accession no.</text></s>
GSE51533).
<s sid="64"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Prior to microarray analysis, the quality of each sample was verified for expression of a panel of placode markers (SIX1, DLX3, EYA1) and the absence of other lineage markers (FOXA2, endoderm; SOX17, endoderm; MYOD, skeletal muscle; CDX2, trophoblast; and T, mesoderm).</text></s>
<s sid="65"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Cluster and principal component analyses showed a temporal segregation of the transcriptome data in PIP versus N-SB-treated cells by day 7 of differentiation (Figures 2A and S2A).</text></s>
<s sid="66"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Transcriptome data also defined a set of genes that distinguish placodal from neuroectodermal fate (Tables S1 and S2).</text></s>
<s sid="67"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>To gain insight into specific genes differentially expressed during placode induction, we performed pairwise comparisons for each differentiation time point (Figures 2B-2E).</text></s>
<s sid="68"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Among the most highly enriched transcripts under PIP condition were known placode markers such as GATA3, DLX5, DLX3, TFAP2A, and TFAP2C.</text></s>
<s sid="69"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>SIX1 was significantly upregulated in the microarray analysis by day 9 of differentiation, though it was not among the 20 most differentially regulated genes.</text></s>
<s sid="70"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Differential expression for these and additional genes was verified by quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) (Figure S2B).</text></s>
<s sid="71"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We also observed significant transcriptional changes in WNT and BMP pathway components such as an increase in the WNT pathway inhibitor DKK-1 and BMP antagonists, such as GREMLIN-1 and BAMBI (Figures 2B-2D), which are known transcriptional targets of BMP signaling (Grotewold et al., 2001).</text></s>
<s sid="72"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Interestingly, we also noticed induction of ISL1, a well-known marker for sensory neurons, motoneurons, heart progenitors, and pancreatic islet cells (Hunter and Rhodes, 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="73"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Based on the early onset of ISL1 expression and the absence of mesodermal fates, we surmised that under PIP conditions ISL1 represents an early human placode marker.</text></s>
<s sid="74"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>ISL1 was one of the first makers induced during PIP differentiation.</text></s>
<s sid="75"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Similar to TFAP2A and SIX1 (Figure 2F), ISL1 protein remained expressed in the majority of cells by day 11 of differentiation partially colocalizing with SIX1 (Figure 2G).</text></s>
<s sid="76"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Another placode marker identified by our microarray expression data is OVOL2, a member of the Ovo family of zinc-finger transcription factors.</text></s>
<s sid="77"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>OVOL2 was enriched during PIP by day 5 of differentiation, and placode clusters showed strong immunoreactivity for OVOL2 (Figure 2H).</text></s>
<s sid="78"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In contrast, OVOL2 was downregulated under conditions promoting CNS (N-SB) or neural crest (N-SB/CHIR [Chambers et al., 2012; Mica et al., 2013]) fates (Figure 2I).</text></s>
<s sid="79"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We identified additional differentially expressed genes during anterior placode specification, including FOXC1 and HAPNL1 (also known as CRTL1).</text></s>
<s sid="80"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>FOXC1 marks the lens placode during chick development (Bailey et al., 2006) but may also be expressed at the preplacode stage (Sasaki and Hogan, 1993).</text></s>
<s sid="81"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>HAPNL1 was one of the most differentially expressed genes in PIP and was previously shown to be expressed in the surface ectoderm and chick neural plate border (Colas and Schoenwolf, 2003).</text></s>
<s sid="82"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Gene ontology (GO) analysis, using DAVID (http://david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/) (Dennis et al., 2003), indicated that transcripts highly enriched in PIP versus N-SB conditions at day 7 and day 9 of differentiation are associated with sensory organ development, BMP and WNT pathways, as well as ectoderm and epidermis development (Figure S2C).</text></s>
<s sid="83"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The total number of differentially expressed genes increased by day 7 of differentiation (Figures S2D and S2E) matching the proposed time frame for placode commitment.</text></s>
<s sid="84"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In summary, our molecular analyses present a roadmap of human placode development and an important resource for future functional studies.</text></s>
<s sid="85"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Early Treatment with FGF Inhibitor Suppresses Placode and Induces Surface Ectoderm Fate</text></s>
<s sid="86"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Lineage studies in several vertebrate species indicate that cranial placode precursors originate from the surface ectoderm and are induced by signals emanating from the adjacent neuroectoderm (Pieper et al., 2012), rather than being of neural origin.</text></s>
<s sid="87"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>However, no such data are available for human development.</text></s>
<s sid="88"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The putative timing of human placode induction (approximately day 20 p.c.) (O'Rahilly, 1987) makes this a stage largely inaccessible to experimental manipulations.</text></s>
<s sid="89"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Gene expression data during PIP indicate that TFAP2A is one of the earliest upregulated and differentially expressed genes (Figures 2B-2E).</text></s>
<s sid="90"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>During mouse development, early expression of the orthologous gene Tcfap2a (E7.5) is restricted to the future surface ectoderm (Arkell and Beddington, 1997).</text></s>
<s sid="91"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The induction of TFAP2A was first detected at day 5 of PIP, whereas absent in N-SB protocol (Figure 3A) suggesting that the period between days 3 and 5 of PIP corresponds to the commitment toward surface ectoderm.</text></s>
<s sid="92"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>SIX1 was induced 2 days later than TFAP2A (Figures 3A and 3B) further pointing to a surface ectoderm intermediate.</text></s>
<s sid="93"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In vivo genetic studies indicate that high levels of BMPs in the absence of FGF signaling promote epidermal fate, whereas placodal cells are established at reduced levels of BMPs upon activation of FGFs (Kudoh et al., 2004; Litsiou et al., 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="94"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Therefore, we tested whether blocking endogenous FGF signaling under PIP conditions disrupts placode induction and triggers epidermal fate.</text></s>
<s sid="95"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Exposure to SU5402, a small molecule inhibiting FGF signaling, from day 3 to 11 of differentiation (Figure S3A) suppressed the emergence of SIX1+ clusters while maintaining TFAP2A expression (Figure 3C).</text></s>
<s sid="96"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Quantification of SIX1 and TFAP2A gene expression at day 11 confirmed a complete loss of placode marker expression (Figure 3D), whereas TFAP2A expression was maintained.</text></s>
<s sid="97"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The ectodermal precursor identity of TFAP2A+ cells was supported by the expression of the epidermal precursor marker KRT8 in PIP + SU5402-treated cultures (Figure 3E).</text></s>
<s sid="98"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Furthermore, long-term cultures (days 42-60) showed robust induction of the mature keratinocyte marker KRT14 (Figure 3F) and formed E-CADHERIN-positive patches with KRT14-immunoreactive cells at the periphery (Figure S3B).</text></s>
<s sid="99"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Analysis of the proliferative capacity of the epidermal precursors showed KI67 expression primarily in E-CADHERIN+/KRT14- cells.</text></s>
<s sid="100"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Cell proliferation decreased by day 60 concomitant with an increased percentage of cells expressing KRT14 (Figures 3G and S3C).</text></s>
<s sid="101"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>In addition to the requirement for endogenous FGF signaling, we observed low WNT and BMP levels as other important parameters for the transition from surface ectoderm (day3) to early placode fate.</text></s>
<s sid="102"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Exposure to high concentrations of CHIR or BMP4 suppressed placode at the expense of NC or putative trophectoderm, respectively (Figures S3D and S3E).</text></s>
<s sid="103"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res37" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Placode Precursors Efficiently Differentiate into Trigeminal-type Sensory Neurons</text></s>
<s sid="104"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res38" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Cranial placodes give rise to a broad range of specialized cell types, including hormone-producing cells of the anterior pituitary gland, structural cells such as lens fibers in the eye, and sensory neurons including trigeminal neurons (Figure 4A).</text></s>
<s sid="105"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res39" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Placodes can be characterized by the expression of specific PAX genes (McCauley and Bronner-Fraser, 2002).</text></s>
<s sid="106"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res40" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We observed that under standard PIP conditions most SIX1+ clusters coexpressed PAX3 (Figure 4B), suggesting ophthalmic trigeminal placode identity (McCabe et al., 2004; Stark et al., 1997).</text></s>
<s sid="107"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res41" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The spontaneous generation of HNK1+ (Metcalfe et al., 1990) cells with neuronal morphologies and coexpression of ISL1 confirmed peripheral sensory neuron identity (Figure 4C).</text></s>
<s sid="108"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>To further ascertain the placode origin of the sensory neurons under PIP conditions, we assessed coexpression of neuronal markers with SIX1 (Figures 4D and S4A).</text></s>
<s sid="109"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res42" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Lack of SOX10 expression during PIP-based sensory neuron differentiation ruled out a neural crest origin.</text></s>
<s sid="110"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res43" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>By day 20 of differentiation (7 days after replating), the cells formed ganglia-like structures with neurons extending long, radial processes and with nuclear expression of BRN3A (Figures 4D and 4E), a sensory neuron marker.</text></s>
<s sid="111"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res44" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Most neurons retained ISL1 expression by day 42 of differentiation and acquired expression of the peripheral neuron marker peripherin (Figures 4F and S4B).</text></s>
<s sid="112"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res45" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Immunocytochemical analysis for neurotransmitter phenotypes revealed expression of glutamate (Figure 4G) but lack of expression of TH and GABA (data not shown).</text></s>
<s sid="113"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res46" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These data are compatible with the generation of glutamatergic trigeminal sensory neurons.</text></s>
<s sid="114"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res47" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Gene expression analysis showed induction of RUNX1 (Figures 4H and S4C) and RET (Figure S4D), indicating sensory/nociceptive lineage.</text></s>
<s sid="115"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res48" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Expression of TRK receptors (Figures 4I and S4E) including NTRK1 and NTRK2 points to the presence of both nociceptive and nonnociceptive sensory neurons (Figures S4E-S4G).</text></s>
<s sid="116"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Diagnostic markers of nociceptive neuron identity include expression of specific sodium channels (SCN9A, SCN10A, SCN11A; Figure 4J) as well as classic pain receptors such as the capsaicin receptor (TRPV1), the receptor for cold sensation (TRPM8), and the P2X3 receptor critical for sensation of inflammatory pain mediated by ATP (Figure 4K).</text></s>
<s sid="117"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Gene expression analysis in long-term trigeminal neuronal cultures (day 55) showed sustained expression of RET1 and RUNX1 (Figures S4C and S4D).</text></s>
<s sid="118"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Functional analysis of placode-derived sensory neurons was performed by whole-cell patch-clamp recordings (Figure S4G).</text></s>
<s sid="119"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Neurons were filled with Lucifer yellow from the recording pipette exhibiting either bipolar or tripolar morphologies (Figures 4L and 4M).</text></s>
<s sid="120"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Responses were measured to a series of hyperpolarizing and depolarizing pulses (Figure 4N).</text></s>
<s sid="121"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>The hESC-derived neurons produced single action potentials at a threshold depolarization matching the functional properties reported for primary embryonic trigeminal neurons (Grigaliunas et al., 2002).</text></s>
<s sid="122"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res49" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The average resting membrane potential (RMP) was -65.6 ± 6.7 (Figures 4L and 4M).</text></s>
<s sid="123"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res50" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Passive membrane and action potential properties were comparable between bipolar and tripolar sensory neurons as summarized in (Figure 4O) suggesting that two morphologically distinct populations do not reflect functionally distinct subgroups.</text></s>
<s sid="124"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We further assessed the robustness of the trigeminal sensory neuron induction protocol across multiple hESC and hiPSC lines.</text></s>
<s sid="125"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We observed comparable percentages of ISL1- and BRN3A-expressing neurons across lines (Figure S4H).</text></s>
<s sid="126"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>In Vivo Analysis of hESC-Derived Trigeminal Neurons in the Developing Chick Embryo and Adult Mouse CNS</text></s>
<s sid="127"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>To assess the in vivo properties of hESC-derived trigeminal placode precursors, PIP-induced neuronal clusters, derived from a constitutively GFP-positive hESC line (Figures S5A and S5B), were injected into the developing chick embryo targeting the early trigeminal anlage at H&amp;H stage 10-12 (Figure S5C).</text></s>
<s sid="128"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Human cells were identified based on GFP expression and use of human specific antibodies against cytoplasmic antigen (hCA).</text></s>
<s sid="129"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Two days after in ovo transplantation, surviving GFP+ cells were found dispersed in the area of the endogenous chick trigeminal ganglion (Figure 4P).</text></s>
<s sid="130"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We observed extensive GFP+ human fiber bundles coexpressing hCA and peripherin (Figures 4Q and 4R).</text></s>
<s sid="131"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In contrast, no hCA or peripherin expression was detected in the neural tube of the embryo (Figure S5D).</text></s>
<s sid="132"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res51" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The in vivo fiber outgrowth 2 days after transplantation was reminiscent of the extensive in vitro fiber outgrowth of replated trigeminal neuron clusters (Figure S5A).</text></s>
<s sid="133"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res52" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Peripherin expression in vivo (Figure 4S) confirmed the peripheral neuron identity of the grafted cells.</text></s>
<s sid="134"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res53" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We next addressed whether hESC-derived trigeminal neurons can engraft in the adult mouse CNS and project toward their physiological target.</text></s>
<s sid="135"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res54" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The trigeminal nuclei in the brainstem receive afferent innervation from the trigeminal sensory ganglion that is relayed to the contralateral thalamus.</text></s>
<s sid="136"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res55" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The pons was selected as site for transplantation, because it is surgically accessible and located within proximity of the trigeminal brain stem nuclei that receive afferent input from the trigeminal ganglia.</text></s>
<s sid="137"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Hence, GFP+ human trigeminal neuron clusters were injected into adult NOD/SCID mice via stereotactic surgery (see Experimental Procedures).</text></s>
<s sid="138"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Histological analysis 4 weeks after transplantation showed survival of GFP+ human cell graft in the ventral pons (Figure S5E).</text></s>
<s sid="139"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res56" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Although GFP+ cell bodies remained tightly clustered at injection site, GFP+ fibers showed extensive projections into the host brain (n = 6) including the endogenous trigeminal nuclei (Figure S5F).</text></s>
<s sid="140"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res57" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Expression of BRN3A confirmed the sensory neuron identity of the cells (Figure S5G).</text></s>
<s sid="141"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res58" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Graft-derived human fiber bundles (hNCAM+ and GFP+) were observed emanating from the graft core (Figure S5H).</text></s>
<s sid="142"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These data demonstrate in vivo survival of trigeminal placode derivatives, differentiation along sensory neuron lineage, and the establishment of axonal projections toward relevant endogenous targets in the embryonic chick and adult mouse brain.</text></s>
<s sid="143"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Identification of a Putative Preplacode Stage</text></s>
<s sid="144"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our results indicate that current PIP conditions efficiently induce ophthalmic trigeminal placode fates.</text></s>
<s sid="145"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>To investigate whether other placodal fates can be generated using modified PIP conditions, we first addressed the presence of putative preplacode cells in our culture system.</text></s>
<s sid="146"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa5" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>During vertebrate development, the preplacode is characterized as the developmental anlage containing precursor cells competent to respond to signals determining placode identity (Martin and Groves, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="147"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Preplacodal cells in various model organisms have been shown to express Six1 and to coexpress markers of both ectodermal and neural fate.</text></s>
<s sid="148"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>However, the development of a human preplacode remains unexplored.</text></s>
<s sid="149"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>We performed a time-course coexpression analysis for TFAP2A (early ectodermal marker) and PAX6 (early neuroectoderm marker [Zhang et al., 2010]).</text></s>
<s sid="150"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res59" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>During the first 3 days of differentiation, only a few sparse patches of PAX6- or TFAP2A-expressing cells were observed without evidence of coexpression (Figure 5A).</text></s>
<s sid="151"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res60" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>At day 5, 2 days following Noggin withdrawal (PIP), there was an increase in the number of TFAP2A+ cells (Figure 5B) under PIP conditions and a concomitant loss of TFAP2A+ cells in N-SB (Figure 5C).</text></s>
<s sid="152"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res61" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>At day 7, N-SB conditions yielded PAX6+ cells devoid of TFAP2A expression (Figure 5C), whereas PIP-treated cultures showed extensive coexpression of TFAP2A and PAX6, indicating preplacode identity (Figure 5B).</text></s>
<s sid="153"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res62" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The emergence of TFAP2A/PAX6 double-positive cells coincided with the onset of SIX1 gene expression and the emergence of SIX1+ clusters around day 7 of differentiation (Figures 3B and S6A).</text></s>
<s sid="154"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res63" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>By day 11, placode clusters were negative for PAX6 but retained expression of TFAP2A (Figure 5B), suggesting that early anterior PAX6+ preplacode cells give rise to PAX6-negative posterior placode populations enriched for PAX3+.</text></s>
<s sid="155"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res64" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This model was further supported by gene expression data showing a robust PAX3 increase from day 7 to 11 of PIP (Figure 5D).</text></s>
<s sid="156"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res65" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Treatment with inhibitors of WNT or FGF signaling from day 7 to 11 of PIP suppressed PAX3 induction (Figure 5E) while maintaining PAX6 (Figure 5F).</text></s>
<s sid="157"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our results indicate that endogenous signals contribute to the transition from an anterior PAX6+ preplacode to a posterior PAX3+ placode lineage.</text></s>
<s sid="158"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res66" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The small number of TFAP2A cells in day 11 N-SB cultures (Figure 5C) likely represents neural crest precursors (Chambers et al., 2009) that lack PAX6 expression.</text></s>
<s sid="159"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res67" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Under PIP conditions the percentage of contaminating SOX10+ NC cells at day 11 was &lt;1% (Figure S1F).</text></s>
<s sid="160"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res68" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Treatment with FGF Inhibitor SU5402 at Preplacode Stage Induces Lens Fates</text></s>
<s sid="161"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj17" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We next tested whether putative preplacode cells can be coaxed into specific placode fates other then trigeminal neurons.</text></s>
<s sid="162"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj18" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>The spontaneous appearance of lens precursors (lentoid bodies) from primate and hESCs has been previously reported (Ooto et al., 2003; Zhang et al., 2010), although the lineage origin and inducing signals remained unexplored in those studies.</text></s>
<s sid="163"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj19" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We tested the impact of four developmental signaling pathways on lens placode specification using activators and inhibitors of BMP, FGF, WNT, and Hedgehog signaling.</text></s>
<s sid="164"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj20" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>To quantify the induction of lens placode fate, we monitored expression of the lens precursor marker PITX3 at day 16 of differentiation (Figure S6B).</text></s>
<s sid="165"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res69" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>PITX3 expression was significantly induced in the presence of recombinant BMP4 or upon exposure to the FGF-inhibitory molecule, SU5402 (Figure 5G).</text></s>
<s sid="166"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res70" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A role for BMPs and FGFs has been previously proposed in developmental studies in the chick (Sjödal et al., 2007).</text></s>
<s sid="167"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res71" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Further differentiation revealed strong induction of αβ-crystalline and the formation of mature lens fiber structures by day 57 (Figure 5H, left panel).</text></s>
<s sid="168"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res72" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The characteristic layering of lens fibers (Figure 5H, right panel) mimicked the structural properties of developing lens in vivo.</text></s>
<s sid="169"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res73" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Treatment with SHH at Preplacode Stage Induces Anterior Pituitary Cells</text></s>
<s sid="170"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj21" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We next explored whether preplacodal cells can be differentiated into anterior pituitary placode and recreate the various pituitary precursors and hormone-producing cell types (Figure 6A).</text></s>
<s sid="171"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>We observed that treatment with agonists for SHH signaling (Figure S7A) at the preplacode stage (days 7-11) induced expression of the oral ectoderm marker SIX6 and PITX1 (Figure 6B), master regulators of pituitary gland development (Tremblay et al., 1998).</text></s>
<s sid="172"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Induction of PITX1 and SIX6 at transcript and protein levels was dependent on SHH dose (Figures 6B and 6C).</text></s>
<s sid="173"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Furthermore, SHH treatment triggered the expression of the definitive pituitary precursor marker LHX3 (Figure 6D).</text></s>
<s sid="174"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Endocrine cells of the anterior pituitary gland are derived from three main precursors lineages (Scully and Rosenfeld, 2002).</text></s>
<s sid="175"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res74" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Following PIP + SHH treatment, we observed robust induction of TBX19 (Figure 6E), specific to precursors giving rise to ACTH- and MSH-producing cells.</text></s>
<s sid="176"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res75" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Induction of PIT1 and GATA2 precursor lineages was less efficient but was increased following treatment with the γ-secretase inhibitor DAPT (Figures 6F and 6G).</text></s>
<s sid="177"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res76" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Immunocytochemistry for pituitary hormones showed expression of CGA by 16 days, whereas protein expression of FSH, ACTH, and GH was first observed by days 25-30 of differentiation (Figures 6H-6K).</text></s>
<s sid="178"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res77" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The induction of ACTH+ cells was particularly efficient (Figure 6J), and in vitro release of ACTH hormone could readily be detected by ELISA (Figure 6L).</text></s>
<s sid="179"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj22" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We next tested whether hESC-derived pituitary cells are capable of in vivo survival and function in mouse and rat xenograft models (Figures 6M, S7B, and S7C).</text></s>
<s sid="180"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res78" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Subcutaneous injection of GFP-marked, hESC-derived pituitary precursors (day 16 of differentiation) into adult male NOD/SCID mice demonstrated survival of glycoprotein subunit (GSU) and follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) cells in vivo (Figures S7D and S7E).</text></s>
<s sid="181"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res79" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Longer-term survival studies in nude male rats (n = 8; 4-6 weeks postgrafting) showed significant increases in serum ACTH levels (Figure 6N) as measured during early morning hours (low point of endogenous ACTH expression during diurnal cycle).</text></s>
<s sid="182"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res80" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We also measured levels of human GH in vivo using an ELISA assay that selectively detects human but not mouse GH (Figure 6O).</text></s>
<s sid="183"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res81" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Transplantation into rat hosts allowed for repeated blood draws and showed a consistent increase of ACTH and GH levels in grafted as compared to sham injected (Matrigel-only) animals.</text></s>
<s sid="184"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res82" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Finally, histological analysis demonstrated in average 0.46 ± 0.015 million surviving hNCAM+ cells (Figure 6P) at 6 weeks after transplantation.</text></s>
<s sid="185"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res83" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>About 10% of the surviving human cells expressed ACTH (Figure 6Q) and 6% of the cells were immunoreactive for GH (Figure 6R).</text></s>
<s sid="186"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The ability to derive functional hormone-producing pituitary cells from hESCs via modified PIP conditions is particularly intriguing given previous work in mouse ESCs suggesting the need for complex coculture systems to induce pituitary lineages (Suga et al., 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="187"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In vivo survival and production of graft-derived ACTH and GH suggest translational potential for patients suffering from genetic, surgical, or radiation induced hypopituitarism (Tabar, 2011).</text></s>
Discussion
<s sid="188"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>An Experimental Platform for the Efficient Generation of Human Cranial Placodes In Vitro</text></s>
<s sid="189"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The study of human cranial placode development has been challenging due to the lack of a tractable experimental system, the inaccessibility of this transient structure during early human development, and the absence of validated human placode markers.</text></s>
<s sid="190"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Our data resolve those major challenges and establish a versatile platform for the study of human placode and ectoderm development (Figure 7).</text></s>
<s sid="191"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Previous studies have observed the emergence of certain placode derivatives such as lens (Ooto et al., 2003; Zhang et al., 2010) or otic placode-derived cells (Chen et al., 2012; Oshima et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="192"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>However, the mechanisms of placode induction were not addressed, and no general model of placode specification has emerged from those studies.</text></s>
<s sid="193"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Very recent studies have shown some promise in directing pluripotent stem cells toward placode fates (Leung et al., 2013; Mengarelli and Barberi, 2013; Shi et al., 2007).</text></s>
<s sid="194"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>However, no functional human placode derivatives have been reported under those conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="195"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>In contrast, studies in mouse ESCs have successfully derived functional otic (Koehler et al., 2013) and pituitary (Suga et al., 2011) placode derivatives.</text></s>
<s sid="196"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa6" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>A developmental question of particular interest is the origin of placode cells.</text></s>
<s sid="197"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res84" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The prevalent hypothesis is that placode tissue originates from nonneural ectoderm upon response to inductive signals from the adjacent neural tissue (Schlosser, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="198"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res85" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Our data indicate that human placode development similarly originates from nonneural ectoderm based on the result that TFAP2A expression precedes the induction of SIX1, whereas TFAP2A is suppressed during N-SB induction.</text></s>
<s sid="199"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>BMP-based induction of TFAP2A and GATA3 may be critical in establishing nonneural ectoderm lineage competent for placode induction (Kwon et al., 2010).</text></s>
<s sid="200"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The ability to block placode induction at the expense of nonneural ectoderm by inhibition of FGF signaling further supports a nonneural ectoderm origin and suggests that endogenous FGF signals may be the neural signal responsible for the placode default in PIP.</text></s>
<s sid="201"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res86" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Our findings further delineate the time point of developmental commitment to placodal fate by day 7, given that treatment of cells at day 7 of differentiation (preplacode) induced a switch between various placode fates but did not affect the ratio of cells of placode versus nonneural ectoderm fate.</text></s>
<s sid="202"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res87" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Previous work described FOXG1 and DACH1 as markers of anterior neuroectoderm and neural rosette stage cells during hPSC differentiation (Chambers et al., 2009; Elkabetz et al., 2008).</text></s>
<s sid="203"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our study reports a small percentage of SIX1+ cells that emerge spontaneously under N-SB conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="204"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Therefore, differentiation studies aimed at generating CNS lineages should address whether contaminating placodal tissues are present in hPSC-derived neural cultures.</text></s>
<s sid="205"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Those spontaneously emerging placodal cells are likely the source of lentoid bodies and other placode derivatives observed in past neural differentiation studies.</text></s>
<s sid="206"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our gene expression data define a broad set of placode markers valuable for future studies.</text></s>
<s sid="207"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>For example, OVOL2 has been shown to be expressed in the mouse epiblast and surface ectoderm, and loss of Ovol2 leads to early embryonic lethality (Mackay et al., 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="208"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Here, we define OVOL2 as a human preplacode marker.</text></s>
<s sid="209"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>FOXC1 and ISL1 are additional transcription factors specifically expressed at the preplacode stage.</text></s>
<s sid="210"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our data provide a framework for defining transcriptional networks that distinguish cranial placode identity from early CNS, neural crest, and surface ectoderm identity.</text></s>
<s sid="211"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Specification toward Functional hESC-Derived Placode Derivatives</text></s>
<s sid="212"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The current study defines a transient preplacode population competent to adopt various specific placode identities.</text></s>
<s sid="213"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>The emergence of a preplacodal region has been described during Xenopus and zebrafish development (Bailey et al., 2006; Martin and Groves, 2006; Schlosser, 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="214"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our data indicate that PIP initially yields a PAX6+/SIX1+ anterior preplacode population that spontaneously adopts a more posterior, PAX3+ ophthalmic trigeminal fate upon further differentiation, likely due to the caudalizing effects of endogenous FGF and WNT signals.</text></s>
<s sid="215"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Exposure to SHH or suppression of FGF signaling at day 7 of differentiation directs the putative preplacode precursors into anterior pituitary and lens placodes fates.</text></s>
<s sid="216"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Lens placode has been suggested as the default state during chick placode development with FGF8 being necessary and sufficient to specify olfactory placode fate (Bailey et al., 2006).</text></s>
<s sid="217"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" type="Bac"/><text>Elegant studies in mouse ESCs (Koehler et al., 2013; Suga et al., 2011) have shown the feasibility of generating hormone-producing pituitary cells and otic sensory neurons respectively using sophisticated 3D culture systems.</text></s>
<s sid="218"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our results demonstrate that modified PIP conditions yield human pituitary precursors efficiently without the need for complex 3D culture conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="219"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Although we observe a bias in generating preferentially TBX19-related pituitary lineages including ACTH-producing cells, all three major precursor lineages (GATA-2, TBX19, and PIT1 lineages, Figure 6A) could be derived.</text></s>
<s sid="220"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Therefore, it is likely that further optimization of the protocol will provide selective access to individual pituitary hormone lineages.</text></s>
<s sid="221"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Our current in vivo studies are limited to a maximum engraftment period of 3 months, subcutaneous injections into the flank of adult murine hosts, and use of animals (both mouse and rat) with normal pituitary function.</text></s>
<s sid="222"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Future experiments should include longer-term survival studies and an in-depth analysis of graft integration into the hypothalamic-pituitary axis, possibly via orthotopic graft placement into the hypothalamus or the sella.</text></s>
<s sid="223"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Finally, in vivo hormone function will need to be validated in animal models of pituitary dysfunction.</text></s>
<s sid="224"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We present data on the specification of trigeminal, lens, and anterior pituitary placode lineages.</text></s>
<s sid="225"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, preliminary evidence indicates that other placode fates are accessible as well using modified PIP conditions.</text></s>
<s sid="226"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con31" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>For example, exposure of preplacode cells to FGF8 enriches for ASCL1 expression compatible with olfactory placode fate (Balmer and LaMantia, 2005).</text></s>
<s sid="227"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con32" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Exposure to caudalizing cues such as WNT3A leads to the induction of a population of cells coexpressing SIX1 and SOX10 compatible of otic placode fates.</text></s>
<s sid="228"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con33" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Those conditions, although requiring further optimization, support the notion that PIP represents a universal platform for cranial placode fate specification.</text></s>
<s sid="229"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con34" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>One of the most immediate applications of PIP-based differentiation is the derivation of trigeminal sensory neurons.</text></s>
<s sid="230"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Goa7" novelty="None" type="Goa"/><text>Given our recent success in deriving neural-crest-derived nociceptive neurons (Chambers et al., 2012), it will be intriguing to compare the developmental and functional features of neural crest versus placode-derived nociceptors.</text></s>
<s sid="231"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con35" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Trigeminal neurons are involved in several pain syndromes such as trigeminal nerve palsy, trigeminal neuralgia, and migraine pain (Love and Coakham, 2001).</text></s>
<s sid="232"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con36" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Therefore, the ability to generate large numbers of trigeminal neurons will be particularly useful for modeling human nociception and for the development of cell-based drug screens in pain research.</text></s>
<s sid="233"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con37" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Another important application will be modeling Herpes simplex encephalitis using human iPSCs (Lafaille et al., 2012).</text></s>
<s sid="234"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con38" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>HSV-1 is a virus that specifically persists in a latent form within the trigeminal ganglia (Barnett et al., 1994).</text></s>
<s sid="235"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con39" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The ability to derive trigeminal neurons from patient-specific iPSCs should address whether defects in the control of viral latency contributes to Herpes simplex encephalitis.</text></s>
<s sid="236"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con40" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The robust in vivo survival of trigeminal placode precursors raises the possibility for developing future regenerative approaches with the goal of nerve repair following mechanical, radiation, or chemotherapy-induced damage.</text></s>
<s sid="237"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con41" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Finally, the potentially largest impact on regenerative medicine may come from deriving functional hormone-producing cells.</text></s>
<s sid="238"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con42" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Hypopituitarism is a common consequence of congenital defects, head injury, or therapeutic intervention in patients with pituitary tumors or patients receiving radiation therapy (Tabar, 2011).</text></s>
<s sid="239"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con43" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Although replacement hormones can be given to normalize resting serum levels in patients, the financial, logistic, and medical costs for such lifelong treatments are considerable.</text></s>
<s sid="240"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con44" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Furthermore, hormone replacement therapy does not allow for dynamic release in response to circadian rhythms, or rapid adjustments to physiological changes in the environment or stressful challenges.</text></s>
<s sid="241"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con45" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Therefore, the ability to generate large numbers of functional ACTH- and GH-producing cells launches the possibility of long-term therapeutic cell replacement strategies in pediatric and adult patients for restoring endocrine function.</text></s>
Experimental Procedures
Cell Culture
<s sid="242"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con46" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>hESCs (WA-09; passages 35-45), hiPSC lines (iPS-14, iPS-27; passages 20-30), and I6 were maintained at undifferentiated state and differentiated toward CNS lineages using dual-SMAD inhibition protocol described previously.</text></s>
<s sid="243"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>For PIP, Noggin was removed at day 3 of differentiation.</text></s>
<s sid="244"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>In some experiments, BMP-4, Noggin, DKK-1, FGF8, SU5402, Wnt-3a, DAPT, CHIR99021, cyclopamine, Sonic Hedgehog (SHH), and purmorphamine were added as detailed in the Supplemental Experimental Procedures.</text></s>
<s sid="245"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>For differentiation toward trigeminal sensory fate placode clusters were maintained in N2 medium supplemented with ascorbic acid and BDNF.</text></s>
<s sid="246"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Pituitary fate was induced by exposure to SHH and purmorphamine from day 7 to 11 of PIP followed by treatment with DAPT to promote PIT1+ fate.</text></s>
Cell Characterization
<s sid="247"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>qRT-PCR data were normalized to HPRT and are based on four to six technical replicates from at least three independent experiments.</text></s>
<s sid="248"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Global gene expression analysis was performed by the MSKCC genomics core according to the specification of the manufacturer (Illumina Human-6 oligonucleotide arrays).</text></s>
<s sid="249"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Detailed information on the use of primary antibodies for immunocytochemistry and flow analysis and on the electrophysiological analyses is presented in the Supplemental Experimental Procedures.</text></s>
Animal Studies
<s sid="250"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Animal studies were done in accordance with protocols approved by our institutional Animal Care and Use Committee and following NIH guidelines.</text></s>
<s sid="251"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Hormone-producing cells were injected subcutaneously into adult male NOD-SCID IL2Rgc mice and eight adult male nude rats.</text></s>
<s sid="252"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Blood was collected at 4-6 weeks after the transplantation followed by ELISA analysis for determining hormone levels.</text></s>
<s sid="253"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Chick transplantation studies were performed at HH stage 9-10, and embryos were harvested at HH stage 20.</text></s>
<s sid="254"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Injections into pons of adult NOD-SCID IL2Rgc mice were performed by stereotactic surgery.</text></s>
Statistical Analysis
<s sid="255"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism version 5.0b (GraphPad).</text></s>
<s sid="256"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>All data were derived from at least three independent experiments.</text></s>
<s sid="257"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Asterisks mark experimental groups that were significantly different from control groups by a two-tailed Students t test, or by ANOVA followed by Dunnett test to compare control against multiple independent treatment groups.</text></s>
<s sid="258"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Data are presented as mean ± SEM unless indicated otherwise.</text></s>
</BODY>
<OTHER>
Acknowledgments
This work was supported in part through grants from the Starr Foundation, NINDS grant NS072381, and NYSTEM contract C026447.
We are grateful to E. Lai for BF1 antibody, A.S.
McNeilly for GSU antibody, R.
Vinagolu for FSH antibody, and K.
Kawakami for Eya1::GFP enhancer element.
We also would like to thank H.
Ford for advice on SIX1 antibody, M. Hashimi for advice on microarray analysis, M. Tomishima and J. Tchieu for critical review of the manuscript, and M. Bronner for help in designing the chick in vivo transplantation studies.
Accession Numbers
The GEO accession number for the microarray gene expression data reported in this paper is GSE51533.
Supplemental Information
Supplemental Information includes Supplemental Experimental Procedures, seven figures, and two tables and can be found with this article online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2013.10.048.
Supplemental Information
Document S1.
Figures S1-S7 and Supplemental Experimental ProceduresTable S1.
PIP SignaturesTable S2.
N-SB SignaturesDocument S2.
Article plus Supplemental Information

</OTHER>
</PAPER>