<?xml version="1.0" ?><PAPER><mode2 hasDoc="yes" name="S2211753914000025.tmf1" version="elsevier"/>
<TITLE>Phialemonium infection complicating chronic suppurative otitis media
</TITLE>
<ABSTRACT>

Abstract
<s sid="1"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>Phialemonium infection in humans is rare.</text></s>
<s sid="2"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" type="Obj"/><text>We report a 7-year-old healthy boy who presented with chronic otorrhea, which persisted despite adequate antibiotic therapy and four preservative tympanomastoidectomy operations.</text></s>
<s sid="3"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met1" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Following 3 years of intermittent topical antibiotic therapy, cultures eventually grew Phialemonium, which necessitated a more extensive operation, combined with systemic/topical anti-fungal agent to achieve clinical cure.</text></s>
</ABSTRACT>
<BODY>

Introduction
<s sid="4"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>Phialemonium spp are a type of dematiaceous fungi that are emerging as opportunistic pathogens of humans.</text></s>
<s sid="5"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>To date, less than 30 cases of human Phialemonium infections have been reported, mainly occurring in immunocompromised patients [1,2].</text></s>
<s sid="6"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Met4" novelty="None" type="Met"/><text>However, infection of immunocompetent patients have been reported in the literature as well in recent years [3].</text></s>
Case
<s sid="7"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>A 7-year-old boy presented for right-sided otalgia and an ongoing otorrhea despite local and systemic antibiotic therapy administered for 1 month (Fig. 1).</text></s>
<s sid="8"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>His past medical history was remarkable for recurrent episodes of otitis media since early childhood, allergic rhinitis and a cutaneous abscess that required drainage.</text></s>
<s sid="9"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>His social history was significant for living on a ranch, daily interaction with outdoor animals, and swimming in a lake 2 weeks prior.</text></s>
<s sid="10"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>On his initial physical exam (day &quot;0&quot;), otoscopy of the right ear revealed pink granulation tissue, obscuring the tympanic membrane (TM).</text></s>
<s sid="11"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Antibiotic treatment for acute otitis media failed, and examination of the right ear under anesthesia (EUA), performed on day 26, revealed a polyp arising from a posterior-superior TM perforation.</text></s>
<s sid="12"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Specimens sent to surgical pathology demonstrated granulation tissue with chronic inflammation.</text></s>
<s sid="13"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Initial computed tomography (CT) of the temporal bone showed a soft tissue opacification in the right middle ear cavity, poorly aerated mastoid cavity, and erosion of the scutum and ossicles.</text></s>
<s sid="14"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>These findings were consistent with chronic serous otitis media (CSOM), with a possible cholesteatoma (Fig. 2A).</text></s>
<s sid="15"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Four months after initial presentation, an attic retraction pocket was observed with anterior tympanosclerosis of the right TM.</text></s>
<s sid="16"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>A repeat CT study demonstrated mild improvement of right tympanomastoid cavity opacification with new-onset thinning of the mastoid cortex (Fig. 2B).</text></s>
<s sid="17"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The patient underwent a canal-wall-down (CWU) tympanomastoidectomy on day 169; operative findings were remarkable for keratin debris in the epitympanum, intact malleus and stapes bones, erosion of the incus, and significant swelling of the middle ear mucosa.</text></s>
<s sid="18"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Surgical pathology revealed cholesteatoma and granulation tissue with chronic inflammation.</text></s>
<s sid="19"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Post-operatively, the patient continued to complain of right otorrhea, otalgia and mild ipsilateral conductive hearing loss despite antibiotic therapy.</text></s>
<s sid="20"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>One year later, the patient developed a right post-auricular abscess that was emergently treated by surgical incision and drainage on day 533.</text></s>
<s sid="21"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>A second CWU tympanomastoidectomy with bilateral tympanostomy tubes insertion was performed 2 months later, on day 628.</text></s>
<s sid="22"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Operative findings included middle ear mucosa swelling with a small amount of debris in the epitympanum.</text></s>
<s sid="23"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In a planned second-look CWU procedure performed 10 months later (day 922), there was no residual cholesteatoma.</text></s>
<s sid="24"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>However, right otorrhea persisted post-operatively.</text></s>
<s sid="25"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Otorrhea cultures over time (days 30-990) grew P. aeruginosa and Fusarium spp, and antibiotics were prescribed according to culture results (oral amoxicillin/azithromycin, intravenous ceftazidime and topical ciprofloxacin drops).</text></s>
<s sid="26"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>Phialemonium species was first cultured from an otorrhea swab nearly 3 years after initial presentation (day 1135).</text></s>
<s sid="27"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>The isolates were received on Sabouraud agar (Becton, Dickinson), sub-cultured on potato flakes agar (Remel), and incubated at 30°C.</text></s>
<s sid="28"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" type="Exp"/><text>After preliminary identification of Phialemonium species was reported, the isolates were referred to the Fungus Testing Laboratory at the University of Texas Medical Branch at Galveston, which confirmed the genus twice, but could not identify the exact species.</text></s>
<s sid="29"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>This unusual fungal isolation was despite several attempts to treat for bacterial-origin otorrhea with antibiotics.</text></s>
<s sid="30"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Due to the persistent CSOM-related otorrhea, now complicated by a rare fungus, the possibility of an underlying immunologic deficiency was considered.</text></s>
<s sid="31"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>However, a comprehensive work up of the patient was normal, and included complement levels in the blood, HIV test, immunoglobulin electrophoresis, blood protein electrophoresis, leukocyte adhesion deficiency test, T lymphocytes count and complete blood count.</text></s>
<s sid="32"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Despite a long-term administration of systemic/topical anti-fungals treatment (clotrimazole, 10mg troche given 5 times/day for 14 days, and voriconazole, 200mg tablet given twice/day, for 3 weeks), Phialemonium spp was still isolated in four consecutive cultures over the following year (days 1271, 1295, 1435, 1498).</text></s>
<s sid="33"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Systemic anti-fungal therapy was eventually discontinued due to severe allergic skin reactions.</text></s>
<s sid="34"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>After attempting to treat the fungal infection medically for 12 months, the patient underwent a fifth tympanomastoidectomy.</text></s>
<s sid="35"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>This procedure was done through a canal-wall-down (CWD) approach.</text></s>
<s sid="36"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Intra-operatively, there was a small amount of cholesteatoma.</text></s>
<s sid="37"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>Significant swelling and inflammation of the middle ear mucosa were also observed.</text></s>
<s sid="38"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>In post-operative monthly visits, the patient reported significant improvement of the right otalgia and otorrhea.</text></s>
<s sid="39"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>As expected, the mastoid bowl was epithelialized within 3 months.</text></s>
<s sid="40"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>No further surgical procedures were carried out, and no post-operative CT studies were performed.</text></s>
<s sid="41"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" type="Obs"/><text>At 18-months postoperative follow-up, all cultures from the right ear have been negative for Phialemonium spp.</text></s>
Discussion
<s sid="42"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We present an unusual case of CSOM in an immunocompetent patient presenting with persistent fungal otorrhea.</text></s>
<s sid="43"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>The isolated mold, Phialemonium, is an extremely rare human pathogen.</text></s>
<s sid="44"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>To our knowledge, this is the first report of such an infection in the ear.</text></s>
<s sid="45"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We describe a confined local Phialemonium infection in the tympanomastoid cavity without any systemic manifestations.</text></s>
<s sid="46"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Unlike other cases of CSOM-associated otomycosis, the patient׳s fungal infection was eradicated only after more aggressive treatment.</text></s>
Phialemonium spp.
<s sid="47"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>was first described as a human pathogen in 1986 (7).</text></s>
<s sid="48"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>Widely distributed in the environment, Phialemonium species have been isolated from air, soil, industrial water, and sewage.</text></s>
<s sid="49"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Although these species rarely cause human disease, this fungal infection can be fatal (9).</text></s>
<s sid="50"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Due to its affinity to the endovascular system, Phialemonium spreads in the blood stream and can eventually cause endocarditis.</text></s>
<s sid="51"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>To date, most of the reported Phialemonium infections cases manifested as systemic disease in immunocompromised patients and were associated with a high mortality rate.</text></s>
<s sid="52"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>We hypothesize two potential sources for this patient׳s Phialemonium inoculation.</text></s>
<s sid="53"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" type="Res"/><text>First, his extensive history of animal contact puts him at greater risk for soil-borne pathogens [4].</text></s>
<s sid="54"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Second, his exposure to lake water while swimming may have exposed him to Phialemonium as contaminated water is a common culture site [5].</text></s>
<s sid="55"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These risk factors combined with an increased susceptibility to secondary fungal infections after chronic antibiotic therapy greatly increased the patient׳s chance of becoming infected with Phialemonium.</text></s>
<s sid="56"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In the CWD procedure, the posterior wall of the external auditory canal is removed in order to create a single cavity mastoid bowl open to outside air.</text></s>
<s sid="57"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>This procedure externalizes the middle ear disease and gives chronic conditions, such as cholesteatoma, a pathway out of the closed middle ear cavity.</text></s>
<s sid="58"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In pediatric CSOM cases, efforts are made to avoid this radical procedure.</text></s>
<s sid="59"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Post-operative disadvantages include repeated external auditory canal and mastoid bowl cleaning, avoidance of water exposure, and possible hearing changes.</text></s>
<s sid="60"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>These can often severely affect the quality of life of a young child.</text></s>
<s sid="61"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Thus many surgeons usually tend to choose the less aggressive CWU mastoidectomy approach early in the disease course.</text></s>
<s sid="62"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The described patient received the standard of care for CSOM.</text></s>
<s sid="63"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Each acute episode was promptly treated with antibiotic therapy, debriding and cleansing.</text></s>
<s sid="64"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>The four CWU procedures were indicated by the presence of cholesteatoma as observed during EUA, clinic examination and imaging studies.</text></s>
<s sid="65"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>However, the course of CSOM in this patient was complicated by the co-existence of a rare fungal infection.</text></s>
<s sid="66"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Initially the Phialemonium infection was treated with topical anti-fungal therapy; systemic anti-fungal were added.</text></s>
<s sid="67"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>Late in the disease course a CWD tympanomastoidectomy was warranted after the patient continued to experience otorrhea, severe otalgia, residual cholesteatoma foci and repeated Phialemonium cultures.</text></s>
<s sid="68"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>With so little known about effective treatment methods for otic Phialemonium infections, further long-term follow-up is very important.</text></s>
<s sid="69"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>In our patient, eradication of the fungal infection was achieved only after the CWD tympanomastoidectomy procedure.</text></s>
<s sid="70"><CoreSc1 advantage="None" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" type="Con"/><text>We propose that early radical surgical intervention for the treatment of CSOM-associated Phialemonium infections may shorten the disease course.</text></s>
</BODY>
<OTHER>
Conflict of interest
There are none.
Acknowledgments
None.

</OTHER>
</PAPER>